<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!-- Template Version 1.1 [FOR REFERENCE - DO NOT DELETE] -->
<!-- This template is intended to be used as a starting point for encoding a new text.
        It is not intended as a fixed structure, but rather collects some of the most common
        structural elements for convenience and uniformity. Please add/remove elements as
        necessary for your use case. -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <!-- File Description -->
        <fileDesc>
            <!-- Title of the work -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Indicator</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                    <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                    <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <p />
            </publicationStmt>

            <!-- Author information -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>
                        <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                        <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                        <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                    </author>,
                    <title>The Indicator</title>
                    <date when="1820-04-12">April 12th, 1820</date> <!-- The publication date of this issue ({Month} {Day}, {Year}) -->
                    <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher> <!-- Publisher details if available -->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <!-- Encoding Description -->
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
            <p>
                Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers are
                included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
                preservation.
            </p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <!-- Profile Description -->
        <profileDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="issue" n="27">
                <pb n="209" /> <!-- Page beginning -->
                <div2 type="title"> <!-- Title, epigraph, and catalogue -->
                    <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                    <epigraph>
                        <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
                        <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                        <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
                        <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055"
                                cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                    </epigraph>
                    <head type="catalogue">No. XXVII.—WEDNESDAY, April 12th, 1820.</head>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="1"> <!-- Header and content -->
                    <head type="header">The Adventures of Cephalus and Procris.</head>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Cephalus</hi>, the son of Deioneus, king of Thessaly, married Procris,
                        daughter of Pandion, king of Athens. They bound each other by a
                        vow never to love any one else. Cephalus, who was fond of hunting,
                        suffered the wood-nymphs to be charming to no purpose; and Procris,
                        waiting his return every day from the <choice><corr>chase</corr><sic>chace</sic></choice>, scarcely had a civil answer
                        for the most agreeable of the Wood-Gods. </p>
                    <p>Their security in each others exclusive attachment was increased, if
                        possible, by a passion which was conceived for Cephalus by Aurora,
                        the Goddess of Morning. To think that the beaming eyes and rosy
                        blushes of so charming a deity were upon him every morning to no
                        purpose, was a high exaltation to the proud confidence which each
                        reposed in the other. Procris, whom the very particular vow which
                        they had entered into had begun to render a little too apt to be jealous,
                        concluded that if he could deny a goddess, she need have no fear of
                        the nymphs. All that disturbed her was lest Aurora should grow
                        angry. Cephalus, on the other hand, whatever airs he might occasionally
                        give himself on the strength of his fidelity, held it to be
                        utterly impossible, that his wife should for a moment forget the
                        rejecter of a divinity. </p>
                    <p>Aurora however was not angry. She was too much in love. Cephalus
                        began to feel a softer pride when he found that she still loved him
                        secretly, and that she did all in her power to gratify him. The dawns
                        in Thessaly had never been known to be so fine. Rosy little clouds,
                        floating in yellow light, were sure to usher in the day, whatever it
                        might turn out at noon. He had but to wish for more air, and it came
                        streaming upon his face. Did he want light in a gloomy depth of the
                        forest? Beams thrilled through the twisted thickets, and made the
                        hunters start to see their faces so plainly. Some said, that a divine
                        countenance was to be seen at these times, passing on the other side of
                        the trees, and looking through. It is certain, that when Cephalus had
                        lain down towards noon to rest himself in a solitary place, he would
                        see, as he woke, a nymph suddenly departing from the spot, whose
                        hair shook out a kind of sunshine, He knew that this was Aurora,
                        and could not help being touched by so delicate an aflection. </p>
                        <pb n="210" />
                        <p>By degrees, Cephalus began to think that Procris might spare a little
                            of so great a love; and as these wicked thoughts stole upon him, he
                            found Aurora steal nearer. She came closer to him, as he pretended
                            to sleep; and loitered more in going away. At length they conversed
                            again; and the argument, which was uppermost in both their minds,
                            soon got more and more explicit. We are bound to believe that a
                            goddess could reason more divinely on the subject; but it must not
                            be concealed, that the argument which made the greatest impression
                            on Cephalu, was one, which has since been much in fashion, though
                            we cannot say a great deal for it. All defences of love should proceed
                            upon the kindest grounds, or on none. The moment it refers to
                            anything like retaliation, or even to a justice which hazards such
                            feelings, it is trenching on the monstrous territory of hate. Be this
                            however as it may, Aurora, one morning, did certainly condescend to
                            finish a conversation with saying, that she would not look to have her
                            love returned, unless Procris should first be found unfaithful. </p>
                        <p>The husband, in whose mind this suggestion seemed to awaken all
                            his exclusive tenderness for his wife, readily accepted the alternative.
                            But how was Procris to be tried? Aurora soon found an expedient.
                            She changed the appearance of Cephalus to that of a young Phoenician
                            merchant; filled his pockets with gold and jewels; hung the rarest
                            gems from Ormus and the Red Sea in his turban; and seating him in
                            a Sidonian ear, drawn by white fawns, with a peacock standing beside
                            him on the edge, sent him to offer all these bribes to Procris for her
                            love. Cephalus turned a little pale at sight of the fawns; but his
                            colour and even his gaiety returned in a minute; and taking a respectful
                            farewell of the Goddess, he shook the reins, and set off down the
                            grassy valley that led to his home. </p>
                        <p>The fawns, with a yearning yet easy swiftness, wound along down
                            the sides of the hill. Their snowy figures flashed in and out of the
                            trees; the peacock's tail trailed along the air; the jewels sparkled in
                            the stranger's turban. Procris, looking out of the window for her
                            husband, wondered what illustrious unknown was coming. He is
                            evidently coming towards her abode. It is the only one in the valley.
                            He arrives, and making a respectful obeisance, alights and enters. He
                            makes no request for admittance, but yet no fault is to be found with
                            his easy gravity. He says indeed that he could not but come in,
                            whether he would or no, for the fame of Procris's beauty and sweetness
                            had reached him in Phoenicia; and as his father's great riches
                            allowed him to travel at his leisure, he had brought a few trifles,—not
                            as a return for the few hours' hospitality which he should presume
                            upon;—by no means;—but solely as he had not wit or attraction
                            enough of his own, to leave any other memorial of his visit and homage.
                            All this was somewhat too elaborate for the people in those days; but
                            Cephalus, in his confidence, had become a little over-ingenious; and
                            when he had done speaking, and had presented his splendid credentials,
                            Procris thought that the accomplished stranger undervalued himself.
                            A little obstacle presented itself. On giving her the peacock, the
                            handsome stranger stooped his face with an air of confident but respectful
                            pleasure, and was about to kiss her. <said>How is this?</said> said
                            <pb n="211" />Procris. <said>We always do so in Phoenicia,</said> said he, <said>when presents
                            are received;</said> and without more ado, he kissed her in a sort of formal
                            and cabalistic manner, first on one cheek, then on the other, and
                            lastly on the forehead. Procris submitted, purely because she did
                            not know how to object to a Phoenician custom. But on his presenting
                            a casket full of gold, she demurred. He seemed to take no notice
                            of this, but stooped as before, and kissed her, not only on the cheeks
                            and forehead, but on the lips. Procris blushed, and looked displeased.
                            <said >We always do so in Phoenecia;</said> said he, in a tone, as if all offence
                            must be done away by that explanation. Another casket succeeded,
                            full of jewels, and much more precious than the last. Procris wondered
                            whether any additional ceremony was to take place in return,
                            and was about to decline the third present in some alarm, when the
                            stranger, with as brief an indifference of voice as his gallantry could
                            assume, observed, that all that was to be done for the third gift, was to
                            have the kiss returned,—slightly, it was true; but still returned:—it
                            was always the way in Phoenicia. And he had scarcely spoken the
                            word when he stooped as before, and kissed her. Procris would sincerely
                            have objected to returning the salute; but as she said afterwards,
                            she really had not time to consider. Besides, she persuaded
                            herself that she felt relieved at thinking the casket was to be the last
                            present; and so,—giving a short glance at the window,—the kiss was
                            returned. A very odd, and not comfortable expression passed over
                            the face of the stranger, but very quickly. The only reason that
                            Procris could conceive why he should look so, was, that the salute
                            might have been too slight. <q type="thought">He is very generous, I own,</q> thought,
                            she; <q type="thought">but these Phoenicians are strange people.</q> The stranger had
                            now a totally different air. It was that of an excessive gaiety, in
                            which respect was nevertheless strongly mingled. <said>Having honoured
                            me so far with your acquaintance,</said> said he, <said>nothing remains but to
                            close our Phoenician ceremonies of introduction with this trifle from
                            the Red Sea.</said> So saying, he took a most magnificent ruby from the
                            front of his turban, and hitched it on the collar of her vest. <said >The
                            hook,</said> said he, <said>is of Phoenician chrystal.</said> Procris's ears fairly
                            tingled with the word Phoenician. She was bewildered; the ceremonies
                            were indeed about to close; and this word somewhat relieved
                            her; but she was going to demur in a more peremptory manner, when
                            he said that all that was to be done on this final occasion was just to
                            embrace him—slightly—in a sisterly way;—<said >It is not always done,</said>
                            said he:—<said>the Tyre people, for instance, do not do it; but the Sidonians
                            do; and generally speaking, it is the closing custom in Phoenici—</said>—and
                            the final syllable was lost in a new kiss, against which
                            she found it out of her power to remonstrate. In giving her at the
                            same time a brief but affectionate embrace, he contrived to bring her
                            arms about himself. He then bowed in the most respectful and grateful
                            manner imaginable, and handed her to a seat. </p>
                        <p>Procris, with whom the ice had been thus broken, and who already
                            thought herself half faithless to the strictness of her vow, scarcely
                            knew whether to feel more angry at the warmth, or piqued at the
                            ceremonious indiiference, of the stranger. A sense however of gratified 
                            <pb n="212" />pride, and of his extraordinary generosity, was the uppermost
                            feeling in her mind; and this led her to be piqued rather than angry.
                            Luckily, she bethought herself of offering him the hospitality of the
                            house, which helped to divert her confusion. The milk and fruit
                            were brought out; and he tasted them, more, it seemed, out of politeness,
                            than for want of refreshment. Procris cast her eyes, first up
                            the hill, and then at the fawns. She wondered whether the fawns and
                            car would follow the other presents; but upon the whole concluded
                            they would not, unless the traveller meant to stop, which was impossible;
                            at least in that house. She made up her mind therefore to be
                            very angry in case he should offer the fawns; when he interrupted
                            any farther reflections. <said >Those fawns,</said> said he, <said>came into my
                            possession in a remarkable manner. They are fatal.</said> <said >Fatal?</said>
                            echoed Procris. <said >Not in a bad sense,</said> returned the stranger, smiling:<said>
                            I am destined to present them to some fair one, (I know not
                            who she is), who shall honour me with the privileges of a husband,
                            and who is to be fairer than the Goddess that gave- them me."</said> <said >A
                            strange impossible condition,</said> said Procris; <said>but who, pray was the
                            Goddess?</said>—<said >Aurora.</said>—The beautiful wife of Cephalus smiled victoriously
                            at the mention of that name. She had already triumphed
                            over the divinity, and thought that this new test of superiority was
                            scarcely necessary. The Phoenician, upon seeing her turn of countenance,
                            added significantly; <said >I saw her just now, and must confess
                            that it will take something very extraordinary to surpass her; but I
                            do not conceive it actually impossible.</said> Procris longed to tell him of
                            Aurora's unsuccessful passion for Cephalus. She asked how long it
                            was, since he had seen the Goddess. <said>I saw her but now,</said> said the
                            stranger: <said>she was conversing in the forest here.</said> <said>Do you know
                            with whom?</said> asked Procris, <said>Oh yes; it was your husband: and
                            this reminds me, that he told me to beg you not to be alarmed, but
                            he should not return till night-fall.</said> <said> Not till night-fall?</said> half
                            murmured and half enquired the fair conqueror of Aurora.—Now this
                            was wrong in Cephalus. He was led into the mention of his interview
                            with Aurora by it's being actually the case; but he need not have
                            gone so far with the lesson she had taught him. We blush to say that
                            it succeeded but too well. There is no necessity to pursue the detail
                            farther. Towards night-fall Procris gave anxious looks up the hill,
                            and hoped (which was kind of her) that her husband might receive
                            great pleasure from the present she intended to make him of the
                            fawns. <said>I think he is coming down the hill,</said> said she. <said>No,</said> said
                            the stranger. <said>How can you tell,</said> returned Procris, <said>with your
                            face turned from the window?</said> <said>Look at me,</said> replied he, <said>and
                            you will know.</said> Procris turned quickly, and looked him in the face.
                            It was Cephalus himself. Astonishment, fear, shame, and a sense of
                            the triumphant artifice of the Goddess, fell upon her at once. She
                            uttered a loud shriek; and tearing her vest from her husband's grasp,
                            darted off into the woods. </p>
                        <p>Cephalus, in his chariot of fawns, sought her a hundred ways in
                            vain. He was at once angry and sorry: and Aurora found that her
                            artifice had been of no use. She hoped however that time, and the
                            <pb n="213" />absence of his wife, would mollify him; and in the mean while, seeing
                            how sullenly he turned aside whenever she ventured to become manifest,
                            she tried to humble him a little. His skill became less supereminent
                            in the <choice><corr>chase</corr><sic>chace</sic></choice>. Other dogs ran faster than his; and other
                            lances took truer aim. The gloom of the forest was still enlightened
                            for him, because she did not wish to let him know how she was trying
                            him; but the name of Cephalus suffered in it's reputation. People
                            began to say that Phalerus was as good as he. </p>
                        <p>He was sitting at home one evening in a melancholy manner, after
                            an unsuccessful day's sport, when a beautiful female with a dog appeared
                            at the door, and begged permission to rest herself. The faintness
                            of her voice interested our suffering huntsman. He brought her
                            in with great kindness, set refreshments before her, and could not help
                            gazing with admiration on her lovely face, which covered with blushes,
                            looked with a particularly melancholy expression on the fruits and
                            the bowls of cream. He thought he distressed her, and began playing
                            in a negligent manner with the dog. The animal, at a slight snap of
                            his fingers, darted up on his legs like lightning, and stood panting
                            and looking eagerly towards the door. Cephalus had the finest dogs
                            in Thessaly, yet he doubted whether this was not finer than any of
                            them. He looked at the female, and now saw that she was buskined
                            up like a nymph of the <choice><corr>chase</corr><sic>chace</sic></choice>. <said>The truth flashes upon me,</said> thought
                            he; <said>this is a fugitive nymph of Diana. Her buskins and her blushes
                            tell her whole story.</said> The fair stranger seemed first oppressed, and
                            then relieved by his gaze. <said>You guess,</said> said she, <said>but too well, I
                            fear, what has put me upon your kind hospitality. But the other
                            sex, especially where they are of the best natures, will be too kind to
                            betray me. I have indeed fled from the company of Diana, having
                            been first left myself by a River-God, who</said>—She blushed, and was
                            silent. <said>And this dog?</said> enquired Cephalus, after reassuring her.
                            <said>It was my favourite dog in the <choice><corr>chase</corr><sic>chace</sic></choice>,</said> said she; <said>now my faithful
                            companion in flight. Poor Lailaps!</said> And the dog, forgetting his
                            vivacity in an instant, came and lay at his mistress's feet, as if he
                            would have wound about them. They were very beautiful feet.
                            <q type="thought">The River-God doubtless admired them,</q> thought Cephalus. But
                            there was a something in her face more touching than all the shapeliness
                            in the world. It was a mixture of the pensive and the pleasurable,
                            which seemed to say that if she had no cause for trouble, she would
                            have been all tender vivacity. <said>And whither are you going, fairest?</said>
                            asked Cephalus. <said>To Cyprus.</said>—<said>To the temple of Venus?</said>—<said>To
                            the temple of Venus:</said> replied the beautiful stranger, dropping
                            her words and face as she spoke. <said>I have made a new vow, which—a
                            new vow.</said> And blushing more deeply, she was again silent.—<said>Which
                            she shall be able to keep better then the last,</said> thought Cephalus.
                            She sat in a simple posture, her back gently bending, her
                            knees together, her rosy face and languid eyes looking down sideways
                            between her dark heavy curls. She moved the fingers of her right hand
                            towards the dog, as if snapping them; but it was done faintly, and evidently
                            only to do something. Cephalus thought she had a look of
                            Procris; and he did not pity her the less for that. <said>But what
                            <pb n="214" />are you to do with this dog?</said> This, it seemed, was a very perplexing
                            question. It was a long time before Cephalus could get an answer;
                            but he was so kind and importunate, and really, with all his love of
                            hunting, appeared to be so much more interested in the nymph than
                            her companion, that at length he did obtain a sort of understanding
                            on the subject. It was necessary to make a renouncement of something
                            highly valued by the possessor, before a new devotee could enter
                            on the service of Venus. The renouncement was to be made to one
                            of the other sex; and Cephalus, partly out of curiosity, partly out of
                            vanity, partly out of self-interest, and not a little out of an interest
                            of a better sort, contrived to discover, that it would be made, with
                            no prodigious unwillingness, to himself. <said>Lailaps,</said> said he. The
                            dog started towards him, as if he knew his future master. The lady
                            gave a gentle laugh, and seemed much happier. The supper, that
                            evening, was upon a much easier footing than the luncheon. The
                            next morning, on waking, Cephalus, saw the face of Procris hanging
                            over him. He would have been more astonished had he not remembered
                            his own transformation. But he was nevertheless quite enough
                            so. Procris shook her head at him archly; then kissed him kindly;
                            then burst into tears; then declared herself happy and forgiving, as
                            well as forgiven; and neither of them ever passed a happier day in
                            their lives. </p>
                        <p>Procris's account of herself was partly true. Our informant<note type="hunt">
                            <bibl>
                                <author>
                                    [<forename>Gaius</forename>
                                    <forename>Julius</forename>]
                                    <surname>Hyginus</surname>
                                </author>,
                                <title>Fabularum Liber,</title>
                                <biblScope>Capitulum 189</biblScope>.
                            </bibl>
                        </note> does
                            not account for a proceeding which certainly requires some explanation;
                            but she had really gone to the haunts of Diana, whose reception
                            of her, though a huntress, was what might have been expected.
                            She begged, her, in very explicit terms, to withdraw. Procris,
                            however, though she could obtain no sympathy purely on her
                            own account, contrived to waken an interest in the bosom of the
                            divine virgin by telling her of the trick played by Cephalus and Aurora.
                            This she thought abominable. She therefore wrought a counter-change
                            in the appearance of Procris; and giving her a hound out
                            of her own pack, sent her to practise artifice for artifice. She regretted
                            afterwards the having consented to interfere at all in such
                            matters; but the impulse had engaged her to commit herself; and she
                            was too proud and stately to recall what she had done. Procris told
                            all to her husband; and the goddess was little aware how they enjoyed
                            the kind result of her anger, at the expense of her dignity. </p>
                        <p>It is on record, that our married couple were never so fond of each
                            other, or so contented, as now. Procris, in the gratitude of her joy,
                            was not disposed even to quarrel with Aurora, whom her husband no
                            doubt saw occasionally. But it is not known whether he was kinder
                            to her than before. Procris was inclined to think not, as he said
                            nothiing about it; so certain she had become of his confidence. As
                            to Cephalus, the praises of his wife by his fellow-huntsmen gave
                            him great pleasure, now that he was sure of her loving him unrestrictedly. </p>
                        <p>What a pity that such a happy state of things was not to last! But
                            Procris had early been taught jealousy. She had even identified it
                            <pb n="215" />with a virtue; and by degrees, as little fits of ill temper were exchanged,
                            and she began to think less kindly of herself, she began to
                            be uneasy about others. Unfortunately for this return of her complaint,
                            a little anxious busy-body, whom she had been accustomed to
                            treat with contemptuous indifference, perhaps to <choice><corr>show</corr><sic>shew</sic></choice> it too much,
                            came and said to her one day, that as she knew she should not be
                            mortifying her with such petty matters, she might tell her, as a piece
                            of news, that Cephalus was passionately and notoriously in love with
                            a beautiful nymph of the name of Aura. <said>Aurora, you mean,</said>
                            said Procris, scornfully. <said>No, no,</said> said the little snappish voice;
                            <said>Aura, Aura:—I know it well enough; all Athens knows it, or
                            else I should not have repeated it. I am no tale-bearer; but I hate
                            to see a man pretending to be what he is not.</said> <said>Cephalus pretends
                            nothing,</said>" said Procris. <said>Oh—of course,</said> said the gossip; <said>and
                            mighty useful it is to him no doubt, to be so wanting in pretence.
                            But my maxim is, Be decent enough, at least, to appear virtuous.</said>
                            <q type="thought">Yes,</q> thought Procris, <q type="thought">and your whole life would be an exemplification
                            of it, if you could hold your tongue.</q> But the blow was
                            struck. She despised the scandal, while she became <choice><corr>its</corr><sic>it's</sic></choice> victim. </p>
                        <p>Procris, who was on a visit with Cephalus to her father, had heard of a
                            spot, in which he reposed himself every day after the <choice><corr>chase</corr><sic>chace</sic></choice>. Here, it was
                            added, the lady as regularly met him. He was even so impatient for
                            her sight, that if she delayed a minute beyond the usual time, he
                            called upon her aloud, in the fondest manner. <said>Come, come, sweet
                            Aura,</said> said he, <said>and cool this glow in my bosom.</said>
                            Now his delight in the new spot, and the invocation also, were both
                            very true; only the informant forget to mention, and Procris to remember,
                            that although Aura was the name of a female, it also signified
                            the fresh air. </p>
                        <p>One day, Cephalus went as usual into his favourite haunt, to enjoy
                            <choice><corr>its</corr><sic>it's</sic></choice> freshness, verdure, and seclusion. The place has been very prettily
                            described by Ovid. </p>
                        <quote>
                            <lg>
                            <l>Est prope purpureos colles florentis Hymetti </l>
                            <l rend="indent">Fons sacer, et viridi cespite mollis humus. </l>
                            <l>Sylva nemus non alta facit: tegit arbutus herbam: </l>
                            <l rend="indent">Ros maris, et lauri, nigraque myrtus olent. </l>
                            <l>Nec densae foliis buxi, fragilesque myticae, </l>
                            <l rend="indent">Nec tenues cytisi, cultaque pinus abest. </l>
                            <l>Lenibus impulsae Zephyris, <hi rend="italic">aura</hi>que salubri, </l>
                            <l rend="indent">Tot generum frondes, herbaque summa tremunt. </l>
                            <note type="source">
                                <bibl>
                                    <author>Ovid</author>,
                                    <title>Ars Amatoria</title>
                                    <biblScope>Liber III, lines 687-94</biblScope>.
                                </bibl>
                            </note>
                        </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <lg type="translation-hunt">
                            <lg type="stanza">
                            <l>Close by the flowery purple hill </l>
                            <l rend="indent">Hymettus, may be found </l>
                            <l>A sacred fountain, and a plot </l>
                            <l rend="indent">Of green and lovely ground. </l>
                            </lg>
                            <lg type="stanza">
                            <l>'Tis in a copse. The strawberry </l>
                            <l rend="indent">Grows blushing through the grass; </l>
                            <l>And myrtle, rosemary, and bay </l>
                            <l rend="indent">Quite perfume all the place. </l>
                            </lg>
                            <lg type="stanza">
                            <l>Nor is the tamarisk wanting there; </l>
                            <l>Nor clumps of leafy box; </l>
                            <l>Ner slender cytisus; nor yet </l>
                            <l>The pine with <choice><corr>its</corr><sic>it's</sic></choice> proud locks. </l>
                            </lg>
                            <pb n="216" />
                            <lg type="stanza">
                                <l>Touched by the zephyrs and sweet airs, </l>
                                <l rend="indent">Which there in balm assemble, </l>
                                <l>This little world of leaves, and all </l>
                                <l rend="indent">The tops of the grass tremble. </l>
                            </lg>
                        </lg>
                    <p>Cephalus lay upon a slope of the velvet ground, his hands behind
                        his head, and his face towards the balmy heaven. He little thought
                        that Procris was near. She was lurking close to him behind some box-trees.
                        She listened. There was not a sound, but that of the fountain,
                        the noise of whose splashes was softened by the trees that half encircled
                        it. She listened again, thinking she heard her husband speak;—It was
                        only the fervid bees, buzzing along from Hymettus, and murmuring as
                        if disdainfully in her ear. A variety of feelings agitate her. Now she
                        is sorry that she came, and would have given any thing to be back
                        again. Now she longs to know who her rival is. Now she is sorry
                        again, and feels that her conduct is unworthy, let her husband's be
                        what it may. Now she reassures herself, and thinks, that he should
                        have at least been ingenuous. Jealousy and curiosity prevail, and she
                        still looks and listens. The air seems more then usually quiet; and
                        the bees worry her with their officious humming. Cephalus leaps up,
                        and plays idly with his javelin. Still nothing is said. Nobody appears.
                        She expects the lady every minute to issue from the trees; and thinks
                        how she shall confound her. But no one comes. At last, her husband
                        speaks. She parts the box-trees a little more, to listen the keener.
                        <said>Come, gentle Aura,</said> cried he, as if in a tone of reproach—<said>Come,
                        and breathe refreshment upon me:—thou scarcely stirrest the poplars
                        to day.</said> Procris leaped up in an extacy of delight and remorse, and
                        began tearing back the boughs to go to her husband. He starts up.
                        He thinks it a deer hampered in the thicket, and raises his javelin to
                        dart it. Forbear, forbear, miserable man: it is thy more miserable
                        wife! Alas! the javelin is thrown, and the wife pierced. Upon
                        coming up to secure his prey, he finds, with a dumb despair, that it
                        is Procris dying. She does not reproach him. She reproaches only
                        herself. <said>Forgive me,</said> said she, <said>dear Cephalus,</said> pressing her
                        cheek against his: <said>I was made wise in vain once, and I am now wise
                        again too late. Forgive my poor jealous heart, and bless me. It weeps
                        blood for it's folly.</said> And as she spoke, she sobbed aloud; and the penitent
                        tears gushed away, as if to emulate the gushing of her heart. Cephalus,
                        bewildered and agonized, uttered what kind and remorseful words
                        his lips could frame, pressing her all the while gently to his heart. He saw
                        that the wound was mortal, and it was quickly so. Her eyes faded away
                        while looking at him; but opening her lips, she still made a yearning
                        movement of them towards his. It reminded him of paying that affectionate
                        office to the departing spirit; and, stooping with a face washed
                        in tears, he put his mouth upon her's, and received at once her last
                        kiss and breath.
                    </p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="colophon"> <!-- Publisher and printer information -->
                    <p>Orders received by the Newsmen, by the Booksellers, and by the Publisher, Joseph Appleyard.</p>
                    <p>Printed by Joseph Appleyard, No. 19, Catherine-street, Strand,——Price 2d.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
  