<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!-- Template Version 1.1 [FOR REFERENCE - DO NOT DELETE] -->
<!-- This template is intended to be used as a starting point for encoding a new text.
        It is not intended as a fixed structure, but rather collects some of the most common
        structural elements for convenience and uniformity. Please add/remove elements as
        necessary for your use case. -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <!-- File Description -->
        <fileDesc>
            <!-- Title of the work -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Indicator</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                    <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                    <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <p>
                    This electronic edition is part of a larger project to digitize and make
                    accessible the complete run of Leigh Hunt's periodical, The Indicator.
                </p>
            </publicationStmt>

            <!-- Author information -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>
                        <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                        <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                        <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                    </author>,
                    <title level="j">The Indicator</title>
                    <date when="1820-01-12">January 12, 1820</date>
                    <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <!-- Encoding Description -->
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
            <p>
                Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers are
                included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
                preservation. Specific entities like persons, places, and literary works are
                identified and linked to external authorities where possible. Typographical errors
                are marked using &lt;choice&gt; tags with &lt;sic&gt; and &lt;corr&gt; elements.
                Old spellings are marked using &lt;choice&gt; tags with &lt;orig&gt; and &lt;reg&gt; elements.
            </p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <!-- Profile Description -->
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="issue" n="14">
                <pb n=""/> <!-- Unnumbered title page for the issue -->
                <div2 type="title">
                    <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                    <epigraph>
                        <lg>
                            <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
                            <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                            <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055" cert="high"
                                type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                    </epigraph>
                    <head type="catalogue">No. <hi rend="smallcaps">XIV</hi>.— <hi rend="smallcaps">WEDNESDAY</hi>,
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">JANUARY</hi> 12th, 1820.</head>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="1">
                    <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">A FEW THOUGHTS ON SLEEP.</head>
                    <p>This is an article for the reader to think of, when he or she is warm in bed, a
                        little before he goes to sleep, the clothes at his ear, and the wind moaning
                        in some distant crevice.</p>
                    <p><q type="spoken">Blessings</q>, exclaimed <persName key="Sancho Panza"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1994605" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Sancho</persName>, <q type="spoken">on him that first
                            invented sleep! It wraps a man all round like a cloak.</q> It is a
                        delicious moment certainly,—that of being well nestled in bed, and feeling
                        that you shall drop gently to sleep. The good is to come, not past: the
                        limbs have been just tired enough, to render the remaining in one posture
                        delightful: the labour of the day is done. A gentle failure of the
                        perceptions comes creeping over one:--the spirit of consciousness disengages
                        itself more and more, with slow and hushing degrees, like a mother detaching
                        her hand from that of her sleeping child;—the mind seems to have a balmy lid
                        closing over it, like the eye;—'tis closing; —'tis more closing;—'tis
                        closed. The mysterious spirit has gone to take it's airy rounds.</p>
                    <pb n="105"/>
                    <p>It is said that sleep is best before midnight: and <persName key="Nature"
                            type="personification">Nature</persName> herself, with her darkness and
                        chilling dews, informs us so. There is another reason for going to bed
                        betimes : for it is universally acknowledged that lying late in the morning
                        is a great shortener of life. At least, it is never found in company with
                        longevity. It also tends to make people corpulent. But these matters belong
                        rather to the subject of early rising, than of sleep.</p>
                    <p>Sleep at a late hour in the morning, is not half so pleasant as the more
                        timely one. It is sometimes however excusable, especially to a, watchful or
                        over-worked head; neither can we deny the seducing merits of <q
                            type="distinct">t' other doze</q>,— the pleasing wilfulness of nestling
                        in a new posture, when you know you ought to be up, like the rest of the
                        house. But then you cut up the day, and your sleep the next night.</p>
                    <p>In the course of the day, few people think of sleeping, except after dinner ;
                        and then it is often rather a hovering and nodding on the borders of sleep,
                        than a sleep itself. This is a privilege, allowable, we think, to none but
                        the old, or the sickly, or the very tired and care-worn ; and it should be
                        well understood, before it is exercised in company. To escape into slumber
                        from an argument; or to take</p>
                    <pb n="106"/>
                    <p>it as an affair of course, only between you and your biliary duct; or to
                        assent with involuntary nods to all that you have just been disputing <choice
                            ><sic>5</sic><corr>is</corr></choice> not so well: much less, to sit
                        nodding and tottering beside a lady; or to be in danger of dropping your
                        head into the fruit-plate or your host's face; or of waking up, and saying
                            <q type="spoken">Just so</q> to the bark of a dog, or <q type="spoken"
                            >Yes, Madam</q> to the black at your elbow.</p>
                    <p>Care-worn people however might refresh themselves oftener with day-sleep than
                        they do; if their bodily state is such as to dispose them to it. It is a
                        mistake to suppose that all care is wakeful. People sometimes sleep, as well
                        as wake, by reason of their sorrow. The difference seems to depend upon the
                        nature of their temperament ; though in the most excessive cases, sleep is
                        perhaps <persName key="Nature" type="personification">Nature's</persName>
                        never-failing relief, as swooning is upon the rack. A person with jaundice
                        in his blood shall lie down and go to sleep at noon-day, when another of a
                        different complexion shall find his eyes as uncloseable as a statue's,
                        though he has had no sleep for nights together. Without meaning to lesson
                        the dignity of suffering, which has quite enough to do with it's waking
                        hours, it is this that may often account for the profound sleeps enjoyed the
                        night before hazardous battles, executions, and other demands upon an
                        over-excited spirit.</p>
                    <p>The most complete and healthy sleep that can be taken in the day, is in
                        summer-time, out in a field. There is perhaps no solitary sensation so
                        exquisite as that of slumbering on the grass or hay, shaded from the hot sun
                        by a tree, with the consciousness of a fresh but light air running through
                        the wide atmosphere, and the sky stretching far overhead upon all sides.
                            <placeName type="physical">Earth</placeName>, and <placeName
                            type="physical">heaven</placeName>, and a placid humanity, seem to have
                        the creation to themselves. There is nothing between the slumberer, and the
                        naked and glad innocence of nature.</p>
                    <p>Next to this, but at a long interval, the <choice>
                            <sic>most, relishing</sic>
                            <corr>most relishing</corr>
                        </choice> snatch of slumber out of bed, is the one which a tired person
                        takes, before he retires for the night, while lingering in his sitting-room.
                        The consciousness of being very sleepy and of having the power to go to bed
                        immediately, gives great zest to the unwillingness to move. Sometimes he
                        sits nodding in his chair; but the sudden and leaden jerks of the head to
                        which a state of great sleepiness renders him liable, are generally too
                        painful for so luxurious a moment; and he gets into a more legitimate
                        posture, sitting sideways with his head on the chair-back, or throwing his
                        legs up at once on another chair, and half reclining. It is curious however
                        to find, how long an inconvenient posture will be borne for the sake of this
                        foretaste of repose. The worst of it is, that on going to bed, the charm
                        sometimes vanishes; perhaps from the colder temperature of the chamber; for a
                        fireside is a great opiate.</p>
                    <pb n="107"/>
                    <p>Speaking of the painful positions into which a sleepy lounger will get
                        himself, it is amusing to think of the more fantastic attitudes that so
                        often take place in bed. If we could add any thing to the numberless things
                        that have been said about sleep by the poets, it would be upon this point.
                            <persName key="Sleep (mythology)" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Sleep</persName> never shews himself a greater leveller. A man in his
                        waking moments may look as proud and self-possessed as he pleases. He may
                        walk proudly, he may sit proudly, he may eat his dinner proudly; he may
                        shave himself with an air of infinite superiority; in a word, he may shew
                        himself grand and absurd upon the most trifling occasions. But <persName
                            key="Sleep (mythology)" cert="high" type="mythological">Sleep</persName>
                        plays the petrifying magician. He arrests the proudest lord as well as the
                        humblest clown in the most ridiculous postures: so that if you could draw a
                        grandee from his bed without waking him, no limb-twisting fool in a
                        pantomime should create wilder laughter. The toy with the string between
                        it's legs is hardly a posture-master more extravagant. Imagine a despot
                        lifted up to the gaze of his valets, with his eyes shut, his mouth open, his
                        left hand under his right ear, his other twisted and hanging helplessly
                        before him like an ideot's, one knee lifted up, and the other leg stretched
                        out, or both knees huddled up together; what a scarecrow to lodge majestic
                        power in!</p>
                    <p>But <persName key="Sleep (mythology)" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Sleep</persName> is kindly, even in his tricks; and the poets have
                        treated him with proper reverence. According to the ancient mythologists, he
                        had even one of the <persName key="Graces (mythology)" type="mythological"
                            >Graces</persName> to wife. He had a thousand sons, of whom the chief
                        were <persName key="Morpheus" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Morpheus</persName>, or the <emph>Shaper</emph>; <persName key="Icelos"
                            cert="high" type="mythological">Icelos</persName>, or the <emph>Likely</emph>;
                            <persName key="Phantasus" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Phantasus</persName>, the <emph>Fancy</emph>; and <persName
                            key="Phobetor" cert="high" type="mythological">Phobetor</persName>, the
                            <emph>Terror</emph>. His dwelling some writers place in a dull and
                        darkling part of the earth; others, with greater compliment, in <placeName
                            type="physical">heaven</placeName>; and others, with another kind of
                        propriety, by the <placeName type="physical">sea-shore</placeName>. There
                        is a good description of it in <persName key="Ovid"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q12196" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Ovid</persName>; but in these abstracted tasks of poetry, the moderns
                        outvie the ancients; and there is nobody who has built his bower for him so
                        finely as <persName key="Edmund Spenser"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Spenser</persName>. <persName key="Archimago" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Archimago</persName> in the first book of the <title
                            level="m" key="The Faerie Queene"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1212871">Faery Queen</title>,
                        (Canto 1, St. 39.) sends a little spirit down to <persName key="Morpheus"
                            cert="high" type="mythological">Morpheus</persName> to fetch him a
                        Dream.</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l>He, making speedy way through spersed ayre,</l>
                                <l>And through the world of waters, wide and <choice><orig>deepe</orig><reg>deep</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>To <persName key="Morpheus" cert="high" type="mythological"
                                        >Morpheus'</persName> house <choice><orig>doth</orig><reg>does</reg></choice> hastily <choice><orig>repaire</orig><reg>repair</reg></choice>.</l>
                                <l>Amid the bowels of the earth full <choice><orig>steepe</orig><reg>steep</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>And low, where dawning day <choice><orig>doth</orig><reg>does</reg></choice> never <choice><orig>peepe</orig><reg>peep</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>His dwelling is. There, <persName key="Tethys" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological">Tethys</persName> his wet bed</l>
                                <l><choice><orig>Doth</orig><reg>Does</reg></choice> ever wash; and
                                    <persName key="Cynthia (mythology)" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological">Cynthia</persName> still <choice><orig>doth</orig><reg>does</reg></choice>
                                    <choice><orig>steepe</orig><reg>steep</reg></choice></l>
                                <l>In silver dew his <choice><orig>ever-drouping</orig><reg>ever-drooping</reg></choice> head,</l>
                                <l>Whiles sad <persName key="Night (mythology)"
                                        type="personification">Night</persName> over him her mantle
                                    black <choice><orig>doth</orig><reg>does</reg></choice>
                                    <choice><orig>spred</orig><reg>spread</reg></choice>.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl><author>Edmund Spenser</author>, <title level="m">The Faerie
                                    Queene</title>, <biblScope unit="book">Book 1</biblScope>,
                                <biblScope unit="canto">Canto 1</biblScope>, <biblScope
                                    unit="stanza">Stanza 39</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <pb n="108"/>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l>And more to lull him in his <choice><orig>slumber</orig><reg>slumbers</reg></choice> soft</l>
                                <l>A trickling <choice><orig>streame</orig><reg>stream</reg></choice>
                                    from high <choice><orig>rocke</orig><reg>rock</reg></choice>
                                    tumbling <choice><orig>downe</orig><reg>down</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>And <choice><orig>ever-dringling</orig><reg>ever-drizzling</reg></choice> rain upon the loft,</l>
                                <l>Mixed with a murmuring winde, much like the <choice><orig>soune</orig><reg>sound</reg></choice></l>
                                <l>Of swarming bees, did cast him in a <choice><orig>swoune</orig><reg>swoon</reg></choice>.</l>
                                <l>No other noise, nor people's troublous <choice><orig>cryes</orig><reg>cries</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>As still are wont to annoy the walled <choice><orig>towne</orig><reg>town</reg></choice>.</l>
                                <l>Might there be heard, but carelesse <persName key="Quiet"
                                        type="personification">Quiet</persName>
                                    <choice><orig>lyes</orig><reg>lies</reg></choice>.</l>
                                <l>Wrapt in eternall silence, farre from <choice><orig>enimyes</orig><reg>enemies</reg></choice>.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl><author>Edmund Spenser</author>, <title level="m">The Faerie
                                    Queene</title>, <biblScope unit="book">Book 1</biblScope>,
                                <biblScope unit="canto">Canto 1</biblScope>, <biblScope
                                    unit="stanza">Stanza 40</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p><persName key="Geoffrey Chaucer" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5663"
                            cert="high" type="real">Chaucer</persName> has drawn the cave of the
                        same god with greater simplicity; but nothing can have a more deep and
                        sullen effect than his cliffs and cold running waters. It seems as real as an
                        actual solitude, or some quaint old picture in a book of travels in
                            <placeName key="Tartary" cert="high" type="region">Tartary</placeName>.
                        He is telling the story of <persName key="Ceyx" cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Ceyx</persName> and <persName key="Alcyone"
                            cert="high" type="mythological">Alcyone</persName> in the poem called
                        his <title level="m" key="The Book of the Duchess"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2078651">Dream</title>. <persName
                            key="Juno" cert="high" type="mythological">Juno</persName> tells a
                        messenger to go to <persName key="Morpheus" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Morpheus</persName> and <q type="spoken">bid him creep into</q></p>
                    <pb n="108"/>
                    <p>the body<q type="spoken"> of the drowned king, to let his wife know the fatal
                            event by his apparition.</q></p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l>This messenger <choice><orig>tooke</orig><reg>took</reg></choice> leave, and went</l>
                                <l>Upon his way; and never he <choice><orig>stent</orig><reg>stint</reg></choice></l>
                                <l>Till he came to the dark valley,</l>
                                <l>That <choice><orig>stant</orig><reg>stands</reg></choice>
                                    betweene <choice><orig>rockes</orig><reg>rocks</reg></choice>
                                    <choice><orig>twey</orig><reg>two</reg></choice>.</l>
                                <l>There never yet grew <choice><orig>corne</orig><reg>corn</reg></choice>, ne <choice><orig>gras</orig><reg>grass</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>Ne tree, ne <choice><orig>nought</orig><reg>naught</reg></choice>
                                    that <choice><orig>aught</orig><reg>aught</reg></choice> was,</l>
                                <l>Beast ne man, ne <choice><orig>naught</orig><reg>naught</reg></choice> else;</l>
                                <l>Save that there were a few <choice><orig>wells</orig><reg>wells</reg></choice></l>
                                <l>Came running fro the the cliffs <choice><orig>adowne</orig><reg>down</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>That made a deadly sleeping <choice><orig>soune</orig><reg>sound</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>And runnen <choice><orig>downe</orig><reg>down</reg></choice>
                                    right by a cave,</l>
                                <l>That was under a <choice><orig>rocke</orig><reg>rock</reg></choice>
                                    <choice><orig>ygrave</orig><reg>engraved</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>Amid the valley, wonder-<choice><orig>deepe</orig><reg>deep</reg></choice>.</l>
                                <l>There these <choice><orig>goddis</orig><reg>gods</reg></choice>
                                    lay <choice><orig>asleepe</orig><reg>asleep</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l><persName key="Morpheus" cert="high" type="mythological"
                                        >Morpheus</persName> and <persName key="Eclympasteire"
                                        cert="high" type="mythological"
                                        >Eclynipasteire</persName>,</l>
                                <l>That was the god of <persName key="Sleep (mythology)"
                                        cert="high" type="mythological">Sleepis</persName>
                                    <choice><orig>heire</orig><reg>heir</reg></choice>,</l>
                                <l>That slept and did none other <choice><orig>worke</orig><reg>work</reg></choice>.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl><author>Geoffrey Chaucer</author>, <title level="m">The Book of
                                    the Duchess</title>, <biblScope unit="line">lines
                                    153-169</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p>Where the credentials of this new son and heir, <persName
                            key="Eclympasteire" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Eclympasteire</persName>, are to be found, we know not; but he acts
                        very much, it must be allowed, like an heir presumptive, in sleeping, and
                        doing <q type="written">none other work.</q></p>
                    <p>We dare not trust ourselves with many quotations upon sleep from the poets;
                        they are so numerous as well as beautiful. We must content ourselves with
                        mentioning that our two most favourite passages are one in the <title
                            level="m" key="Philoctetes" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q928073"
                            cert="high">Philoctetes</title> of <persName key="Sophocles"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q43405" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Sophocles</persName>, admirable for it's contrast to a scene of
                        terrible agony, which it closes<note type="hunt"><bibl>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">We do not translate it here, as we intend to
                                    present the reader with the whole scene in an article upon
                                        <title level="a">Philoctetes</title>.</hi>
                            </bibl></note>: and the other the following address in <persName
                            key="Francis Beaumont" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q310636"
                            cert="high" type="real">Beaumont</persName> and <persName
                            key="John Fletcher" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q455799"
                            cert="high" type="real">Fletcher's</persName> tragedy of <title
                            level="m" key="Valentinian (play)"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q7910906" cert="high"
                            >Valentinian</title>, the hero of which is also a sufferer under bodily
                        torment. He is in a chair, slumbering; and these most exquisite lines are
                        gently sung with music.</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l>Care-charming <persName key="Sleep (mythology)" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological">Sleep</persName>, thou easer of all
                                    woes,</l>
                                <l>Brother to <persName key="Death (personification)"
                                        type="personification">Death</persName>, sweetly thyself
                                    dispose</l>
                                <l>On this afflicted <persName key="Valentinian" cert="high"
                                        type="fictional">prince</persName>. Fall like a cloud</l>
                                <l>In gentle showers: give nothing that is loud</l>
                                <l>Or painful to his slumbers: easy, light,</l>
                                <l>And as a purling stream, thou son of, <persName key="Night (mythology)"
                                        type="personification">Night</persName>,</l>
                                <l>Pass by his troubled senses: sing his pain</l>
                                <l>Like hollow murmuring wind, or silver rain:</l>
                                <l>Into this <persName key="Valentinian" cert="high"
                                        type="fictional">prince</persName>, gently, oh gently
                                    slide;</l>
                                <l>And kiss him into slumbers, like a bride.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl>
                                <author>Francis Beaumont</author> and <author>John Fletcher</author>,
                                <title level="m">Valentinian</title>, <biblScope unit="act"
                                    >Act 5</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="scene">Scene
                                    2</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p>How earnest and prayer-like are these pauses! How lightly sprinkled, and yet
                        how deeply settling, like rain, the fancy! How quiet, affectionate, and
                        perfect the conclusion!</p>
                    <p><persName key="Sleep (mythology)" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Sleep</persName> is most graceful in an infant; soundest, in one who
                        has been tired in the open air; completest, to the seaman after a hard
                        voyage; most welcome, to the mind haunted with one idea; most touching to
                        look at, in the parent that has wept; lightest, in the playful child;
                        proudest, in the bride adored.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="2">
                    <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">THE FAIR REVENGE.</head>
                    <p>The elements of this story are to be found in the old poem called <title
                            level="m" key="Albion's England"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4712431" cert="high"
                            >Albion's England</title>, to which we referred in the article on
                            <persName key="Charles Brandon"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q881347" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Charles Brandon</persName> and <persName key="Mary Tudor, Queen of France"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q232336" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Mary Queen of France</persName>,</p>
                    <p><persName key="Aganippus" cert="high" type="fictional"
                            >Aganippus</persName>, king of <placeName key="Argos"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q189568" cert="high" type="city"
                            >Argos</placeName>, dying without heirs male, bequeathed his throne to
                        his only daughter, the beautiful and beloved <persName key="Daphles"
                            cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName>. This female succession
                        was displeasing to a nobleman who held large possessions on the frontiers;
                        and he came for the first time towards the court, not to pay his respects to
                        the new queen, but to give her battle. <persName key="Doracles" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Doracles</persName> (for that was his name) was not
                        much known by the people. He had distinguished himself for as jealous an
                        independence as a subject could well assume; and though he had been of use
                        in repelling invasion during the latter years of the king, had never made
                        his appearance to receive his master's thanks personally. A correspondence
                        however was understood to have gone on between him and several noblemen
                        about the court ; and there were those, who in spite of his inattention to
                        popularity, suspected that it would go hard with the young queen, when the
                        two armies came face to face.</p>
                    <pb n="109"/>
                    <p>But neither these subtle statesmen, nor the ambitious young soldier
                            <persName key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>,
                        were aware of the effects to be produced by a strong personal attachment.
                        The young queen, amiable as she was beautiful, had involuntarily baffled his
                        expectations from her courtiers, by exciting in the minds of some a real
                        disinterested regard, while others nourished a hope of sharing her throne
                        instead. At least, they speculated upon becoming, each the favourite
                        minister; and held it a better thing to reign under that title and a
                        charming mistress, than be the servants of a master, wilful and domineering.
                        By the people she was adored; and when she came riding out of her palace, on
                        the morning of the fight, with an unaccustomed spear standing up in it's
                        rest by her side, her diademed hair flowing a little off into the wind, her
                        face paler than usual, but still tinted with it's roses, and a look in which
                        confidence in the love of her subjects, and tenderness for the wounds they
                        were going to encounter, seemed to contend for the expression, —the shout
                        which they sent up would have told a stouter heart than a traitor's, that
                        the royal charmer was secure.</p>
                    <p>The queen, during the conflict, remained in a tent upon an eminence, to which
                        the younger leaders vied who should best spur up their smoking horses, to
                        bring her good news from time to time. The battle was short and bloody.
                            <persName key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>
                        soon found that he had miscalculated his point; and all his skill and
                        resolution could not set the error to rights. It was allowed, that if either
                        courage or military talent could entitle him to the throne, he would have
                        had a right to it; but the popularity of <persName key="Daphles" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Daphles</persName> supplied her cause with all the
                        ardour, which a lax state of subjection on the part of the more powerful
                        nobles might have denied it. When her troops charged, or made any other
                        voluntary movement, they put all their hearts into their blows; and when
                        they were compelled to await the enemy, they stood as inflexible as walls of
                        iron. It was like hammering upon</p>
                    <pb n="110"/>
                    <p>metal statuary; or staking their fated horses upon spears rivetted in stone.
                            <persName key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>
                        was taken prisoner. The queen, re-issuing from her tent, crowned with
                        laurel, came riding down the eminence, and remained at the foot with her
                        generals, while the prisoners were taken by. Her pale face kept as royal a
                        countenance of composed pity as she could manage, while the commoner rebels
                        passed along, aching with their wounded arms fastened behind, and shaking
                        back their bloody and blinding locks for want of a hand to part them. But
                        the blood mounted to her cheeks, when the proud and handsome <persName
                            key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>, whom
                        she now saw for the first time, blushed deeply as he cast a glance at his
                        female conqueror, and then stepped haughtily along, handling his gilded
                        chains as if they were an indifferent ornament. <q type="thought">I have
                            conquered him,</q> thought she: <q type="thought">it is a heavy blow to
                            so proud a head; and as he looks not unamiable, it might be politic as
                            well as courteous and kind in me to turn his submission into a more
                            willing one.</q> Alas! pity was helping admiration to a kinder set of
                        offices, than the generous-hearted queen suspected. The captive went to his
                        prison, a conqueror after all; for <persName key="Daphles" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Daphles</persName> loved him.</p>
                    <p>The second night, after having exhibited in her manners a strange mixture of
                        joy and seriousness, and signified to her counsellors her intention of
                        setting the prisoner free, she released him with her own hands. Many a step
                        did she hesitate as she went down the stairs; and when she came to the door,
                        she shed a full, but soft, and as it seemed to her a wilful and refreshing
                        flood of tears, humbling herself for her approaching task. When she had
                        entered, she blushed deeply, and then turning as pale, stood for a minute
                        silent and without motion, She then said, <q type="spoken">Thy queen,
                                <persName key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional"
                                >Doracles</persName>, has come to shew thee how kindly she can treat
                            a great and gallant subject, who did not know her</q> and with these
                        words, and almost before she was aware, the prisoner was released, and
                        preparing to go. He appeared surprised, but not off his guard, nor in any
                        temper to be over-grateful. <q type="spoken">Name,</q> said he, <q
                            type="spoken">O queen, the conditions on </q></p>
                    <pb n="111"/>
                    <p><q type="spoken">which I depart, and they will be faithfully kept.</q>
                            <persName key="Daphles" cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName>
                        moved her lips, but they spoke not. She waved her head and hand with a
                        deadly smile, as if free- ing him from all conditions; and he was turning
                        to go, when she fell senseless on the floor. The haughty warrior raised her
                        with more impatience than goodwill. He could guess at love in a woman; but
                        he had but a mean opinion both of it and her sex; and the deadly struggle in
                        the heart of <persName key="Daphles" cert="high" type="fictional"
                            >Daphles</persName> did not help him to distinguish the romantic
                        passion, which had induced her to put all her past and virgin notions of
                        love into his person, from the commonest liking that might flatter his
                        soldierly vanity.</p>
                    <p>The queen, on awaking from her swoon, found herself compelled, in very
                        justice to the intensity of a true passion, to explain how pity had brought
                        it upon her. <q type="spoken">I might ask it,</q> said she, <q type="spoken"
                            ><persName key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional"
                                >Doracles</persName>, in return;</q> and here she resumed something
                        of her queen-like dignity; <q type="spoken">but I feel that my modesty will
                            be sufficiently saved by the name of your wife: and a substantial
                            throne, with a return that shall nothing perplex or, interfere with thee,
                            I do now accordingly</q></p>
                    <pb n="111"/>
                    <p><q type="spoken">offer thee, not as the condition of thy freedom, but as a
                            diversion of men's eyes and thoughts from what they will think ill in
                            me, if they find me rejected.</q> And in getting out that hard word, her
                        voice <choice><orig>£aultered</orig><reg>faltered</reg></choice> a little,
                        and <choice><orig>hfer</orig><reg>her</reg></choice> eyes filled with
                        tears.</p>
                    <p><persName key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>,
                        with the best grace his lately defeated spirit could assume, spoke in
                        willing terms of accepting her offer. They left the prison; and his full
                        pardon having been proclaimed, the courtiers, with feasts and
                        entertainments, vied who should seem best to approve their mistress's
                        choice; for so they were quick to understand it. The late captive, who was
                        really as graceful and accomplished as a proud spirit would let him be,
                        received and returned all their attention in princely sort; and <persName
                            key="Daphles" cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName> was
                        beginning to hope that he might turn a glad eye upon her some day, when news
                        was brought her that he had gone from court, nobody knew whither. The next
                        intelligence was too certain. He had passed the frontiers, and was leaguing
                        with her enemies for another struggle.</p>
                    <p>From that day, gladness, though not kindness, went out of the face of
                            <persName key="Daphles" cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName>.
                        She wrote him a letter, without a word of reproach in it, enough to bring
                        back the remotest heart that had the least spark of sympathy; but he only
                        answered it in a spirit, which shewed that he regarded • the deepest love
                        but as a wanton trifle. That letter touched her kind wits. She had had a
                        paper drawn up, leaving him her throne in case she should die; but some of
                        her ministers, availing themselves of her enfeebled spirit, had summoned a
                        meeting of the nobles, at which she was to preside in the dress she wore on
                        the day of victory; the sight of which, it was thought, with the arguments
                        which they meant to use, would prevail upon the assembly to urge her to a
                        revocation of the bequest. Her women dressed her, while she was almost
                        unconscious of what they were doing, for she had now began to fade quickly,
                        body as well as mind. They put on her the white garments edged with silver
                        waves, in remembrance of the stream of <persName key="Inachus" cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Inachus</persName>, the founder of the <placeName
                            key="Argos" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q189568" cert="high"
                            type="city">Argive</placeName> monarchy; the spear was brought out, to
                        be stuck by the side of the throne, instead of the sceptre; and their hands
                        prepared to put the same laurel on her head, which bound it's healthy white
                        temples, when she sat on horse-back, and saw the prisoner go by. But at
                        sight of it's twisted and withered green, she took it in her hand; and
                        looking about her in her chair with an air of momentary recollection, began
                        picking it, and letting the leaves fall upon the floor. She went on thus,
                        leaf after leaf, looking vacantly downwards; and when she had stripped
                        <choice><orig>thie</orig><reg>the</reg></choice> circle half round, she leaned her
                        cheek against the side of her sick chair; and shutting her eyes quietly, so
                        died.</p>
                    <pb n="112"/>
                    <p>daughter. The new prince observing the melancholy which he scarcely affected
                        to repress, and seeing him look up occasionally at a picture which had a veil
                        over it, asked him what the picture was that seemed to disturb him so, and
                        why it was veiled. <q type="spoken">If it be the portrait of the late
                            king,</q> said <persName key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional"
                            >Doracles</persName>,<q type="spoken"> pray think me worthy of doing
                            honour to it, for he was a noble prince. Unveil it, pray. I insist upon
                            it. What? Am I not worthy to look upon my predecessors,
                                <persName key="Phorbas" cert="high" type="fictional"
                                >Phorbas</persName>?</q> And at these words, he frowned
                        impatiently. <persName key="Phorbas" cert="high" type="fictional"
                            >Phorbas</persName>, with a trembling hand, but not for want of courage,
                        withdrew the black covering; and the portrait of <persName key="Daphles"
                            cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName>, in all her youth and
                        beauty, flashed upon the eyes of <persName key="Doracles" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Doracles</persName>. It was not a melancholy face. It
                        was drawn before misfortune had touched it, and sparkled with a blooming
                        beauty, in which animal spirits and good-nature contended for predominance.
                            <persName key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional"
                            >Doracles</persName> paused, and seemed struck. <q type="spoken">The
                            possessor of that face,</q> said he, inquiringly, <q type="spoken"
                            >could never have been so sorrowful, as I have heard?</q>—<q
                            type="spoken">Pardon me, Sir,</q> answered <persName key="Phorbas"
                            cert="high" type="fictional">Phorbas</persName>; <q type="spoken">I was
                            as another father to her, and knew all.</q><q type="spoken"> It cannot
                            be,</q> returned the <persName key="Doracles" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">prince</persName>. The old man begged his other guests
                        to withdraw a while, and then told <persName key="Doracles" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Doracles</persName> how many fond and despairing things
                        the queen had said of him, both before her wits began to fail, and after.
                            <q type="spoken">Her wits to fail?</q> murmured the <persName
                            key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional">king</persName>: <q
                            type="spoken">I have known what it is to feel almost a mad impatience of
                            the will; but I knew not that these — -- gentle creatures, women, could
                            so feel for such a trifle.</q><persName key="Phorbas" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Phorbas</persName> brought out the laurel-crown, and
                        told him how it was that the half of it became bare. The impatient blood of
                            <persName key="Doracles" cert="high" type="fictional"
                            >Doracles</persName> mounted, but not in anger, to his face; and
                        breaking up the party, he requested that the picture might be removed to his
                        own chamber, promising to return it.</p>
                    <p>A whole year however did he keep it; and as he had no foreign enemies to
                        occupy his time, nor was disposed to enter into the common sports of peace,
                        it was understood that he spent the greatest part of his time, when he was
                        not in council, in the room where the picture hung. In truth, the image of
                        the once smiling <persName key="Daphles" cert="high" type="fictional"
                            >Daphles</persName> haunted him wherever he went; and to ease himself
                        of the yearning of wishing her alive again and seeing her face, he was in
                        the habit of being with it as much as possible. His self-will turned upon
                        him, even in that gentle shape. Millions of times did he wish back the loving
                        author of his fortunes, whom he had treated with so clownish an
                        ingratitude; and millions of times did the sense of the impotence of his
                        wish run up in red hurry to his cheeks, and help to pull them into a gaunt
                        melancholy. But this is not a repaying sorrow to dwell upon. He was one day,
                        after being in vain expected at council, found lying madly on the floor of
                        the room, dead. He had torn the portrait from the wall. His dagger was in
                        his heart; and his cheek lay upon that blooming and smiling face, which had
                        it been living, would never have looked so at being revenged.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="3">
                    <pb n="113"/>
                    <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">SPIRIT OF THE ANCIENT MYTHOLOGY.</head>
                    <p>From having a different creed of our own, and always encountering the heathen
                        mythology in a poetical and fabulous shape, we are apt to have a false idea
                        of the religious feeling of the ancients. We are in the habit of supposing,
                        whatever we allow when we come to reason upon the point, that they regarded
                        their fables in the same poetical light as ourselves; that they could not
                        possibly put faith in <persName key="Jupiter (mythology)" cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Jupiter</persName>, <persName key="Neptune"
                            cert="high" type="mythological">Neptune</persName>, and <persName
                            key="Pluto (mythology)" cert="high" type="mythological">Pluto</persName>;
                        in the sacrifice of innocent turtle doves, the libation of wine, and the
                        notions about <placeName key="Tartarus" cert="high" type="mythological_place"
                            >Tartarus</placeName> and <persName key="Ixion" cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Ixion</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Undoubtedly there were multitudes of free thinkers in the ancient world. Most
                        of the <placeName key="Ancient Greece" type="country">Greek</placeName> poets
                        and philosophers appear to have differed with the literal notions of the
                        many.<note type="hunt"><bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">It is remarkable that
                                        <persName key="Aeschylus"
                                        ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q40939" cert="high"
                                        type="real">Æschylus</persName> and <persName
                                        key="Euripides"
                                        ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q48305" cert="high"
                                        type="real">Euripides</persName>, the two dramatists whose
                                    faith in the national religion was most doubted, are said to
                                    have met with strange and violent deaths.—The latter was torn to
                                    pieces by dogs, and the former killed by a tortoise which an
                                    eagle let fall upon his bald head in mistake for a stone. These
                                    exits from the scene look very like the retributive death-beds
                                    wliieh the bigots of all religions are so fond of ascribing to
                                    one another.</hi></bibl></note> A system of refined theism is
                        understood to have been taught to the initiated in the celebrated
                            <q type="term">Mysteries</q>. The doctrines of <persName
                            key="Epicurus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q846872" cert="high"
                            type="real">Epicurus</persName> were so prevalent in the most
                        intellectual age of <placeName key="Ancient Rome" type="country"
                            >Rome</placeName>, that <persName key="Lucretius"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q193645" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Lucretius</persName> wrote a poem upon them, in which he treats their
                        founder as a divinity; and <persName key="Virgil"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1398" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Virgil</persName>, in a well-known passage of the <title level="m"
                            key="Georgics" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q723654" cert="high"
                            >Georgics</title>, <foreign xml:lang="latin"><q type="mentioned"
                                >Felix qui potuit</q></foreign> &amp;c. exalts either <persName
                            key="Epicurus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q846872" cert="high"
                            type="real">Epicurus</persName> or <persName key="Lucretius"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q193645" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Lucretius</persName> as a blessed being, who put <placeName key="Hell"
                            type="mythological_place">hell</placeName> and terror under his feet. A
                        sickly temperament appears to have made him wish, rather than be able, to
                        carry his own scepticism so far: yet he insinuates his disbelief in
                            <placeName key="Tartarus" cert="high" type="mythological_place"
                            >Tartarus</placeName> in the sixth book of his epic poem, where
                            <persName key="Aeneas" cert="high" type="mythological">Æneas</persName>
                        and the <persName key="Sibyl" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Sybil</persName>, after the description of the lower world, go out
                        through the ivory gate, which was the passage of false visions.<note
                            type="hunt"><bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Did <persName key="Dante
                                        Alighieri" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1067"
                                        cert="high" type="real">Dante</persName> forget this, when
                                    he took <persName key="Virgil"
                                        ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1398" cert="high"
                                        type="real">Virgil</persName> for his guide through the
                                        <title level="m" key="Inferno (Dante)"
                                        ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q670679" cert="high"
                                        >Inferno</title>?</hi></bibl></note>
                        <persName key="Julius Caesar" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1048"
                            cert="high" type="real">Cæsar</persName>, according to a speech of his
                        in <persName key="Sallust" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q76082"
                            cert="high" type="real">Sallust</persName>, derided the same notions
                        in open <orgName type="government">Senate</orgName>; and <persName
                            key="Cicero" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1541" cert="high"
                            type="real">Cicero</persName>, in other parts of his writings, as well
                        as in a public pleading, speaks of them as fables and impertinence,—<foreign
                            xml:lang="latin"><q type="mentioned">ineptiis ac fabulis</q></foreign>.</p>
                    <pb n="114"/>
                    <p>But however this plain-dealing may look on the part of the men of letters,
                        there is reason to believe that even in those times, the people in general
                        were strong upon points of faith. The extension of the <placeName
                            key="Ancient Greece" type="country">Greek</placeName> philosophy may
                        have insensibly rendered them familiar with latitudes of interpretation on
                        the part of others. They would not think it impious in <persName
                            key="Cicero" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1541" cert="high"
                            type="real">Cicero</persName> and <persName key="Cato the Elder"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q193638" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Cato</persName> to have notions of the Supreme Being more consistent
                        with the elevation of their minds. But for themselves, they adhered, from
                        habit, to the literal creed of their ancestors, as the <placeName
                            key="Ancient Greece" type="country">Greek</placeName> populace had done
                        before them. The jealous enemies of <persName key="Socrates"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q913" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Socrates</persName> contrived to have him put to death on a charge of
                        irreverence for the gods. A frolic of the libertine <persName
                            key="Alcibiades" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q185116"
                            cert="high" type="real">Alcibiades</persName>, which to say the least
                        of it, was in very bad taste,—the defacing the statues of <persName
                            key="Mercury (mythology)" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Mercury</persName>,—was followed with important consequences. The
                        history of <persName key="Socrates" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q913"
                            cert="high" type="real">Socrates</persName> had the effect, in after
                        times, at least in the ancient world, of saving philosophical speculators
                        from the vindictive egotism of opinion. But even in the days of <persName
                            key="Augustus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1405" cert="high"
                            type="real">Augustus</persName>, <persName key="Ovid"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q12196" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Ovid</persName> wrote a popular work full of mythological fables; and
                            <persName key="Virgil" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1398"
                            cert="high" type="real">Virgil</persName> himself, whose creed perhaps
                        only rejected what was unkindly, gave the hero of his intended popular epic,
                        the particular appellation of <emph>Pious</emph>. That <persName
                            key="Augustus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1405" cert="high"
                            type="real">Augustus</persName> should pique himself on the same
                        attribute, proves little; for he was a cold-blooded man of the world, and
                        could play the hypocrite for the worst and most despotic purposes. Did he
                        now and then lecture his poetical friends upon this point, respecting their
                        own appearances with the world ? There is a curious ode of <persName
                            key="Horace" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q9758" cert="high"
                            type="real">Horace</persName> (<bibl>Book 1. Od. 34.</bibl>) in which
                        he says that he finds himself compelled to give up his sceptical notions,
                        and to attend more to public worship, because it had thundered one day when,
                        the sky was cloudless. The critics are divided in their opinion of his
                        object in this ode. Some think him in earnest, others in jest. It is the only
                        thing of the sort in his works; and is, at all events, of an equivocal
                        character that would serve his purpose on either side of the question.</p>
                    <p>The opinions of the ancients upon religion may be divided into three general
                        classes. The great multitude believed any thing; the very few disbelieved
                        every thing, the philosophers and poets entertained a refined natural
                        religion, which while it pronounced upon nothing, rejected what was evidently
                        unworthy of the spirit; of the creation, and regarded the popular deities, as
                        personifications of it's various workings. All these classes had their
                        extravagances, in proportion to their ignorance, or viciousness, or
                        metaphysical, perplexity. The multitude, whose notions were founded on
                        ignorance, habit, and fear, admitted many absurd and some cruel
                        imaginations. The mere man of the world measured every thing by his own vain
                        and petty standard, and thought the whole goods of the universe a scramble
                        for the cunning and hypocritical. The over-refining followers of <persName
                            key="Plato" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q859" cert="high"
                            type="real">Plato</persName>, endeavouring to pierce into the nature of
                        things by the mere effort of the will, arrived at conclusions visible to none
                        but their own yearning and impatient eyes; and lost themselves in the
                        ethereal dogmatisms of <persName key="Plotinus"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q193656" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Plotinus</persName> and <persName key="Porphyry"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q208159" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Porphyry</persName>.</p>
                    <pb n="115"/>
                    <p>ancient mythology, is in a mingled sense of the old popular belief and of the
                        philosophical refinements upon it. We take <persName key="Apollo"
                            cert="high" type="mythological">Apollo</persName>, and <persName
                            key="Mercury (mythology)" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Mercury</persName>, and <persName key="Venus (mythology)" cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Venus</persName>, as shapes that existed in popular
                        credulity, as the greater fairies bf the ancient world; and we regard them,
                        at the same time, as personifications of all that is beautiful and genial in
                        the forms and tendencies of creation. But the result, coming as it does too
                        through avenues of beautiful poetry, both ancient and modern, is so entirely
                        chearful, that we are apt to think it must have wanted gravity to more
                        believing eyes. We fancy that the old world saw nothing in religion but
                        lively and graceful shapes, as remote from the more obscure and awful
                        hintings of the world unknown, as physics appear to be from the
                        metaphysical;—as the eye of a beautiful woman is from the inward
                        speculations of a <persName key="Brahmin" cert="high" type="role"
                            >Brahmin</persName>; or a lily at noon-day from the wide obscurity of
                        night-time.</p>
                    <p>This supposition appears to be carried a great deal too far. We will not
                        enquire in this place, how far the mass of mankind, when these shapes were
                        done away, did or did not escape from a despotic anthropomorphitism; nor how
                        far they were driven by the vaguer fears, and the opening of a more visible
                        eternity, into avoiding the whole subject, rather than courting it; nor how
                        it is, that the nobler practical religion which was afforded them, has been
                        unable to bring back their frightened theology from the angry and avaricious
                        pursuits into which they fled for refuge. But setting aside the portion of
                        terror, of which heathenism partook in common with all faiths originating in
                        uncultivated times, the ordinary run of pagans were perhaps more impressed
                        with a sense of the invisible world, in consequence of the very visions
                        presented to their imagination, than the same description of men under a more
                        shadowy system. There is the same difference between the two things, as
                        between a populace believing in fairies, and a populace not believing. The
                        latter is in the high road to something better, if not drawn aside into new
                        terrors on the one hand, or mere worldliness on the other. But the former is
                        led to look out of the mere worldly commonplaces about it, twenty times to
                        the other's once. It has a sense of a supernatural state of things, however
                        gross. It has a link with another world, from which somethink like gravity is
                        sure to strike into the most chearful heart. Every <placeName type="physical"
                            >forest</placeName>, to the mind's eye of a <placeName
                            key="Ancient Greece" type="country">Greek</placeName>, was haunted with
                        superior intelligences. Every <placeName type="physical">stream</placeName>
                        had it's presiding <persName key="Nymph" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >nymph</persName>, who was thanked for the draught of water. Every
                            <placeName type="building">house</placeName> had it's protecting gods,
                        which had blessed the inmate's ancestors; and which would bless him also, if
                        he cultivated the social affections: for the same word which expressed
                        piety towards the <persName key="Deity" type="personification">Gods</persName>,
                        expressed love towards relations and friends. If in all this there was
                        nothing but the worship of a more graceful humanity, there may be worships
                        much worse as well as much better. And the divinest spirit that ever
                        appeared on <placeName type="physical">earth</placeName> has told us, that
                        the extension of human sympathy embraces all that is required of us, either to
                        do or to foresee.</p>
                    <pb n="116"/>
                    <p>Imagine the feelings with which an ancient believer must have gone by the
                        oracular oaks of <placeName key="Dodona"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q840833" cert="high" type="physical"
                            >Dodona</placeName>, or the calm groves of the <persName
                            key="Eumenides" cert="high" type="mythological">Eumenides</persName>,
                        or the fountain where <persName key="Persephone" cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Proserpine</persName> vanished underground with
                            <persName key="Pluto (mythology)" cert="high" type="mythological"
                            >Pluto</persName>; or the Great Temple of the Mysteries at <placeName
                            key="Eleusis" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q723049" cert="high"
                            type="city">Eleusis</placeName>; or the laurelled mountain <placeName
                            key="Mount Parnassus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q105680"
                            cert="high" type="physical">Parnassus</placeName>, on the side of which
                        was the temple of <placeName key="Delphi"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q142704" cert="high" type="physical"
                            >Delphi</placeName>, where <persName key="Apollo" cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Apollo</persName> was supposed to be present in
                        person. Imagine <persName key="Plutarch"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q11854" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Plutarch</persName>, a devout and yet a liberal believer, when he went
                        to study theology and philosophy at <placeName key="Delphi"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q142704" cert="high" type="physical"
                            >Delphi</placeName>: with what feelings must he not have passed along
                        the woody paths of the hill, approaching nearer every instant to the presence
                        of the divinity, and not sure that a glance of light through the trees was not
                        the lustre of the god himself going by. This is mere poetry to us, and very
                        fine it is; but to him it was poetry, and religion, and beauty, and gravity,
                        and hushing awe, and a path as from one world to another.</p>
                    <p>With similar feelings he would cross the ocean, an element that naturally
                        detaches the mind from <placeName type="physical">earth</placeName>, and
                        which the ancients regarded as especially doing so. He had been in the
                            <placeName key="Karpathos" corresp="Greece"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q213693" cert="high" type="region"
                            >Carpathian sea</placeName>, the favourite haunt of <persName
                            key="Proteus" cert="high" type="mythological">Proteus</persName>, who
                        was supposed to be gifted above every other deity with a knowledge of the
                        causes of things. Towards evening, when the winds were rising, and the sailors
                        had made their vows to <persName key="Neptune" cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Neptune</persName>, he would think of the old <q
                            type="distinct">shepherd of the seas, of yore,</q> and believe it
                        possible that he might become visible to his eyesight, driving through the
                        darkling waters, and turning the sacred wildness of his face towards the
                        blessed ship.</p>
                    <p>In all this, there is a deeper sense of another world, than in the habit of
                        contenting oneself with a few vague terms and embodying nothing but
                            <persName key="Mammon" cert="high" type="biblical"
                            >Mammon</persName>. There is a deeper sense of another world, precisely
                        because there is a deeper sense of the present; of it's varieties, it's
                        benignities, it's mystery. It was a strong sense of this, which made a living
                        poet, who is accounted very orthodox in his religious opinions, give vent, in
                        that fine sonnet, to his impatience at seeing the beautiful <placeName
                            type="physical">planet</placeName> we live upon, with all it's starry
                        wonders about it, so little thought of, compared with what is <q
                            type="soCalled">ridiculously called the world.</q> He seems to have
                            <choice><orig>dreaded</orig><reg>dreaded</reg></choice> the symptom, as an
                        evidence of materialism, and of the planets being dry self-existing things,
                        peopled with mere successive mortalities, and unconnected with any
                        superintendance or consciousness in the universe about them. It is abhorrent
                        from all we think and feel, that they should be so: and yet <persName
                            key="Love" type="personification">Love</persName> might make heavens of
                        them, if they were.</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l><q type="spoken">The world is too much with us. Late and soon,</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Getting and spending, we lay waste our
                                        powers:</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Little we see in <persName key="Nature"
                                            type="personification">Nature</persName> that is
                                        ours:</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">We have given our hearts away, a sordid
                                        boon!</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">This Sea that bares her bosom to the
                                        moon;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">The Winds that will be howling at all hours,</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">And are <choice><sic>npgathered</sic><corr>ungathered</corr></choice> now like sleeping
                                        flowers;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">For this, for every thing, we are out of
                                        tune;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">It moves us not.—Great <persName key="God"
                                            type="mythological">God</persName>! I'd rather
                                        be</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">A <rs type="religious">Pagan</rs> suckled in a
                                        creed outworn,</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">So might I, standing on this pleasant lea,</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Have glimpses that would make me less
                                        forlorn;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Have sight of <persName key="Proteus"
                                            cert="high" type="mythological">Proteus</persName>
                                        coming from the sea;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Or hear old <persName key="Triton" cert="high"
                                            type="mythological">Triton</persName> blow his wreathed
                                        horn."</q></l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl><author>William Wordsworth</author>, <title level="a">The World
                                    Is Too Much with Us</title>, <title level="m">Poems in Two
                                    Volumes</title>, <date when="1807">1807</date>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="4">
                    <pb n="117"/>
                    <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">GETTING UP ON COLD MORNINGS.</head>
                    <p>An <placeName key="Italy" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q38"
                            cert="high" type="country">Italian</placeName> author,—<persName
                            key="Giulio Cordara" cert="high" type="real">Giulio Cordara</persName>,
                        a <orgName type="religious">Jesuit</orgName>,—has written a poem upon
                        Insects, which he begins by insisting, that those troublesome and
                        abominable little animals were created for our annoyance, and that they were
                        certainly not inhabitants of <placeName key="Garden of Eden" cert="high"
                            type="fictional_place">Paradise</placeName>. We of the <placeName
                            key="Europe" type="continent">North</placeName> may dispute this piece
                        of theology; but on the other hand, it is as clear as the snow on the
                        house-tops, that <persName key="Adam (Biblical figure)" cert="high"
                            type="biblical">Adam</persName> was not under the necessity of shaving;
                        and that when <persName key="Eve (Biblical figure)" cert="high"
                            type="biblical">Eve</persName> walked out of her delicious bower, she
                        did not step upon ice three inches thick.</p>
                    <p>Some people say it is a very easy thing to get up of a cold morning. You
                        have only, they tell you, to take the resolution; and the thing is done. This
                        may be very true; just as a boy at school has only to take a flogging, and
                        the thing is over. But we have not at all made up our minds upon it; and we
                        find it a very pleasant exercise to discuss the matter, candidly, before we
                        get up. This at least is not idling, though it may be lying. It affords an
                        excellent answer to those, who ask how lying in bed can be indulged in by a
                        reasoning being,—a rational creature. How? Why with the argument calmly at
                        work in one's head, and the clothes over one's shoulder. Oh—it is a fine way
                        of spending a sensible, impartial half-hour.</p>
                    <p>If these people would be more charitable, they would get on with their
                        argument better. But they are apt to reason so ill, and to assert so
                        dogmatically, that one could wish to have them stand round one's bed of a
                        bitter morning, and lie before their faces. They ought to hear both sides of
                        the bed, the inside and out. If they cannot entertain themselves with their
                        own thoughts for half an hour or so, it is not the fault of those who can.
                        If their will is never pulled aside by the enticing arms of imagination, so
                        much the luckier for the stage-coachman.</p>
                    <p>Candid inquirers into one's decumbency, besides the greater or less
                        privileges to be allowed a man in proportion to his ability of keeping early
                        hours, the work given his faculties, &amp;c., will at least concede their
                        due merits to such representations as the following. In the first place, says
                        the injured but calm appealer, I have been warm all night, and find my
                        system in a state perfectly suitable to a warm-blooded animal. To get out of
                        this state into the cold, besides the inharmonious and uncritical
                        abruptness of the transition, is so unnatural to such a creature, that the
                        poets, refining upon the tortures of the damned, make one of their greatest
                        agonies consist in being suddenly transported from heat to cold,—from fire to
                        ice. They are <q type="spoken">haled</q> out of their <q type="spoken"
                            >beds</q>, says <persName key="John Milton"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q163559" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Milton</persName>, by <q type="spoken">harpy-footed furies</q>,—fellows
                        who come to call them.—On my first movement towards the anticipation of
                        getting up, I find that such parts of the sheets and bolster, as are exposed
                        to the air of the room, are stone cold. On opening my eyes, the first thing
                        that meets them is my own breath rolling forth, as if in the open air, like
                        smoke out of a cottage-chimney. Think of this symptom. Then I turn my eyes
                        sideways and see the window all frozen over. Think of that. Then the servant
                        comes in. <q type="spoken">It is very cold this morning, is it not?</q>--</p>
                    <pb n="118"/>
                    <p><q type="spoken">Very cold, Sir.</q>—<q type="spoken">Very cold indeed, isn't
                            it?</q>—<q type="spoken">Very cold indeed, Sir.</q>—<q type="spoken"
                            >More than usually so, isn't it, even for this weather?</q> (Here the
                        servant's wit and good nature are put to a considerable test, and the
                        inquirer lies on thorns for the answer.) <q type="spoken">Why, Sir- - - -I
                            think it is.</q> (Good creature! There is not a better, or more
                        truth-telling servant going.) <q type="spoken">I must rise however—Get me
                            some warm water.</q>—Here comes a fine interval between the departure of
                        the servant and the arrival of the hot water; during which, of course, it is
                        of <q type="soCalled">no use</q> to get up. The hot water comes. <q
                            type="spoken">Is it quite hot?</q>—<q type="spoken">Yes, Sir.</q>—<q
                            type="spoken">Perhaps too hot for shaving: I must wait a
                            little?</q>—<q type="spoken"> No, Sir; it will just do.</q> (There is
                        an over-nice propriety sometimes, an officious zeal of virtue, a little
                        troublesome.) <q type="spoken">Oh— the shirt—you must air my clean
                            shirt:—linen gets very damp this weather.</q>—<q type="spoken">Yes,
                            Sir.</q> Here another delicious five minutes. A knock at the door. <q
                            type="spoken">Oh, the shirt—very well. My stockings—I think the
                            stockings had better be aired too.</q> —<q type="spoken"> Very well.
                            Sir.</q>—Here another interval. At length every thing is ready, except
                        myself. I now, continues our incumbent (a happy word, by the bye, for a
                        country vicar)—I now cannot help thinking a good deal—who can?—upon the
                        unnecessary and villainous custom of shaving: it is a thing so unmanly (here
                        I nestle closer)—so effeminate (here I recoil from an unlucky step into the
                        colder part of the bed.)—No wonder, that the <persName
                            key="Marie Antoinette" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q47365"
                            cert="medium" type="real">Queen of France</persName> took part with the
                        rebels against that degenerate King, her husband, who first affronted her
                        smooth visage with a face like her own. The <persName key="Julian the
                            Apostate" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q134106" cert="high"
                            type="real">Emperor Julian</persName> never showed the luxuriancy of
                        his genius to better advantage than in reviving the flowing beard. Look at
                            <persName key="Pietro Bembo" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q355415"
                            cert="high" type="real">Cardinal Bembo's</persName> picture—at
                            <persName key="Michelangelo" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5592"
                            cert="high" type="real">Michael Angelo's</persName>—at <persName
                            key="Titian" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q42337" cert="high"
                            type="real">Titian's</persName>—at <persName key="William Shakespeare"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q692" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Shakspeare's</persName>—at <persName key="John Fletcher"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q455799" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Fletcher's</persName>—at <persName key="Edmund Spenser"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Spenser's</persName>—at <persName key="Geoffrey Chaucer"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5663" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Chaucer's</persName>—at <persName key="Alfred the Great"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q82883" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Alfred's</persName>—at <persName key="Plato"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q859" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Plato's</persName>.—I could name a great man for every tick of my
                        watch.— Look at the <placeName key="Turkey" corresp="Turkey" type="country"
                            >Turks</placeName>, a grave and otiose people.—Think of <persName
                            key="Harun al-Rashid" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q186326"
                            cert="high" type="real">Haroun Al Raschid</persName> and <persName
                            key="Bed-ridden Hassan" cert="low" type="fictional">Bed-ridden
                            Hassan</persName>—Think of <persName key="Edward Wortley Montagu"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1291817" cert="high" type="real"
                            >Wortley Montague</persName>, the worthy son of his mother, a man above
                        the prejudice of his time—Look at the <placeName key="Persia"
                            corresp="Iran" type="country">Persian</placeName> gentlemen, whom one is
                        ashamed of meeting about the suburbs, their dress and appearance are so much
                        finer than our own—Lastly, think of the razor itself—how totally opposed to
                        every sensation of bed—how cold, how edgy, how hard! how utterly different
                            <choice><sic>frond</sic><corr>from</corr></choice> any thing like the
                        warm and circling amplitude, which</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l><q type="spoken">Sweetly recommends itself</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Unto our gentle senses.</q></l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl><author>William Shakespeare</author>, <title level="m"
                                    key="Macbeth" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q130283"
                                    cert="high">Macbeth</title>, <biblScope unit="act"
                                    >Act I</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="scene">Scene
                                    VII</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p>Add to this, benumbed fingers, which may help you to cut yourself, a
                        quivering body, a frozen towel, and an ewer full of ice; and he that says
                        there is nothing to oppose in all this, only shews, at any rate, that he has
                        no merit in opposing it.</p>
                    <pb n="119"/>
                    <p><persName key="James Thomson" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q316499"
                            cert="high" type="real">Thomson</persName> the poet, who exclaims in
                        his <title level="m" key="The Seasons (Thomson)"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q3009710" cert="high">Seasons</title>—</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l><q type="spoken">Falsely luxurious! Will not man awake?</q></l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl><author>James Thomson</author>, <title level="m">The
                                Seasons</title>, <biblScope unit="book">Summer</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="line">line 67</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p>used to lie in bed till noon, because he said he had no motive in getting
                        up. He could imagine the good of rising; but then he could also imagine the
                        good of lying still and his exclamation, it must be</p>
                    <pb n="119"/>
                    <p>allowed, was made upon summer-time, not winter. We must proportion the
                        argument to the individual character. A money-getter may be drawn out of his
                        bed by three and four-pence; but this will not suffice for a student. A proud
                        man may say <q type="spoken">What shall I think of myself, if I don't get
                            up?</q> but the more humble one will be content to waive this prodigious
                        notion of himself, out of respect to his kindly bed. The mechanical man
                        shall get up without any ado at all; and so shall the barometer. An
                        ingenious lier in bed will find hard matter of discussion even on the score
                        of health and longevity. He will ask us for our proofs and precedents of the
                        ill effects of lying later in cold weather; and sophisticate much on the
                        advantages of an even temperature of body; of the natural propensity (pretty
                        universal) to have one's way; and of the animals that roll themselves up and
                        sleep all the winter. As to longevity, he will ask whether the longest life
                        is of necessity the best; and whether <placeName key="Holborn"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2002360" cert="high" type="region"
                            >Holborn</placeName> is the handsomest street in <placeName
                            key="London" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q84" cert="high"
                            type="city">London</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>We only know of one confounding, not to say confounded argument, fit to
                        overturn the huge luxury, the <q type="distinct">enormous bliss</q>—of the
                        vice in question. A lier in bed may be allowed to profess a disinterested
                        indifference for his health or longevity; but while he is shewing the
                        reasonableness of consulting his own, or one person's comfort, he must admit
                        the proportionate claim of more than one; and the best way to deal with him
                        is this, especially for a lady; for we earnestly recommend the use of that
                        sex on such occasions, if not somewhat over-persuasive; since extremes have
                        an awkward knack of meeting. First then, admit all the ingeniousness of what
                        he says, telling him that the bar has been deprived of an excellent lawyer.
                        Then look at him in the most goodnatured manner in the world, with a mixture
                        of assent and appeal in your countenance, and tell him that you are waiting
                        breakfast for him; that you never like to breakfast without him; that you
                        really want it too; that the servents want theirs; that you shall not know
                        how to get the house into order, unless he rises; and that you are sure he
                        would do things twenty times worse, even than getting out of his warm bed, to
                        put them all into good humour and a state of comfort. Then, after having said
                        this, throw in the comparatively indifferent matter, to him, about his
                        health; but tell him that it is no indifferent matter to you; that the sight
                        of his illness makes more people suffer than one; but that if nevertheless,
                        he really does feel so very sleepy and so very much refreshed by----Yet
                        stay; we hardly know whether the frailty of a— Yes, yes; say that too,
                        especially if you say it with sincerity; for if the weakness of human nature
                        on the one hand, and the <foreign xml:lang="latin"><hi rend="italic">vis
                                inertiæ</hi></foreign> on the other, should lead him to take
                        advantage of it once or twice, good-humour and sincerity form an
                        irresistible junction at last; and are still better and warmer things than
                        pillows and blankets.</p>
                    <p>Other little helps of appeal may be thrown in, as occasion requires. You may
                        tell a lover for instance, that lying in bed makes people corpulent; a
                        father, that you wish, him to complete the fine manly example he sets his
                        children; a lady, that she will injure her bloom or her shape, which <persName
                            key="M." cert="low" type="person">M.</persName> or <persName key="W."
                            cert="low" type="person">W.</persName>, admires so much; and a student
                        or</p>
                    <pb n="120"/>
                    <p>artist, that he is always so glad to have done a good day's work, in his best
                        manner.</p>
                    <p><persName key="Reader (fictional character)" cert="high"
                            type="fictional_character">Reader</persName>. <q type="spoken">And pray,
                                <persName key="The Indicator (magazine)" cert="high"
                                type="fictional_character">Mr. Indicator</persName>, how do you
                            behave yourself in this respect ?</q></p>
                    <p><persName key="The Indicator (magazine)" cert="high"
                            type="fictional_character">Indic</persName>. <q type="spoken">Oh, Madam,
                            perfectly, of course; like all advisers.</q></p>
                    <p><persName key="Reader (fictional character)" cert="high"
                            type="fictional_character">Reader</persName>. <q type="spoken">Nay, I
                            allow that your mode of argument does not look quite so suspicious as the
                            old way of sermonizing and severity, but I have my doubts, especially
                            from that laugh of yours. If I should look in to-morrow morning---</q></p>
                    <p><persName key="The Indicator (magazine)" cert="high"
                            type="fictional_character">Indic</persName>. <q type="spoken">Ah, Madam,
                            the look in of a face like yours does any thing with me. It shall fetch
                            me up at nine, if you please----six, I meant to say.</q></p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="correspondents">
                    <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">TO CORRESPONDENTS.</head>
                    <p>It does not enter within the plan, or perhaps we should rather say, the
                        understood promises, of this little weekly publication, to relieve the
                        Editor with much correspondence; but he is glad when he can indulge himself,
                        in proportion; and he inserts with pleasure the following piece of poetry,
                        which is very much to his heathenish taste.</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="latin">
                                <head type="title"><foreign xml:lang="latin">VOX ET PRÆTEREA
                                        NIHIL</foreign>.</head>
                                <l>Oh! what a voice is silent. It was soft</l>
                                <l>As <placeName type="physical">mountain</placeName>-echoes, when
                                    the winds aloft</l>
                                <l>(The gentle winds of summer) meet in caves;</l>
                                <l>Or when in sheltered places the white waves</l>
                                <l>Are <q type="written">'waken'd into music</q>, as the breeze</l>
                                <l>Dimples and stems the current: or as trees</l>
                                <l>Shaking their green locks in the days of June:</l>
                                <l>Or <placeName key="Delphi"
                                        ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q142704" cert="high"
                                        type="physical">Delphic</placeName> girls when to the
                                        maiden <persName key="Moon (mythology)"
                                        type="mythological">moon</persName></l>
                                <l>They sang harmonious pray'rs: or sounds that come</l>
                                <l>(However near) like a faint distant hum</l>
                                <l>Out of the grass, from which mysterious birth</l>
                                <l>We guess the busy secrets of the <placeName type="physical"
                                        >earth</placeName>.</l>
                                <l>— Like the low voice of <persName key="Syrinx" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological">Syrinx</persName>, when she ran</l>
                                <l>Into the <placeName type="physical">forests</placeName> from
                                    <placeName key="Arcadia"
                                        ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q186001" cert="high"
                                        type="region">Arcadian</placeName>
                                    <persName key="Pan (mythology)" cert="high" type="mythological"
                                        >Pan</persName>:</l>
                                <l>Or sad <persName key="Oenone" cert="high" type="mythological"
                                        >Œnone's</persName>, when she pined away</l>
                                <l>For <persName key="Paris (mythology)" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological">Paris</persName>, or (and yet 'twas not
                                    so gay)</l>
                                <l>As <persName key="Helen of Troy" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological">Helen's</persName> whisper when she came
                                    to <placeName key="Troy"
                                        ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q22695" cert="high"
                                        type="city">Troy</placeName>,</l>
                                <l>Half sham'd to wander with that, blooming boy.</l>
                                <l>Like air-touch'd harps in flowery casements hung;</l>
                                <l>Like unto lovers' ears the wild words sung</l>
                                <l>In garden bowers at twilight: like the sound</l>
                                <l>Of <persName key="Zephyr (mythology)" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological">Zephyr</persName> when he takes his
                                    nightly round</l>
                                <l>In May, to see the roses all asleep:</l>
                                <l>Or like the dim strain which along the deep</l>
                                <l>The sea-maid utters to the sailors' ear,</l>
                                <l>Telling of tempests, or of dangers near.</l>
                                <l>Like <persName key="Desdemona" cert="high" type="fictional"
                                        >Desdemona</persName>, who (when fear was strong</l>
                                <l>Upon her soul) chaunted the willow song.</l>
                                <l>Swan-like before she perish'd: or the tone</l>
                                <l>Of flutes upon the waters heard alone:</l>
                                <l>Like words that come upon the memory</l>
                                <l>Spoken by friends departed; or the sigh</l>
                                <l>A gentle girl breathes when she tries to hide</l>
                                <l>The love her eyes betray to all beside.</l>
                                <l rend="right">XXX.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                    </cit>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="colophon">
                    <p>Orders received by the Newsmen, by the Booksellers, and by the <orgName
                            type="publisher">Publisher</orgName>, <persName key="Joseph Appleyard"
                            type="real">JOSEPH APPLEYARD</persName>,</p>
                    <p><address><addrLine>No. 19, <placeName key="Catherine Street, London"
                                    corresp="England" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q28591876"
                                    cert="high" type="street">Catherine-street</placeName>,
                                    <placeName key="Strand, London"
                                    ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q193644" cert="high"
                                    type="street">Strand</placeName></addrLine>.— Price 2d.</address></p>
                    <p>Printed by <persName key="C. H. Reynell" type="real">C. H. REYNELL</persName>,
                            <address><addrLine>No. 45, <placeName key="Broad Street, Soho"
                                    corresp="England" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4972306"
                                    cert="high" type="street">Broad-street</placeName>, <placeName
                                    key="Golden Square"
                                    ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q896207" cert="high"
                                    type="landmark">Golden-square</placeName>, <placeName
                                    key="London" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q84" cert="high"
                                    type="city">London</placeName></addrLine>.</address></p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>