<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <!-- File Description -->
  <fileDesc>
   <!-- Title of the work -->
   <titleStmt>
    <title>The Indicator</title>
    <author>Hunt, James Henry Leigh (1784-1859)</author>
   </titleStmt>

   <publicationStmt>
    <p />
   </publicationStmt>

   <!-- Author information -->
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <author>Hunt, James Henry Leigh (1784-1859)</author>
     <title>The Indicator</title>
     <date when="1819-12-08"> DECEMBER 8th, 1819</date> <!-- The publication date of this issue ({Month} {Day}, {Year}) -->
     <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
     <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher> <!-- Publisher details if available -->
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>

  <!-- Encoding Description -->
  <encodingDesc>
   <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
   <p>
    Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers are
    included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
    preservation.
   </p>
  </encodingDesc>

  <!-- Profile Description -->
  <profileDesc>
  </profileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div1 type="issue" n="9">
    <pb n="65" /> <!-- Page beginning -->
    <div2 type="forematter"> <!-- Title, epigraph, and catalogue -->
     <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
     <epigraph>
      <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
      <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
      <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
      <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055"
        cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
     </epigraph>
     <head type="catalogue">No. IX. <date when="1819-12-08">—WEDNESDAY, DECEMBER 8th, 1819</date>.</head>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="section" n="1"> <!-- Header and content -->
<head type="header">MORE NEWS OF ULYSSES. </head>

<p>Talking the other day with a friend about Dante, he observed, 
that whenever so great a poet told us any thing in addition or 
continuation of an ancient story, he had a right to be regarded as classical 
authority. For instance, said he, when he tells us of that characteristic 
death of Ulysses in one of the books of his Inferno, we ought 
to receive the information as authentic, and be glad that we have 
more news of Ulysses than we looked for. </p>

<p>We thought this a happy remark, and instantly turned with him 
to the passage in question; for not having read Dante regularly, we 
had passed it over so slightly as not to remember it. Yet it is 
a striking one, as the reader will see. The last account of Ulysses 
upon which we may fairly reckon, in the ancient poets, is his sudden 
re-appearance before the suitors at Ithaca, and his consummate and 
godlike victory over their crest-fallen insolence. There is something 
more told of him, it is true, before the Odyssey concludes; but with 
the exception of his visit to his aged father, our memory scarcely 
wishes to retain it; nor does it controvert the general impression 
left upon us, that the wandering hero is victorious over his domestic 
enemies; and reposes at last, and for life, in the bosom of his family. </p>

<p>The lesser poets however could not let him alone. Homer leaves 
the general impression upon one's mind, as to the close of his life;
but there are plenty of obscurer fables about it still. We have 
specimens in modern times of this propensity never to have done with a 
good story; which is natural enough, though not very wise; nor 
are the best writers likely to meddle with it. Thus Cervantes was 
plagued with a spurious Quixote; and our circulating libraries have 
the adventures of Tom Jones in his Married State. The ancient 
writers on the present subject, availing themselves of an obscure 
prophecy of Tiresias, who tells Ulysses on his visit to hell, that 
his old enemy the sea would be the death of him at last, bring 
over the sea Telegonus, his son by the goddess Circe, who gets into 
a scuffle with the Ithacans, and kills his father unknowingly. It is 
added, that Telegonus afterwards returned to his mother's island, 
taking Penelope and his half-brother Telemachus with him; and 

<pb n="66"/>

here a singular arrangement takes place, more after the fashion of 
a modern Catholic dynasty, than an ancient heathen one: for while 
<choice><orig>AEdipus</orig><reg>Oedipus</reg></choice> was fated to undergo such dreadful misfortunes for marrying 
his mother without the knowledge of either party, Minerva herself 
comes down from heaven, on the present occasion, to order Telegonus 
the son of Ulysses, to marry his father's wife; the other son, 
at the same time, making a suitable match with his father's mistress, 
Circe, Telemachus seems to have had the best of this extraordinary 
bargain, for Circe was a goddess, consequently always young; and 
yet to perplex these windings-up still more, Telemachus is represented 
by some as marrying Circe's daughter, and killing his immortal 
mother-in-law. Nor does the character of the chaste and enduring 
Penelope escape in the confusion. Instead of waiting her husband's 
return in that patient manner, she is reported to have been 
over-hospitable to all the suitors; the consequence of which was a son 
called Pan, being no less a personage than the god Pan himself, or 
Nature; a fiction, as Lord Bacon says, "applied very absurdly and 
indiscreetly." There are different stories respecting her lovers; but it is 
reported that when Ulysses returned from Troy, he divorced her for 
incontinence; and that she fled, and passed her latter days in 
Mantinea. Some even go so far as to say, that her father Icarius had 
attempted to destroy her when young, because the oracle had told him 
that she would be the most dissolute of the family. This was probably 
invented by the comic writers out of a buffoon malignity; for 
there are men, so foolishly incredulous with regard to principle, that 
the reputation of it, even in a fiction, makes them impatient. </p>

<p>Now it is impossible to say whether Dante would have left Ulysses 
quietly with Penelope after all his sufferings, had he known them 
as described in Homer. The old Florentine, though wilful enough 
when he wanted to dispose of a modern's fate, had great veneration 
for his ancient predecessors. At all events, he was not acquainted 
with Homer's works. They did not make their way again into Italy 
till a little later. But there were Latin writers extant, who might 
have informed him of the other stories relative to Ulysses; and he 
saw nothing in them, to hinder him from giving the great wanderer 
a death of his own. </p>

<p>He has accordingly, with great attention to nature, made him 
impatient of staying at home, after a life of such adventure and 
excitement. But we will relate the story in his own order. He begins 
it with one of his most romantic pieces of wildness. The poet and 
his guide Virgil are making the best of their difiicult path along a 
ridge of the craggy rock, that overhangs the eighth gulph of hell: 
when Dante, looking down, sees the abyss before him full of flickering 
lights; as numerous, he says, as the fire-flies, which a peasant, 
reposing on a hill, sees filling the valley, of a hot evening. Every 
flame shot about separately; and he knew that some terrible mystery 
or other accompanied it. As he leaned down from the rock, grasping 
one of the crags, in order to look closer, his guide who perceived his 
earnestness, said, "Within those fires are spirits; every one swathed 

<pb n="67"/>

in what is burning him." Dante told him, that he had already 
guessed as much; and pointing to one of them in particular, asked 
who was in that fire, which was divided at top, as though it had  
ascended from the funeral-pile of the hating Theban brothers. 
"Within that," answered Virgil, "are Diomed and Ulysses; who 
speed together now to their own misery, as they used to do to that of 
others." They were suffering the penalty of the various frauds they 
had perpetrated in concert; such as the contrivance of the Trojan 
horse, and the plunder of the Palladium. Dante entreats with the 
greatest earnestness, that if those who are within the sparkling horror 
can speak, it may be made to come near. Virgil says it shall; but 
begs the Florentine not to question it himself; as the spirits, being 
Greek, might be shy of holding discourse with him. When the flame 
has come near enough to be spoken to, Virgil addresses the "two 
within one fire;" and requests them, if he ever deserved anything of 
them as a poet, great or little, that they would not go away, till one 
of them had told him how he came into that extremity. </p>

<p>At this, says Dante, the greater horn of the old fire began to lap 
hither and thither, murmuring; like a flame struggling with the 
wind. The top then, yearning to and fro, like a tongue trying to 
speak, threw out a voice, and said : "When I departed from Circe, 
who withdrew me to her for more than a year in the neighbourhood 
of Gaieta, before Eneas had so named it; neither the sweet company 
of my son, nor pious affection for my old father, nor the long-owed 
love with which I ought to have gladdened Penelope, could conquer 
the ardour that was in me to become wise in knowledge of the world, 
of man's vices and his virtue. I put forth into the great open deep 
with only one bark, and the small remaining crew by whom I had 
not been left. I saw the two shores on either side, as far as Spain  
and Morocco; and the island of Sardinia, and the other isles which 
the sea there bathes round about. Slowly we went, my companions and 
I, for we were old; till at last we came to that narrow outlet, where 
Hercules set up his pillars, that no man might go further. I left Seville 
on the right hand : on the other I had left Ceuta. O brothers, said 
I, who through a hundred thousand perils are at length arrived at 
the west, deny not to the short waking day that yet remains to our 
senses, an insight into the unpeopled world, setting your backs upon 
the sun. Consider the stock from which ye sprang : ye were not 
made to live like the brute beasts, but to follow virtue and 
knowledge. I so sharpened my companions with this little speech on our 
way, that it would have been difficult for me to have withheld them, 
if I would. We left the morning right in our stern, and made wings 
of our oars for the idle flight, always gaining upon the left. The 
night now beheld all the stars of the other pole; while our own was 
so low, that it arose not out of the ocean-floor. Five times the light 
had risen underneath the moon, and five, times fallen, since we put 
forth upon the great deep; when we descried a dim mountain in the 
distance, which appeared higher to me than ever I had seen any before. 
We rejoiced, and as soon mourned : for there sprung a whirlwind 

<pb n="68"/>

from the new land; and struck the foremost frame of our vessel. 
Three times, with all the waters, it whirled us round : at the fourth 
it dashed the stern up in air, and the prow downwards; till, as 
seemed fit to others, the ocean closed above our heads." </p>
<cit><quote>
<lg xml:lang="italian" type="original-quotation" xml:id="inferno-canto-26" rend="center"><l>Tre volte il fe girar con tutte l'acque : </l>
<l>A la quarta levar la poppa in suso, </l>
<l>E la prora ire in giu, come altrui piacque, </l> 
<l>Infin ch'l mar fu sopra noi richiuso. </l></lg>
</quote></cit>
<p>Why poor Ulysses should find himself in hell after his immersion, 
and be condemned to a swathing of eternal fire, while St. Dominic, 
who deluged Christianity with fire and blood, is called a Cherubic 
light, the papist, not the poet, must explain. He puts all the Pagans 
in hell, because however good some of them may have been, they 
lived before Christ, and could not worship God properly — (debitamente). 
But he laments their state, and represents them as suffering 
a mitigated punishment: they only live in a state of perpetual 
desire without hope <hi xml:lang="italian">(sol di tanto offesi)</hi> ! A sufficing misery, it must 
be allowed; but compared with the horrors he fancies for heretics 
and others, undoubtedly a great relief. Dante, throughout his 
extraordinary work, gives many evidences of great natural sensibility;
and his countenance, as handed down to us, as well as the shadestruck 
gravity of his poetry in general, shews the cuts and disquietudes 
of heart he must have endured. But unless the occasional 
hell of his own troubles, and his consciousness or the mutability of all 
things, helped him to discover the brevity of individual suffering as a 
particular, and the lastingness of nature's benevolence as an universal; 
and thus gave his poem an intention beyond what appears upon 
the surface; we must conclude, that a bigoted education, and the 
fierce party politics in which he was a leader and a sufferer, obscured 
the kind greatness of his spirit. It is always to be recollected 
forever, as Mr. Coleridge has observed somewhere in other words, that 
when men consign each other to eternal punishment and such like 
horrors, their belief is rather a venting of present impatience and  
dislike, than any thing which they take it for. The fiercest Papist or 
Calvinist only flatters himself (a strange flattery too ! ) that he could 
behold a fellow creature tumbling and shrieking about in eternal fire. 
He would begin shrieking himself in a few minutes; and think that 
he and all heaven ought to pass away, rather than that one such 
agony should continue. Tertullian himself, when he longed to 
behold the enemies of his faith burning and liquefying, only meant, 
without knowing it, that he was in an excessive rage at not convincing 
every body that read him. Yet, in the mean time, these notions 
disturb humanity, and degrade the Divine Spirit. </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2">
<head type="header">FAR COUNTRIES.</head>


<p>Imagination, though no mean thing, is not a proud one. If it 
looks down from its wings upon common places, it only the more 
perceives the vastness of the region about it. The infinity into 

<pb n="69"/>

which it's flight carries it, might indeed throw back upon it a too 
great sense of insignificance, did not Beanty or Moral Justice, 
with it's equal eye, look through that blank aspect of power, and 
reassure it; shewing it, that there is a power as much above power 
itself, as the thought that reaches to all, is to the hand that can 
touch only thus far. </p>

<p>But we do not wish to get into this tempting region of speculation, 
just now. We only intend to shew a particular instance, in which 
imagination instinctively displays it's natural humility : we mean, in 
the fondness which imaginative times and people have shewn for 
what is personally remote from them; for what is opposed to their 
own individual consciousness, even in range of space, in farness of 
situation. </p>

<p>There is no surer mark of a vain people than their treating other 
nations with contempt, especially those of whom they know least. 
It is better to verify the proverb, and take every thing unknown for 
magnificent, rather than predetermine it to be worthless. The gain 
is greater. The instinct is more judicious. When we mention the 
French as an instance, we do not mean to be invidious. Most nations 
have their good as well as bad features; and in Vanity Fair there are 
many booths. </p>

<p>The French, not long ago, praised one of their neighbours so 
highly, that the latter is suspected to have lost as much modesty, as 
the former gained by it. But they did this as a set-off against their 
own despots and bigots. When they again became the greatest 
power in Europe, they had a relapse of their old egotism. The 
French, though an amiable and intelligent people, are not an imaginative 
one. The greatest height they go is in a balloon. They get 
no farther than France, let them go where they will. They "run 
the great circle and are still at home," like the squirrel in his rolling 
cage. Instead of going to Nature in their poetry, they would make 
her come to them, and dress herself at their last new <choice><orig>toilet</orig><reg>toilette</reg></choice>. In 
practical philosophy and metaphysics, they divest themselves of gross 
prejudices, and then think they are in as graceful a state of nakedness 
as Adam and Eve. </p>

<p>At the time when the French had this fit upon them of praising 
the English (which was nevertheless the honester one of the two), 
they took to praising the Chinese for numberless unknown qualities. 
This seems a contradiction to the near-sightedness we speak of : but 
the reason they praised them was, that the Chinese had the merit of 
unbounded religious toleration; a great and extraordinary one 
certainly, and not the less so, for having been, to all appearance, the 
work of one man. All the romance of China, such as it was, — any 
thing in which they differed from the French, — their dress, their 
porcelain towers, their Great Wall, — was nothing. It was the 
particular agreement with the philosophers. </p>

<p>It happened curiously enough, that they could not have selected 
for their panegyric a nation apparently more contemptuous of others; 
or at least more self-satisfied and unimaginative. The Chinese are 
cunning and ingenious; and have a great talent at bowing out 

<pb n="70"/>

ambassadors who come to visit them. But it is somewhat inconsistent 
with what appears to be their general character, that they should 
pay strangers even this equivocal compliment; for under a prodigious 
mask of politeness, they are not slow to evince their contempt 
of other nations, whenever any comparison is insinuated with the 
subjects of the Brother of the Sun and Moon. The knowledge they 
respect in us most, is that of gun-making, and of the East Indian 
passage. When our countrymen shewed them a map of the earth, they 
enquired for China; and on finding that it only made a little piece 
in a corner, could not contain their derision. They thought that it 
was the main territory in the middle, the apple of the world's eye. </p>

<p>On the other hand, the most imaginative nations, in their highest 
times, have had a respect for remote countries. It is a mistake to 
suppose that the ancient term barbarian, applied to foreigners, 
suggested the meaning we are apt to give it. It may have gathered 
some such insolence with it among the Romans, as they spread their 
own barbarous power; but the more intellectual Greeks venerated 
the countries from which they brought the elements of their mythology 
and philosophy. The philosopher travelled into Egypt, like a 
son to see his father. The merchant heard in Phoenicia the far- 
brought stories of other realms, which he told to his delighted 
countrymen. It is supposed, that the mortal pari; of Mentor in the 
Odyssey was drawn from one of these voyagers. When Anacharsis 
the Scythian was reproached with his native place by an unworthy 
Greek, he said, "My country may be a shame to me, but you are a 
shame to your country." Greece had a lofty notion of the Persians 
and the Great King, till Xerxes came over to teach it better, and 
betrayed the softness of their skulls. </p>

<p>It was the same with the Arabians, at the time when they had the 
chief accomplishments of the world to themselves; as we see by their 
delightful tales. Every thing shines with them in the distance, like 
a sunset. What an amiable people are their Persians! What a 
wonderful place is the island of Serendib! You would think nothing 
could be finer than the Caliph's city of Bagdat, till you hear of Grand 
Cairo; and how has that epithet and that name towered in the 
imagination of all those, who have not had the misfortune to see the 
modern city! Sindbad was respected, like Ulysses, because he had 
seen so many adventures and nations. So was Aboulfaouris the 
Great Voyager, in the Persian Tales. His very name sounds like a 
wonder. </p>

<cit>
    <quote>
        <p>With many a tempest had his beard been shaken. </p>
    </quote>
    <note type="source"> 
        <bibl> Chaucer, Geoffrey: The Canterbury Tales </bibl>
    </note>
</cit>

<p>It was one of the workings of the great Alfred's mind, to know about 
far distant countries. There is a translation by him of a book of 
geography; and he even employed people to travel; a great stretch 
of intellectual munificence for those times. About the same period, 
Haroun al Raschid (whom our manhood is startled to find almost a 
less real person than we thought him, for his very reality) wrote a 
letter to the Emperor of the West, Charlemagne. Here is Arabian 
and Italian romance, shaking hands in person ! </p>

<pb n="71"/>

<p>The Crusades pierced into a new world of remoteness. We do not 
know whether those were much benefited, who took, part in them; 
but for the imaginative persons remaining at home, the idea of going 
to Palestine must have been like travelling into a supernatural world. 
When the compaign itself had a good effect, it must have been of a 
very fine and highly-tempered description. Chaucer's Knight, had 
been </p>

<lg xml:lang="en" type="original-quotation" xml:id="the-canterbury-tales" rend="center"><l>Sometime with the lord of Palatiee </l>
<l>Agen another hethen in Turkie : </l>
<l>And evermore he had a sovereign price; </l>
<l>And though that he was worthy, he was wise. </l>
<l>And of his port as meek as is a mayde. </l></lg>

<p>How like a return from the moon must have been the re-appearance 
of such travellers as Sir John Mandevile, Marco Polo, and 
William de Rubruquis, with their news of Prester John, the Great 
Mogul, and the Great Cham of Tartary! The long-lost voyager 
must have been like a person consecrated in all the quarters of 
heaven. His staff and his beard must have looked like relics of his 
former self. The Venetians, who were some of the earliest European 
travellers, have been remarked, among their other amiable qualities, 
for their great respect for strangers. The peculiarity of their position, 
amid the absence of so many things which are common-places to other 
countries, such as streets, horses, and coaches, add, no doubt, to 
this feeling. But a foolish or vain people would only feel a contempt 
for what they did not possess. Milton, in one those favourite 
passages of his, in which he turns a mere vocabulary into such grand 
meaning and music, shews us whose old footing he had delighted to 
follow. How he enjoys the distance; emphatically using the words, 
far, farthest, and utmost ! </p>
<cit><quote>
<lg xml:lang="en" type="original-quotation" xml:id="paradise-regained" rend="center"><l> — Embassies from regions far remote, </l>
<l>In various habits, on the Appian road. </l>
<l>Or on the Emilian; some from farthest south, </l>
<l>Syene, and where the shadow both way falls, </l>
<l>Meroe, Nilotick isle; and more to west. </l>
<l>The realm of Bocchus to the Black-moor sea; </l>
<l>From the Asian kings, and Parthian among these; </l>
<l>From India and the golden Chersonese, </l>
<l>And utmost Indian isle Taprobane. <bibl>— <title>Parad.</title> <biblScope>Reg. B. 4.</biblScope></bibl> </l></lg>
</quote></cit>

<p>One of the main helps to our love of remoteness in general, is the 
associations we connect with it of peace and quietness. Whatever 
there may be at a distance, people feel as if they should escape 
from the worry of their local cares. "O that I had wings like 
a dove! then would I fly away and be at rest." The word far is 
often used wilfully in poetry, to render distance still more distant. 
An old English song begins — </p>

<lg xml:lang="en" rend="center">
<l>In Irelande farre over the sea</l> 
<l>There dwelt a bonny king.</l> </lg>

<p>Thomson, a Scotchman, speaking of the western isles of his own 
country, has that delicious line, full of a dreary yet lulling pleasure : — </p>

<lg xml:lang="en" rend="center">
<l>As when a shepherd of the Hebrid isles,</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Placed far amid the melancholy main</hi>. </l></lg>

<pb n="72"/>

<p>In childhood, the total ignorance of the world, especially when we 
are brought up in some confined spot, renders every thing beyond 
the bounds of our dwelling a distance and a romance. Mr. Lamb, in 
his Recollections of Christ's Hospital, says that he remembers when some 
half-dozen of his schoolfellows set off, "without map, card, or 
compass, on a serious expedition to find out Philip Quarll's Island." We 
once encountered a set of boys as romantic. It was at no greater 
distance than at the foot of a hill near Hampstead; yet the spot was 
so perfectly Cisalpine to them, that two of them came up to us with 
looks of hushing eagerness, and asked, "whether, on the other side 
of that hill there were not robbers:" to which, the minor 
adventurer of the two added, "And some say, serpents." They had 
all got bows and arrows, and were evidently hovering about the 
place, betwixt daring and apprehension, as on the borders of some 
wild region. We smiled to think which it was that husbanded their 
suburb wonders to more, advantage, they or we : for while they peopled 
the place with robbers and serpents, we were peopling it with 
sylvans and fairies. </p>

<cit><quote><lg xml:lang="en" xml:id="my-heart-leaps-up" rend="center"><l>"So was it when my life began; </l> 
<l>So is it now I am a man; </l>
<l>So be it when I shall grow old. </l> 
<l>Or let me die I </l>
<l>The child is father to the man; </l>
<l>And I could wish my days to be </l>
<l>Bound each to each by natural piety."</l> </lg></quote>
<note type="source">
<bibl><author>William Wordsworth</author> : <title>My Heart Leaps Up</title></bibl></note></cit>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3">

<head type="header">PASSAGES FROM OSSIAN, ALLUDED TO IN OUR LAST. </head>

<p>On renewing our acquaintance with Ossian, we felt tempted to 
go to some length about him; but we must reserve our criticism for 
another time. The following are as many specimens of his uses of 
mist, as we have room for. The first is very grand; the second as 
happy in it's analogy; the third is ghastly, but of more doubtful 
merit. </p>

<p>TWO CHIEFS PARTED BY THEIR KING.—<cit><quote>"They sunk from the king on either 
side, like two columns of morning mist, when the sun rises between them on his 
glittering rocks. Dark is their rolling on either side, each toward its reedy pool." </quote><note type="source"><bibl>Macpherson, James: Temora (Book 4)</bibl></note></cit></p>

<p>A GREAT ENEMY.—<cit><quote>"I love a foe like Cathmor: his soul is great; his arm is 
strong; his battles are full of fame. But the little soul is like a vapour, that 
hovers round the marshy lake. It never rises on the green hill, lest the winds 
meet it there." </quote><note type="source"><bibl>Macpherson, James: Temora</bibl></note> </cit></p>

<p>A TERRIBLE OMEN.—<cit><quote>"A mist rose slowly from the lake. It came, in the 
figure of an aged man, along the silent plain. It's large limbs did not move in 
steps; for a ghost supported it in mid air. It came towards Selma's hall, and 
dissolved in a shower of blood."</quote><note type="source"><bibl>Macpherson, James: Carthon: A Poem</bibl></note></cit></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="colophon" rend="center">
                <p>Orders received by the Booksellers, by the Newsmen, and by the Publisher, <persName type="real" key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName>, 19, Catherine-street, Strand. –Price Twopence.</p>
                <p>Printed by <persName type="real" key="C. H. Reynell">C. H. Reynell</persName>, No. 45, Broad-street, Golden-square, London.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
 