<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <!-- File Description -->
        <fileDesc>
            <!-- Title of the work -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Indicator</title>
                <author>Hunt, James Henry Leigh (1784-1859)</author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <p />
            </publicationStmt>

            <!-- Author information -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Hunt, James Henry Leigh (1784-1859)</author>
                    <title>The Indicator</title>
                    <date when="1819-10-27">OCTOBER 27th, 1819</date> <!-- The publication date of this issue ({Month} {Day}, {Year}) -->
                    <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher> <!-- Publisher details if available -->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <!-- Encoding Description -->
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
            <p>
                Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers are
                included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
                preservation.
            </p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <!-- Profile Description -->
        <profileDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="issue" n="3">
                <pb n="17" /> <!-- Page beginning -->
                <div2 type="forematter"> <!-- Title, epigraph, and catalogue -->
                    <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                    <epigraph>
                    <p>There  is  a  bird  in  the  interior  of  Africa,  whose  habits  would  rather  seem  to  belong  to  the  interior  of Fairy-land:  but  they  have  been,  well  authenticated.  It  indicates  to  honey-hunters  where  the  nests  of  wild bees  are  to  be  found.  It  calls  them  with  a  cheerful  cry,  which  they  answer;  and  on  finding  itself  recognized, flies  and  hovers  over  a  hollow  tree  containing  the  honey.  While  they  are  occupied  in  collecting  it,  the  bird goes  to  a  little  distance,  where  he  observes  all  that  passes;  and  the  hunters,  wnen  they  have  helped  themselves, take  care  to  leave  him  his  portion  of  the  food. — This  is  the  <hi rend="smallcaps">Cuculus Indicator  of  Linnæus</hi>,  otherwise called  the  Moroc,  Bee  Cuckoo,  or  Honey  Bird.</p>
                        <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
                        <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                        <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
                        <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055"
                                cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                    </epigraph>
                    <head type="catalogue">No. I. <date when="1819-10-27">—WEDNESDAY, OCTOBER 27th, 1819</date>.</head>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="1"> <!-- Header and content -->
                    <head type="header"> GODIVA. </head>


<p>This is the lady, who under the title of Countess of Coventry, used  
to make such a figure in our childhood upon some old pocket-pieces  
of that city. We hope she is in great request there still; or the  
inhabitants deserve to be sent from Coventry. That city used to  
be famous in saintly legends for the visit of the eleven thousand  
virgins, — an "incredible number" saith Selden. But the eleven  
thousand virgins have vanished with their credibility; and a real  
noble-hearted woman of flesh and blood is Coventry's true immortality.</p>

<p>The story of Godiva is not a fiction, as many suppose it. At least  
it is to be found in Matthew of Westminster, and is not of a nature  
to have been a mere invention. Her name, and that of her husband,  
Leofric, are mentioned in an old charter recorded by another  
early historian. That the story is omitted by Hume and others  
argues little against it; for the latter are accustomed to confound  
the most interesting anecdotes of times and manners with something  
below the dignity of history (a very absurd mistake); — and Hume,  
of whose philosophy better things might have been expected, is  
notoriously less philosophical in his history than in any other of  
his works. A certain coldness of temperament, not unmixed with  
aristocratical pride, or at least with a great aversion from every thing  
like vulgar credulity, rendered his scepticism so extreme, that it  
became in spite of itself a sort of superstition in turn, and blinded  
him to the claims of every species of enthusiasm, civil as well as  
religious. Milton, with his poetical eyesight, saw better when he  
meditated the history of his native country. We do not remember  
whether he relates the present story; but we remember well, that  
at the beginning of his fragment on that subject, he says he shall  
relate doubtful stories as well as authentic ones, for the benefit of  
those, if no others, who will know how to make use of them,—  
namely, the poets.<note type="hunt" place="foot"> When Dr. Johnson, among his other impatient accusations of our great republican, charged him with telling unwarrantable stories in his history, he must  
haye overlooked this announcement; and yet, if we recollect, it is but in the  
second page of the fragment. So hasty, and blind, and liable to be put to shame  
is prejudice.</note> We have faith however in the story ourselves.</p>

<pb n="18"/>

<p>It has innate evidence enough for us, to give full weight to that of  
the old annalist. Imagination can invent a good deal; affection  
more: but affection can sometimes do things, such as the tenderest  
imagination is at least not in the habit of inventing; and this piece  
of noble-heartedness we believe to have been one of them.</p>

<p>Leofric, Earl of Leicester, was the lord of a large feudal territory  
in the middle of England, of which Coventry formed a part. He  
lived in the time of Edward the Confessor; and was so eminently a  
feudal lord, that the hereditary greatness of his dominion appears to  
have been singular even at that time, and to have lasted with an  
uninterrupted succession from Ethelbald to the Conquest, — a period  
of more than three hundred years. He was a great and useful  
opponent of the famous Earl Goodwin.</p>

<p>Whether it was owing to Leofric or not, does not appear; but  
Coventry was subject to a very oppressive tollage, by which it would  
seem that the feudal despot enjoyed the greater part of the profit  
of all marketable commodities. The progress of knowledge has  
shewn us how abominable, and even how unhappy for all parties,  
is an injustice of this description; yet it gives one an extraordinary  
idea of a mind in those times, to see it capable of piercing through  
the clouds of custom, of ignorance, and even of self-interest, and  
petitioning the petty tyrant to forego such a privilege. This mind  
was Godiva's. The other sex, always more slow to admit reason  
through the medium of feeling, were then occupied to the full in  
their warlike habits. It was reserved for a woman to anticipate  
whole ages of liberal opinion, and to surpass them in the daring  
virtue of setting a principle above a custom.</p>

<p>The countess entreated her lord to give up his fancied right; but  
in vain. At last, wishing to put an end to her importunities, he  
told her, either in a spirit of bitter jesting, or with a playful raillery  
that could not be bitter with so sweet an earnestness, that he would  
give up his tax, provided she rode through the city of Coventry,  
naked. She took him at his word; and said she would. One may  
imagine the astonishment of a fierce unlettered chieftain, not  
untinged with chivalry, at hearing a woman, and that too of the greatest  
delicacy and rank, maintaining seriously her intention of acting  
in a manner contrary to all that was supposed fitting tor her sex,  
and at the same time forcing upon him a sense of the very beauty  
of her conduct by it's principled excess. It is probable, that as he  
could not prevail upon her to give up her design, ixe had sworn  
some religious oath when he made his promise : but be this as it  
may, he took every possible precaution to secure her modesty from  
hurt. The people of Coventry were ordered to keep within doors, to  
close up all their windows and outlets, and not to give a glance into  
the streets upon pain of death. The day came; and Coventry, it  
may be imagined, was silent as death. The lady went out at the  
palace door, was set on horseback, and at the same time divested of  
her wrapping garment, as if she had been going into a bath; then  
taking the fillet from her head, she let down her long and lovely  
tresses, which poured around her body like a veil; and so, with only </p>

<pb n="19"/>

<p>her white legs remaining conspicuous, took her gentle way through  
the streets. <note type="hunt" place="foot"> <q xml:lang="latin">"Nuda,"</q> says Matthew of Westminster, <q xml:lang="latin">"equum ascendens, erines capitis et tricas dissolvens, corpus suum totum, prjeter crura candidissima, inde velavit."</q> See Selden's Notes to the Polyolbion of Drayton. Song 13. It is Selden from whom we learn, that Leofric was Earl of Leicester, and the other particulars of him mentioned above. The Earl was buried at Coventry, his Countess most  
probably, in the same tomb. </note> </p>

<p>What scene can be more touching to the imagination, — beauty,  
modesty, feminine softness, a daring sympathy; an extravagance,  
producing by the nobleness of it's object and the strange gentleness  
of it's means, the grave and profound effect of the most reverend  
custom. We may suppose the scene taking place in the warm noon;  
the doors all shut, the windows closed; the earl and his court serious  
and wondering; the other inhabitants, many of them gushing with  
gi-ateful tears, and all reverently listening to hear the footsteps of  
the horse; and lastly, the lady herself, with a downcast but not a  
shamefaced eye, looking towards the earth through her flowing  
locks, and riding through the dumb and deserted streets, like an  
angelic spirit.</p>

<p>It was an honourable superstition in that part of the country, that  
a man who ventured to look at the fair saviour of his native town,  
was struck blind. But the vulgar use to which this superstition has  
been turned by some writers of late times, is not so honourable. The  
whole story is as unvulgar and as sweetly serious, as can be conceived.</p>

<p>Drayton has not made so much of this subject, as might have been  
expected; yet what he says, is said well and earnestly.</p>

<cit><quote><lg><l>Coventry at length </l>
<l>From her small, mean regard recovered state and strength; </l>
<l>By Leofric her lord, yet in base bondage held, </l>
<l>The people from her marts by tollage were expelled; </l>
<l>Whose dutchess which desired this tribute to release. </l>
<l>Their freedom often begged.  The duke, to make her cease. </l>
<l>Told her, that if she would his loss so far enforce. </l>
<l>His will was, she should ride stark naked upon a horse </l>
<l>By daylight through the street : which certainly he thought </l>
<l>In her heroic breast so deeply would have wrought. </l>
<l>That in her former suit she would have left to deal. </l>
<l>But that most princely dame, as one devoured with zeal, </l>
<l>Went on, and by that mean the city clearly freed. </l></lg></quote></cit>

<p>We wonder that none of our painters have yet drawn us Godiva  
upon her horse. They can hardly have met with the subject, or  
surely they would have fallen in love with it.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2">
<head type="header">PLEASANT RECOLLECTIONS CONNECTED WITH VARIOUS PARTS OF THE METROPOLIS.</head>

<p>One of the best secrets of enjoyment is the art of cultivating  
pleasant associations. We spoke of this in our first number, and  
shall often have occasion to recur to it. It is an art that of  
necessity increases with the stock of our knowledge; and though in  
acquiring our knowledge we must encounter disagreeable associations
<pb n="20"/>
also, yet if we secure a reasonable quantity of health by the way  
these will be far less in number than the agreeable ones: for unless  
the circumstances which gave rise to the associations, press upon  
us; it is only from want of health that the power of throwing off  
these burdensome images becomes suspended.</p>

<p>And the beauty of this art is, that it does not insist upon pleasant  
materials to work on. Nor indeed does health. Health will give us  
a vague sense of delight, in the midst of objects that would teaze  
and oppress us during sickness. But healthy association peoples this  
vague sense with agreeable images. It will relieve us, even when  
a painful sympathy with the distresses of others becomes a part of  
the very health of our minds. For instance, we can never go  
through St. Giles's, but the sense of the extravagant inequalities in  
human condition presses more forcibly upon us; but some pleasant  
images are at hand even there to refresh it. They do not displace  
the others, so as to injure the sense of public duty which they  
excite; they only serve to keep our spirits fresh for their task, and  
hinder them from running into desperation or hopelessness. In  
St. Giles's Church lie Chapman, the earliest and best translator of  
Homer; and Andrew Mar veil, the wit and patriot, whose poverty  
Charles the Second could not bribe. We are as sure to think of  
these two men, and of all the good and pleasure they have done to  
the world, as of the less happy objects about us. The steeple of the  
church itself too is a handsome one; and there is a flock of pigeons  
in that neighbourhood, which we have stood with great pleasure to  
see careering about it of a fine afternoon, when a western wind had  
swept back the smoke towards the city, and shewed the white of  
the stone steeple piercing up into a blue sky. So much for St.  
Giles's, whose very name is a nuisance with some. It is dangerous  
to speak disrespectfully of old districts. Who would suppose  
that the Borough was the most classical ground in the metropolis?  
And yet it is undoubtedly so. The Globe theatre was there, of  
which Shakspeare himself was a proprietor, and for which he wrote  
his plays. Globe-lane, in which it stood, is still extant, we believe,   
under that name. It is probable that he lived near it : it is certain  
that he must have been much there. It is also certain that on the  
Borough side of the river, then and still called the Bank side, in the  
same lodging, having the same wardrobe, and some say, with other  
participations more remarkable, lived Beaumont and Fletcher. In  
the Borough also, at St. Saviour's, lie Fletcher and Massinger in  
one grave; in the same church, under a monument and effigy, lies  
Chaucer's contemporary, Gower; and from an inn in the Borough,  
the existence of which is still boasted, and the scite pointed out by a  
picture and inscription, Chaucer sets out his pilgrims and himself on  
their famous road to Canterbury.</p>

<p>To return over the water, who would expect any thing poetical  
from East Smithfield? Yet there was born the most poetical even  
of poets, Spenser. Pope was born within the sound of Bow-bell, in  
a street no less anti-poetical than Lombard-street. So was Gray, in  
Cornhill. So was Milton, in Bread-street, Cheapside. The presence 
<pb n="21"/>
of the same great poet and patriot has given happy memories to  
many parts of the metropolis. He lived in St. Bride's Churchyard,  
Fleet-street; in Aldersgate-street, in Jewin-street, in Barbican,  
in Bartholomew - close; in Holborn, looking back to Lincoln's  
Inn Fields; in Holborn, near Red Lion-square; in Scotland-yard  
in a house looking to St. James's Park, now belonging to an  
eminent writer on legislation, and lately occupied by a celebrated  
critic and metaphysician; and he died in the Artillery-walk,  
Bunhill-Fields; and was buried in St. Giles's, Cripplegate.</p>

<p>Ben Jonson, who was born "in Hartshorne-lane, near Charing-cross,"  
was at one time "master" of a theatre in Barbican. He  
appears also to have visited a tavern called the Sun and Moon, in  
Aldersgate-street; and is known to have frequented, with  
Beaumont and others, the famous one called the Mermaid, which was  
in Cornhill. Beaumont, writing to him from the country in an epistle  
full of jovial wit, says.</p>

<cit><quote><lg>
<lg xml:id="verse1"><l>The sun, which doth the greatest comfort bring. </l>
<l>To absent friends, because the self-same thing </l>
<l>They know they see, however absent, is </l>
<l>Here our best haymaker : forgive me this : </l>
<l>It is our country style : — in this warm shine </l>
<l>I lie, and dream of your full Mermaid wine. </l>
</lg>
<l>* * * * * *</l>  
<lg xml:id="verse2"><l>Methinks the little wit I had, is lost, </l>
<l>Since I saw you; for wit is like a rest </l>
<l>Held up at tennis, which men do the best </l>
<l>With the best gamesters. What things have we seen </l>
<l>Done at the Mermaid. Hard words that have been </l>
<l>So nimble, and so full of subtle flame. </l>
<l>As if that every one from whom they came </l>
<l>Had meant to put his whole wit in a jest. </l>
<l>And had resolved to live a fool the rest </l>
<l>Of his dull life. Then, when there hath been thrown </l>
<l>Wit, able enough to justify the town </l>
<l>For three days past, — wit, that might warrant be </l>
<l>For the whole city to talk foolishly </l>
<l>Till that were cancelled, and when that was gone. </l> 
<l>We left an air behind us, which alone </l>
<l>Was able to make the two next companies </l>
<l>Right witty, — though but downright fools, more wise. </l>
</lg>
</lg>
</quote>
<note type="source"><bibl><title>The Mermaid</title><author>Francis Beaumont</author></bibl></note>
</cit>

<p>The other celebrated report of the great wits of that time, was the  
Devil Tavern, in Fleet-street, close to Temple-Bar. Ben Jonson  
lived also in Bartholomew-close, where Milton afterwards lived. It  
is. in the passage from the cloisters of Christ's Hospital into St.  
Bartholomew's, Aubrey gives it as a common opinion, that at the time  
when Jonson's father-in-law made him help him in his business of  
bricklayer, he worked with his own hands upon the Lincoln's Inn  
garden wall, which looks upon Chancery-lane, and which seems old  
enough to have some of his illustrious brick and mortar still remaining.</p>

<p>Under the cloisters in Christ's Hospital (which stand in the heart  
of the city unknown to most persons, like a house kept invisible for  
young and learned eyes) lie buried a multitude of peisons of all  
ranks; for it was once a monastery of Grey Friars. Among them is  
John of Bourbon, one of the prisoners taken at the battle of Agincourt.</p>

<pb n="22"/>

<p>Here also lies Thomas Burdet, ancestor of the present Sir  
Francis, who was put to death in the reign of Edward the Fourth,  
for wishing the horns of a favourite white stag which the king had  
killed, in the body of the person who advised him to do it. And  
here too (a sufficing contrast) lies Isabella, wife of Edward the Second,</p>

<lg><l>She, wolf of France, with unrelenting fangs. </l>
<l>Who tore the bowels of lier mangled mate. — Gray. </l></lg>

<p>Her "mate's" heart was buried with lier, and placed upon her  
bosom ! a thing that looks like the fantastic incoherence of a dream.  
It is well we did not know of her presence when at school; or after  
reading one of Shakspeare's tragedies, we should have run twice as  
fast round the cloisters at night time, as we used. Camden, "the  
nourrice of antiquitie," received part of his education in this school;  
and here also, not to mention a variety of others known in the  
literary world, were bred two of the most powerful and deep-spirited  
writers of the present day; whose visits to the cloisters we well  
remember.</p>

<p>In a palace on the scite of Hatton Garden, died John of Gaunt.  
Brook House, at the corner of the street of that name in Holborn,  
was the residence of the celebrated Sir Fulke Greville, Lord Brook,  
the "friend of Sir Philip Sydney." In the same street, died, by a  
voluntary death, of poison, that extraordinary person Thomas  
Chatterton, — </p>

<q>The sleepless boy, who perished in his pride.  
<persName type="real" key='William Wordsworth'>Wordsworth</persName>.</q>

<p>He was buried in the workhouse in Shoe Lane; — a circumstance, at  
which one can hardly help feeling a movement of indignation. Yet  
what could beadles and parish officers know about such a being?  
No more than Horace Walpole. In Gray's Inn lived, and in Gray's  
Inn garden meditated. Lord Bacon. In Southampton Row, Holborn,  
Cowper was a fellow-clerk to an attorney with the future Lord  
Chancellor Thurlow. At the Fleet Street corner of Chancery Lane,  
Cowley, we believe, was born. In Salisbury Court, Fleet Street, was  
the house of Thomas Sackville, first Earl of Dorset, the precursor  
of Spenser, and one of the authors of the first regular English  
tragedy. On the demolition of this house, part of the ground was  
occupied by the celebrated theatre built after the Restoration, at  
which Betterton performed, and of which Sir William Davenant was  
manager. Lastly, here was the house and pi'inting-office of Richardson.  
In Bolt-court, not far distant, lived Dr. Johnson, who resided  
also for some time in the Temple. A list of his numerous other  
residences is to be found in Boswell.<note type="hunt" place="foot">The Temple must have had many eminent inmates. Among them it is believed was Chaucer, who is also said, upon the strength of an old record, to have been fined two shillings for beating a Franciscan friar in Fleet Street. </note> Congreve died in Surrey-street, in the Strand, at his own house. At the corner of Beaufort-buildings,  
was Lilly's, the perfumer, at whose house the Tatler was published.  
In Maiden-lane, Covent-garden, Voltaire lodged while in  
London, at the sign, of the White Peruke, Tavistock-street was
<pb n="23"/>
then, we believe, the Bond-street of the fashionable world; as Bow-  
street was before. The change of Bow-street from fashion to the police,  
with the theatre still in attendance, reminds one of the spirit of the  
Beggar's Opera. Button's Coffee-house, the resort of the wits of Queen  
Anne's time, was in Russell-street,— we believe, near where the  
Hummums now stand. We think we recollect reading also, that in  
the same street, at one of the corners of Bow-street, was the tavern  
where Dryden held regal possession of the arm chair. The whole  
of Covent-garden is classic ground, from its association with the  
dramatic and other wits of the times of Dryden and Pope. Butler  
lived, perhaps died, in Rose-street, and was buried in Covent-garden  
Church-yard; where Peter Pindar the other day followed him. In  
Leicester-square, on the scite of Miss Linwood's exhibition and other  
houses, was the town mansion of the Sydneys, Earls of Leicester,  
the family of Sir Philip and Algernon Sydney. In the same square  
lived Sir Joshua Reynolds. Dryden lived and died in Gerrard-street,  
in a house which looked backwards into the garden of Leicester  
House. Newton lived in St. Martin's-street, on the south side of  
the square. Steele lived in Bury-street, St. James's: he furnishes an  
illustrious precedent for the loungers in St. James's-street, where a  
scandal-monger of those times delighted to detect Isaac BickerstafF in  
the person of Captain Steele, idling before the Coffee-houses, and  
jerking his leg and stick alternately against the pavement. We  
have mentioned the birth of Ben Jonson near Charing-cross. Spenser  
died at an inn, where he put up on his arrival from Ireland, in  
King-street, Westminster, — the same which runs at the back of  
Parliament-street to the Abbey. Sir Thomas More lived at Chelsea.  
Addison lived and died in Holland-House, Kensington, now the  
residence of the accornplished nobleman who takes his title from it.  
In Brook-street, Grosvenor-square, lived Handel; and in Bentinck-  
street, Manchester-square. Gibbon. We have omitted to mention  
that De Foe kept a hosier's shop in Cornhill; and that on the scite  
of the present Southampton-buildings, Chancery-lane, stood the  
mansion of the Wriothesleys, Earls of Southampton, one of whom  
was the celebrated friend of Shakspeare. But what have we not  
omitted also? No less an illustrious head that the Boar's, in  
East-cheap,— the Boar's Head Tavern, the scene of Falstaff's revels. We  
believe the place is still marked out by a similar sign. But who  
knows not East-cheap and the Boar's Head? Have we not all been  
there time out of mind? And is it not a more real as well as  
notorious thing to us than the London Tavern, or the Crown and  
Anchor, or the Hummums, or White's, or What's-his-name's, or any  
other of your contemporary and fleeting taps? </p>

<p>But a line or two, a single sentence in an author of former times,  
will often give a value to the commonest object. It not only gives  
us a sense of its duration, but we seem to be looking at it in company   
with its old observer; and we are reminded at the same time of all that  
was agreeable in him. We never saw, for instance, even the gilt ball  
at the top of the College of Physicians, without thinking of that  

<pb n="24"/>

pleasant mention of it. in Garth's Dispensary, and of all the wit syad 
generosity of that amiable man : —</p> 

<lg><l>Not far from that most celebrated place, <note> The Old Bailey </note> </l>
<l>Where angry Justice shews her awful face; </l>
<l>Where little villains must submit to fate </l>
<l>That great ones may enjoy the world in state; </l>
<l>There stands a dome, majestic to the sight. </l>
<l>And sumptuous arches bear it's oval height; </l>
<l>A golden globe, placed high with artful skill. </l>
<l>Seems, to the distant sight, a gilded pill. </l></lg>

<p>Gay, in describing the inconvenience of the late narrow part of  
tlie Strand, by St. Clement's, took away a portion of it's unpleasantness  
to the next generation, by associating his memory with the  
objects in it. We did not miss without regret even the "combs"  
that hung "dangling in your face" at a shop which be describes,  
and which was standing till the improvements took place. The rest  
of the picture is still alive. (Trivia, Book 3d.) </p> <!--encoder bibl!!!-->

<lg><l>Where the fair columns of St. Clement stand. </l> 
<l>Whose straitened bounds encroach upon the Strand; </l>
<l>Where the low pent-house bows the walker's head. </l>
<l>And the rough pavement wounds the yielding tread; </l>
<l>Where not a post protects the narrow space. </l>
<l>And strung in twines, combs dangle in thy face; </l>
<l>Summon at once thy courage, rouse thy Care, </l>
<l>Stand firm, look back, be resolute, beware. </l>
<l>Forth issuing from steep lanes, the collier's steeds </l>
<l>Drag the black load; another cart succeeds; </l>
<l>Team follows team, crouds heaped on crouds appear, </l>
<l>And wait impatient till the road grow clear. </l></lg>

<p>There is a touch in the winter picture in the same poem, which  
every body will recognize : — </p>

<lg><l>At White's the harnessed chairman idly stands, </l>
<l>And swings around his waist his tingling hands. </l></lg>

<p>The bewildered passenger in the Seven Dials is compared to Theseus  
in the Cretan Labyrinth. And thus we come round to the point at  
which we began.</p>

<p>Before we rest our wings, however, we must take another drift  
over the city, as far as Stratford at Bow, where, with all due tenderness  
for boarding-school French, a joke of Chaucer's has existed as a  
piece of local humour for nearly four hundred and fifty years. Speaking  
of the Prioress, who makes such a delicate figure among his  
Canterbury Pilgrims, he tells us, among her other accomplishments,  
that </p>

<l>French she spake full faire and featously; </l>
<p>adding with great gravity.</p>
<lg><l>After the school of Stratford atte Bowe; </l> 
<l>For French of Paris was to her unknowe. </l></lg>

</div2>
 <div2 type="correspondents"> <!-- Publisher and printer information -->
                <p>[ Persons in the country who  wish to become subscribers, should therefore order it of booksellers who send weekly or monthly parcels to their respective places of residence. The delay would be of little consequence with a work not containing  
                any thing of merely temporary interest.] </p> 
 </div2>
<div2 type="colophon" rend="center">
                <p>Orders received by the Booksellers, by the Newsmen, and by the Publisher, <persName type="real" key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName>, 19, Catherine-street, Strand. –Price Twopence.</p>
                <p>Printed by <persName type="real" key="C. H. Reynell">C. H. Reynell</persName>, No. 45, Broad-street, Golden-square, London.</p>
 </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
  