<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://cwrc.ca/templates/css/tei.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>THE INDICATOR.</title>
                <title type="sub">No. XX.--WEDNESDAY, FEBRUARY 23rd, 1820.</title>
                <author>Leigh Hunt</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p />
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc sameAs="http://www.cwrc.ca">
                <p>Created from original research by members of CWRC/CSÉC unless
                    otherwise noted.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson> <!-- This format is borrowed from the Folger Shakespeare TEIs -->
                    <person xml:id="Cont">
                        <persName type="standard">Contarini</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Cont.</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mol">
                        <persName type="standard">Molilo</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Mol.</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Seb">
                        <persName type="standard">Sebastian</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Seb.</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Cand">
                        <persName type="standard">Candian</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Cand.</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Greg">
                        <persName type="standard">Gregory</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Greg.</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Van">
                        <persName type="standard">Vanni</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Van.</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Fiam">
                        <persName type="stadard">Fiammetta</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Fiam.</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Vit">
                        <persName type="standard">Vittoria</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Vit.</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mal">
                        <persName type="standard">Malipiero</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Mal.</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Herb">
                        <persName type="standard">Walter Herbert</persName>
                        <persName type="form">Herb.</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="issue" n="21">
                <pb n="161" />
                <div2 type="forematter"> 
                <head type="title" rend="center">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                <epigraph rend="center">
                    <l>There he arriving round about doth flie</l>
                    <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                    <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.<note type="citation"><bibl><ref target="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Elizabeth_Spencer,_Baroness_Hunsdon"/></bibl></note></l>
                    <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055" cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                </epigraph>
                <head type="subtitle" rend="center">No. XXI.—<date when="1820-03-01" cert="high">WEDNESDAY, MARCH 1st, 1820</date>.</head>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="1">
                <head type="header" rend="center">SCENES FROM AN UNFINISHED DRAMA.</head>
                <p>THE following scenes are from a play which the Editor intended 
                    to write, and belonged to the more serious part of it. The rest he 
                    has retained for another purpose. The objects of the piece in gene-
                    ral were to shew the character of an English gentleman in the time 
                    of Elizabeth; the manners at the same period of the Venetians, both 
                    rich and poor; and the generous struggle of a mother to suppress a 
                    passion she conceived for our countryman, who had saved her daughter 
                    from drowning. The accident, like the scheme of Pollexfen in Sir 
                    Charles Grandison, had been purposely contrived by a Venetian of
                    darker character, Malipiero, as the only means of gaining the young
                    lady's affection; but the Englishman was quicker to rescue her, and 
                    so threw him doubly aback. The incidents, or rather the dialogues, 
                    which took place imediately after this circumstance, occup the 
                    scenes now laid before the reader. Vittoria and Flammetta, the mother 
                    and daughter, are of a similar character for goodness and frankness; 
                    but the one is the more stately minded, the other sparkling and full 
                    of spirits. Candian, her grand-uncle, Sebastian, her brother, Mo-
                    lino, Contarini, and Malipiero, are Venetian gentlement, the four first 
                    of different characters of sprightliness or warmth; the last an intel-
                    igent man like the rest, but of a violent and envious disposition. 
                    Vanni and Gregory are the servants of Candian and the Englishman. 
                    With Walter Herbert the Englishman, and indeed with most of the 
                    others, it is lucky perhaps that the author had nothing farther to 
                    do; for he intended him as one of those high and graceful spirits, in 
                    the best age of this country, who were admitted to the society of its 
                    poets and other great men.
                </p>
                <q type="written">For <hi rend="italic">valour</hi>, <hi rend="italic">is</hi> not Love a Hercules?</q>
                </div2>
                <pb n="162" />
                <div2 type="scene" n="1">
                    <sp who="#Cont">
                        <speaker>Contarini.</speaker>
                        <l>The Englishmen indeed, Sir, have graced us, </l>
                        <l>Not we the Englishmen. How instantly </l>
                        <l>Sebastian's friend laid himself out o' the boat, </l>
                        <l>Before our thoughts had time to find themselves, </l>
                        <l>And gave us back our pale one.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Mol">
                        <speaker>Molilo.</speaker>
                        <l>Like a god </l> <!-- How can this be formatted to show it completes Contarini's previous line? -->
                        <l>In his own element. 'Twas a strange thing,—</l>
                        <l>That sudden shock. I never knew the like </l>
                        <l>Happen before in Venice, though our gondolas </l>
                        <l>Serve us for every purpose of the road, </l>
                        <l>And pierce about like fish.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cont">
                        <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                        <l>It marred so too </l>
                        <l>The stately self-possesion of the day, </l>
                        <l>Especially before our naval emulators. </l>
                        <l>How Malipiero's vexed!</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Mol">
                        <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
                        <l>He seized directly </l>
                        <l>Piero, the gondolier, who is supposed </l>
                        <l>To have meant this mischief out of some revenge </l>
                        <l>Towards his good master; and conveyed him off </l>
                        <l>With his fierce fist against the scoundrel's throat.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cont">
                        <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                        <l>That's settled then. Some singular punishment </l>
                        <l>Will mark this singular disgrace of Venice.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <stage type="entrance" rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> Sebastian.</stage>
                    <sp who="#Mol">
                        <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
                        <l>How are the ladies now?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Sebastian.</speaker>
                        <l>Quite well again.</l>
                        <l>'Twas but a fright at last, though a severe one.</l>
                        <l>Fiammetta sparkles like a flower new washed, </l>
                        <l>And turns it all, as she is wont to do, </l>
                        <l>To chearfulness and grace.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cont">
                        <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                        <l>A charming lady.</l>
                        <l>But how's your mother?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
                        <l>She's recovered too;</l>
                        <l>Yet though she had no drowning, takes on still, </l>
                        <l>Kissing my sister's hand, and cheek, and pressing her, </l>
                        <l>And then again turning to plenteous tears, </l>
                        <l>As if she wept for all that might have happened.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Mol">
                        <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
                        <l>I have observed it so: the heart, as 'twere, </l>
                        <l>Takes pity on itself, and so turns fond </l>
                        <l>On it's own gentle nature.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, when tears </l>
                        <l>Come, as these do, seldom, and out of sweetness.</l>
                        <l>My dearest mother is of a true clay, </l>
                        <l>Much like her daughter; only former trouble—</l>
                        <l>The loss of a loved partner,—made her quit </l>
                        <l>The dance, and sit her down in a still patience, </l>
                        <l>Happy to see us nevertheless enjoy it.</l>
                        <l>She seldom weeps: but now that this rude shock </l>
                        <l>Has shaken up the long-collecting fountains,</l>
                        <l>She bathes her heart's great thirst.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <stage type="entrance" rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> Candian.</stage>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>Piero's escaped.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
                        <l>Escaped?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>Escaped,—in an unguarded moment.</l>
                        <l>Poor Malipiero reddens for mere rage, </l>
                        <l>And will not patiently endure to hear </l>
                        <l>Even the English praised:—he says their coming </l>
                        <l>Is a bad omen.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Mol">
                        <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
                        <l>'Tis his vehemence.</l>
                        <l>He's vexed at the escape; and to speak truly, </l>
                        <pb n="163" />
                        <l>I think his natural emulation chides him </l>
                        <l>For not being quicker than the Englishman.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cont">
                        <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                        <l>He'll make it up to him with double praise.</l>
                        <l>This jealousy in noble spirits runs forth </l>
                        <l>For it's own self, only to turn again </l>
                        <l>With a new shape of ardour, and perform </l>
                        <l>Another's messages to fame more quickly.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
                        <l>It does so. I have heard my noble friend </l>
                        <l>Our visitor say, that spirits which have wings </l>
                        <l>Of muscular root enough to winnow up, </l>
                        <l>As they go on, the petty from the great, </l>
                        <l>Find something more succesful than success </l>
                        <l>Itself, or rather than the name of it,—</l>
                        <l>Succeeding most where they most realize </l>
                        <l>Their own calm world of beauty, and inspire </l>
                        <l>A self-divested sense of it in others: </l>
                        <l>Like odour-wafting airs in summer-time,</l>
                        <l>In which the odour's praised, though not the air.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>'Tis wondered at by some, that Piero escaped; </l>
                        <l>And certainly 'tis strange, especially </l>
                        <l>AS his own tribe are jealous of their fame, </l>
                        <l>And fall, like clamourous birds, upon foul play.</l>
                        <l>Yet as to what concerns our anxious friend, </l>
                        <l>Who is to wonder, that a spirit like his, </l>
                        <l>Unused to keep constrained it's very thoughts, </l>
                        <l>Should let his generous hand forget it's hold, </l>
                        <l>And find it a bad jail.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cont">
                        <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
                        <l>Who, Sir, indeed?</l>
                        <l>But we'll detain you, gentlemen, no longer </l>
                        <l>From our fair friends; pray tell them of our joy, </l>
                        <l>And willing envy of the Englishman.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay we will praise, and thank him, but not envy.</l>
                        <l>We can afford, I hope, to let a foreigner </l>
                        <l>Plunge in our waters for a lady's sake,</l>
                        <l>Without making the windows stare the wider, </l>
                        <l>And lift their stony brows up in astonishment.</l>
                        <l>But he's a gallant fellow, and we'll tell him so.</l>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="2">
                    <stage type="setting" rend="center">SCENE.—The front of the Candian Palace.</stage>
                    <stage type="entrance" rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> Gregory.</stage>
                    <sp who="#Greg">
                        <speaker>Gregory.</speaker>
                        <p>This comes of travelling. It seems all a dream. I'm not sure that 
                            I sha'n't wake and find myself in the arms of the dear old chair at the Bull. My 
                            master, whom it is impossible to resist, offers me to go with him; I consent; and 
                            so he ties me in a manner to his coat like a witch, and off I go; first scouring over 
                            the road to the seaside; then rocking up and down, up and down, till I'm sick; 
                            then scouring away again; then dragged up mountains into the clouds, till my 
                            teeth chatter for fear and cold; then whew! down again like a flourish on paper; 
                            then jolted along, all unbuttoned for heat; then bitten till I could have got the 
                            sign of the comb to scratch me; or scraped acquaintance with a brick wall; or 
                            taken to the cunning custom of flogging myself for penance; or winced, and 
                            tumbled, and beaten myself and the very air about me, like a shirt hung out to 
                            dry in a high wind:—then comes some more sea-rocking, and then says my 
                            master, <q type="spoken">Now, Gregory, we land for good:</q>—thinks I, looking about me, and 
                            seeing nothing but canals for streets, and houses standing out of them like so 
                            many cows in a pond,——I hope we don't land for evil: and I had scarcely 
                            thought the word, when we took to boating it again, and hey! presto! down 
                            goes that Will-o'-the-wisp, my master, souse over head and ears after a fish in 
                            petticoats.
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                    <stage type="entrance" rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> Vanni.</stage>
                    <sp who="#Van">
                        <speaker>Vanni.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, Gregory, this is a strange unaccountable circumstance, isn't it!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <pb n="164" />
                    <sp who="#Greg">
                        <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                        <p>What, a fall in the water! not half so strange to me, Vanni, as that 
                            you Venetians will have so much water to fall in.
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Van">
                        <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                        <p>If we hadn't so much water to fall in, we shouldn't have so much love 
                            to fall in. Our shews and our shews-off by day, our gondolas, and our serenades, 
                            what should we do without them? And the water causes or sweetens them all. 
                            You'll hear guitars to night twinkling about like stars. I won my mistress's 
                            heart by a plunge higher than was known before into the River of Song!
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Greg">
                        <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                        <p>How these Venetians do talk! Guitars twinkling about like stars! and 
                            a plunge into the River of Song! there's a name for a canal! It's fine talking, 
                            and sometimes puts me in mind of my master's friends, Master Shakespeare and the 
                            others at the mermaid; but what name comes home to me like the manly and 
                            natural one of Fleet Ditch!
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Van">
                        <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                        <p>You seem sad, Gregory. We shall cheer you up before long. We have 
                            everything here to make a man merry,—rowing, laughing, sunshine, music, wo-
                            men, every thing.
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Greg">
                        <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Sir,—no, Sir,—you haven't my wife and Bunhill-fields.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Van">
                        <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                        <p>There's plenty of fields over the water, and as to your wife, my dear Gre-
                            gory, I never heard you talk much about her before. Besides, she told you she 
                            should be quite happy, you know; and she looked so.
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Greg">
                        <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                        <p>Ah, Sir, and then you pretend that the English women are not so chear-
                            ful as your's. Oh, I never loved my wife more than now I am in the thick of 'em. 
                            Oh, how I loved her during the squall at sea! and how prodigiously I did love 
                            her, when I thought I should have broken my neck on the top of the Alps! I hope, 
                            Sir, you found your intended as well as could be expected after your absence.
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Van">
                        <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                        <p>Better than ever: as hearty as you'll find your wife, Gregory:—but how 
                            formal and ceremonious you seem to think it necessary to be in your pathetics. 
                            Come, man, I'll shew you the lions, as you used to say, and keep my word for better 
                            too, as far as stone lions can go; and then I'll introduce you to Momola. She'll 
                            rouse your spirits for you. We'll cross the way to St. Mark's. Bartolo, there! 
                            Hallo! Mind the canal, Gregory, you'll run over the parapet.
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Greg">
                        <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord! the very dangers in this place have nothing Christian about 
                            them! We can't even be run over by a horse, but must be warned how a parapet 
                            is run over by a man.
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Van">
                        <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                        <p>We'll go round by the bridge if you prefer it, Gregory.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Greg">
                        <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                        <p>Ah, do.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Van">
                        <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                        <p>Never mind, then, Bartolo, this time.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Greg">
                        <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                        <p>Perhaps I shall have the pleasure of meeting with some dust.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <stage type="exit" rend="italic rightJustified">[Exeunt.</stage>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="3">
                    <stage type="setting" rend="center">SCENE.—An apartment in the Palace Candian. Vittoria and Fiam-
                        metta sitting together, with books, music, and flowers about them; 
                        the former with her face towards a looking-glass, adjusting some-
                        thing about her head.
                    </stage>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>My dear, dear mother, let me make you merry again.</l>
                        <l>I'm merry.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>Be so, child,—be so, dear child.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>You see how stout I am; I'm drest before you.</l>
                        <l>'Twas but a kind of unexpected bath.</l>
                        <l>'Twas frightful to be sure; the sudden missing </l>
                        <l>Of one's dry senses,—the deaf plunge and bubbling, </l>
                        <l>And wrapping up in heavy wateriness: </l>
                        <l>But now that it is past, somehow or other, </l>
                        <l>One feels the grander for it, and, poor soul!</l>
                        <l>Fancies one's accident a grand achievement!</l>
                        <l>You're absent, mother! You're in the boat still!</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>No more of that, my love, I have you fast;</l>
                        <l>Your brother is come home, our noble bird, </l>
                        <l>Nobler than ever! What can I want more </l>
                        <l>To make me happy? I believe I want </l>
                        <l>Some pain to pinch away these foolish tears, </l>
                        <l>And make me, as before, give smile for smile.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <pb n="165" />
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>Shall I read to you, mother?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>No, my child.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>Or sing? or dance? or bring your favourite picture </l>
                        <l>Of Dido playing with the cheeks of Cupid, </l>
                        <l>As if she said unwittingly, "You rogue!"</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh no, no, no! talk to me of things common; </l>
                        <l>Of dress, for instance, flounces, coifs, and fashions, </l>
                        <l>And what new creature we're to look like next, </l>
                        <l>When some great lady quarrels with her shoulder-blade, </l>
                        <l>Or has a private pique against her waist.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh, if no waist, like a tied sack of charcoal, </l>
                        <l>Or like the letter B run up to seed; </l>
                        <l>And if a waist, why then we must be wasps </l>
                        <l>Cut right in two, or hour-glasses that shew </l>
                        <l>The time by letting their wise heads run empty.</l>
                        <l>Or if we must be neither, we'll preside </l>
                        <l>O'er hoops, like busts upon a cupola; </l>
                        <l>Or turn to real walking bells, with feet </l>
                        <l>For double clappers; and let mother church </l>
                        <l>Look to high winds, or we'll have belfry and all, </l>
                        <l>For bonnet, with the penthouse, and stick in it </l>
                        <l>The whole FLower-Market and the shops of plumes, </l>
                        <l>And all the Sunday ribbons in the parish.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>Why you dash on this morning like Sebastian, </l>
                        <l>Along your gay reflections in wit's gondola.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>And you must think of gondolas again, </l>
                        <l>And sigh, dear mother. Well, if you will think of 'em, </l>
                        <l>Pray tell me now what think you of the Englishman; </l>
                        <l>Taking him in the common light, you know,—</l>
                        <l>His look, his figure; for to say the truth, </l>
                        <l>Only don't tell, I've hardly seen him yet; </l>
                        <l>Though I've the recollection at my heart </l>
                        <l>Of—</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>What, my love?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>. . . . . . His terrible pinching fingers.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>Why, you sweet trifler! this is the way, is it, </l>
                        <l>You treat a — gentleman that saves your life.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>A gentleman that saves one's life! Well, really now, </l>
                        <l>That is a proper philosophic way </l>
                        <l>Of putting it, before we've got the right </l>
                        <l>Of speaking highlier of him for himself. </l>
                        <l>You mean, I know, you dare not trust yourself </l>
                        <l>Just now, upon that watery subject, mother;—</l>
                        <l>But this, believe me, is the very way </l>
                        <l>To speak of such good chances giv'n the gentlemen. </l>
                        <l>From what I've read, there are some ladies who </l>
                        <l>Think one such plunge renders a man invulnerable </l>
                        <l>To all objection. By their rule, one ought </l>
                        <l>To save one's life, only to lose one's freedom; </l>
                        <l>Begging the gentleman, that since a shark </l>
                        <l>Was not to have you, or since he had kindly </l>
                        <l>Taken the trouble to pick you up, he'd have you. </l>
                        <l>Tis lucky, mother, the same principle </l>
                        <l>Does not extend to limbs, or 'twould be requisite </l>
                        <l>To give one's hand for saving it a scratch; </l>
                        <l>Or when a dog was hindered of his bite, </l>
                        <l>Present one's foot with an elaborate stretch, </l>
                        <l>Like a French dancer, and say, "Gracious Sir, </l> <!-- How to mark cross line quotation ??-->
                        <l>You saved this foot of mine; will't please ye accept it?"</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh rattler, rattler! How am I to know </l>
                        <l>That all this smiling surface of your talk </l>
                        <l>Has not grave ground beneath?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <pb n="166" />
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>. . . . Nay, other, now </l>
                        <l>You make me blush to think that I could give </l>
                        <l>More than my thaks at first to one of whom </l>
                        <l>I know so little; grateful thanks, 'tis true, </l>
                        <l>Most grateful,—but—I'm sure <emph rend="italic">you</emph> think a man </l>
                        <l>Should shew that he has picked up a few qualities </l>
                        <l>As well as ladies, ere he picks our hearts. </l>
                        <l>My brother, to be sure, is fond of truth, </l>
                        <l>Extremely fond,—but then as uncle said—</l>
                    </sp>
                    <stage type="entrance" rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> Candian, <hi rend="italic">followed by</hi> Molino, Contarini, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> Malipiero.</stage>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>And what did uncle say? Ladies, allow me—</l>
                        <l>The Signor Malipiero, a sad gentleman, </l>
                        <l>Who thinks it necessary to apologize </l>
                        <l>For not being a king-fisher.—We found him </l>
                        <l>Eyeing his would-be element at the door.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Mal">
                        <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, Sir, I yield to none in hearty chearfulness; </l>
                        <l>And as I hope and think the best of others, </l>
                        <l>'Tis thought, I trust, of me: and yet, dear ladies, </l>
                        <l>A man may reasonably regret, that chance </l>
                        <l>Should on the turn, as 'twere, of one swift instant, </l>
                        <l>Whisk him from shewing all his zeal for ye.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>My daughter loves a good intention, Sir, </l>
                        <l>Too well to make it answerable to fortune.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Mal" toWhom="Fiam">
                        <speaker>Mal. </speaker>
                        <stage type="delivery">(to Fiam.)</stage>
                        <l>Then, Madam, I may hope that this omission </l>
                        <l>Will not be held a punishable sin, </l>
                        <l>When heavenly eyes look down upon one's homage.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>If you mean my eyes, Signor Malipiero, </l>
                        <l>Which heaven forbid should look down on tall gentlemen, </l>
                        <l>I think no evil of our other friends here, </l>
                        <l>And why should I of you?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>Come, Malipiero, </l>
                        <l>Settle these grave state questions by and bye, </l>
                        <l>For here's Sebastian and the Englishman: </l>
                        <l>I saw them from the window, coming in.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <stage type="entrance" rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> Servant.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <l>Signor Sebastian, and his noble friend, Sir.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <stage type="entrance" rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> Sebastian <hi rend="italic">and</hi> Walter Herbert.</stage>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
                        <l>Dear mother, uncle, sister sweet, and gentlemen, </l>
                        <l>I need not introduce my noble friend </l>
                        <l>And your's—the Signor Walter Herbert, Englishman.</l>
                        <l>Dear Walter, this is the affectionate circle </l>
                        <l>I've told you of so often. Heaven be praised </l>
                        <l>You're in the midst of it, and have been so.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>Our silence, Sir, must shew you what we feel, </l>
                        <l>This ready swiftness to oblige your friends, </l>
                        <l>Is, I perceive, a habit with you.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>If, Sir, </l>
                        <l>Winning their ready kindness be obliging them. </l>
                        <l>'Tis counted so by some.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, the best thanks  </l>
                        <l>A mother can pay to you, who has been </l>
                        <l>Made breathless with two rushing visitations, </l>
                        <l>Terror and joy, is to shew what you saved for her:—</l>
                        <l>My daughter, Sir.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>A pearl indeed, whose sight </l>
                        <l>Would pay a fathomless plunge.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l><emph rend="italic" cert="medium">I</emph> cannot, Sir, </l>
                        <l>Pay compliments; I fear, I had expected—</l>
                        <l>I thank you, Sir, from bottom of my heart.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <pb n="167" />
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>I am paid, Madam, beyond compliment,—</l>
                        <l>Almost beyond surprise, to think that two </l>
                        <l>Such spirits from the earthly heaven of womanhood </l>
                        <l>Should stand before me—pardon me this burst,—</l>
                        <l>And fancy that they owed me any thing.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>You can pay compliments at any rate, Sir, </l>
                        <l>Whether we must or not.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>You make me vain, Madam; </l>
                        <l>And vanity assumes the right to praise, </l>
                        <l>Where silence is best worship.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, Sir, I neither </l>
                        <l>Deny your right, nor, to say truth, our pleasure. </l>
                        <l>We feel but doubly flattered to conjecture </l>
                        <l>That you are driven by your sympathy </l>
                        <l>Out of your plainer path.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb</speaker>
                        <l>You judge me, Madam, </l>
                        <l>Truly and nobly.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>You're no friend then, Sir, </l>
                        <l>To compliment in general?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh yes, Sir, </l>
                        <l>Where 'tis th' escape of pleased sincerity, </l>
                        <l>And not so needlessly alone, as shews it </l>
                        <l>Vanity and a superfluous common-place.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>And what, Sir, as to taking compliments?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>It seems to me, Madam, as I presume </l>
                        <l>It does to you, by your reception of them, </l>
                        <l>That not to take a compliment in general, </l>
                        <l>With leaning rather to the praiser's feelings </l>
                        <l>Than his true sight, or our own better merits, </l>
                        <l>Argues self-love rather than modesty.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>You see, Sir, we have scarcely yet recovered </l>
                        <l>Our drowning, and our gratitude. Come, this weight </l>
                        <l>Of mutual homage bows us into ceremony </l>
                        <l>In our own spite. It must give way to something </l>
                        <l>Quite as respectful, and more easy and pleasant: </l>
                        <l>Mutual enjoyment.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
                        <l>The right proposition.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>I feel the hand of home, Sir, in this grasp.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, Walter, we but fancy we're new friends here;</l>
                        <l>We are as old ones the tastes we love.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>And friends ave other privileges in England.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                        <l>Ay, and in most places. Come, girls, your cheeks.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <stage type="business" rend="rightJustified">(Herbert <hi rend="italic">kisses them</hi>.)</stage>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <stage type="delivery" rend="italic">(aside).</stage>
                        <l>I told you how 'twould be, Mother.</l>
                        <l>My cheek's gone off already.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>And your heart; </l>
                        <stage type="delivery" rend="italic">(aside).</stage>
                        <l>She blushes, and I fear I do so too:—</l>
                        <l>I have most cause.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
                        <stage type="delivery">(to Fiam.)</stage>
                        <l>Well, Sister gravity, and have you no praises </l>
                        <l>AS well as cheeks?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, just as many as friends </l>
                        <l>Would wish to have just now;—at least I think so.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>Your brother could not be more gladly answered, </l>
                        <l>Nor I more honoured.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Mal">
                        <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                        <l>'Tis an answer, Sir, </l>
                        <l>Befitting the coy oracle that sits </l>
                        <l>Within a maid's sincerity: but suffer </l>
                        <l>Us to give louder grace to your achievement, </l>
                        <l>And hail you at the shrine whose present goddess </l>
                        <l>You have preserv'd. It was a happy deed, </l>
                        <l>And might have made us watery champions jealous, </l>
                        <l>Did it not ev'n outbenefit envy.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <pb n="168" />
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>That </l>
                        <l>Were to outdo the deeds of Hercules, </l>
                        <l>And make old Atlas turn to kiss his burden, </l>
                        <l>Like a borne lass. Your generous spirit, Sir, </l>
                        <l>Sees, like an eye, ore infinite things outside it, </l>
                        <l>Than ever it would boast to hold itself. </l>
                        <l>You measure my desert by your great joy.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Mal">
                        <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                        <l>Is not this contradicting you own sentiment, </l>
                        <l>A little so at least,—denying us </l>
                        <l>The pride of giving you what you give others?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>Well, Sir, to shew you I can claim my due, </l>
                        <l>And have my benefits returned, I'll ask </l>
                        <l>This lady to speak for me, and to own </l>
                        <l>That what would have been done by any gentleman </l>
                        <l>Should not be charged so brightly on my scutcheon.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Fiam">
                        <speaker>Fiam.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, Sir, I'll own still more, and plainly tell you, </l>
                        <l>And that without the fear of being tossed back </l>
                        <l>Into the sea for my ingratitude, </l>
                        <l>that I insinuated as much just now </l>
                        <l>To Signor Malipiero here himself. </l>
                        <l>Did I not, gentlemen? And did I rate </l>
                        <l>You, Signor Contarini, or you, Sir, </l>
                        <l>For not being quicker than our other friend, </l>
                        <l>And catching me no agues!—Pardon me, </l>
                        <l>But I should have asked, Sir, whether you suffered </l>
                        <l>The least - - no clinging chilliness, I trust, </l>
                        <l>Or other - -</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Herb">
                        <speaker>Herb.</speaker>
                        <l>Not the least, Madam; no more </l>
                        <l>Than if I had put my hand into a brook, </l>
                        <l>To bring away a lily. I had heard </l>
                        <l>Of your own welfare: and if I had not, </l>
                        <l>I see—You, Madam, 
                            <stage type="delivery" rend="italic">(to Vit.)</stage> 
                            scarcely seem so well, 
                        </l>
                        <l>As when I first came in.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Vit">
                        <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh quite, Sir, thank you, </l>
                        <l>I feel the ebbing of these waters yet </l>
                        <l>At intervals. Quite well, child,—quite indeed. </l>
                        <l>Uncle, we're getting at our compliments </l>
                        <l>Again.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Cand">
                        <speaker>Indeed! I fear I've scarcely given our friend </speaker>
                        <l>A proper English welcome. Well; I hope </l>
                        <l>You'll spend the day with us, and teach us how </l>
                        <l>To interchange each other's cordial customs. </l>
                        <l>My nephew tells me you must leave ys now </l>
                        <l>To visit the ambassador. Be it so; </l>
                        <l>But come back quickly—will you? that's well looked: </l>
                        <l>For you must know, you have a face, young gentleman, </l>
                        <l>As full of dialogue as my neice's here.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp who="#Seb">
                        <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
                        <l>In the evening we shall have a masquerade, </l>
                        <l>Which was already intended, and will serve </l>
                        <l>To let the whole tide of congratulation </l>
                        <l>Come in at once. A dance, a little music, </l>
                        <l> Hearts at their merriest, faces at their best, </l>
                        <l>And after all, a look into the still </l>
                        <l>And smiling ferment of our starry hour, </l>
                        <l>Whose ear is kissed with waters gently spooned, </l>
                        <l>Whose nightingale is Love, shall give you a taste </l>
                        <l>Of Venice to the core.</l>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="colophon">
                    <p>Orders received by the Booksellers, by the Newsmen, and by the Publisher, <persName type="real" key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName>, No. 19, Catherine-street, Strand—Price 2d.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Printed by <persName type="real" key="C. H. Reynell">C. H. Reynell</persName>, No. 45, Broad-street, Golden-square.
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>