<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!-- Template Version 1.1 [FOR REFERENCE - DO NOT DELETE] -->
<!-- This template is intended to be used as a starting point for encoding a new text.
        It is not intended as a fixed structure, but rather collects some of the most common
        structural elements for convenience and uniformity. Please add/remove elements as
        necessary for your use case. -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <!-- File Description -->
        <fileDesc>
            <!-- Title of the work -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Indicator</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                    <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                    <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <p />
            </publicationStmt>

            <!-- Author information -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>
                        <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                        <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                        <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                    </author>,
                    <title>The Indicator</title>
                    <date when="1820-01-19">January 19, 1820</date> <!-- The publication date of this issue ({Month} {Day}, {Year}) -->
                    <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher> <!-- Publisher details if available -->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <!-- Encoding Description -->
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
            <p>
                Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers are
                included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
                preservation.
            </p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <!-- Profile Description -->
        <profileDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="issue" n="15">
                <pb n="113" /> <!-- Page beginning -->
                <div2 type="title"> <!-- Title, epigraph, and catalogue -->
                    <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                    <epigraph>
                        <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
                        <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                        <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
                        <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055"
                                cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                    </epigraph>
                    <head type="catalogue">No. XV.—WEDNESDAY, JANUARY 19th, 1820.</head>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="1"> <!-- Header and content -->
                    <head type="header" rend="uppercase">SPIRIT OF THE ANCIENT MYTHOLOGY.</head>
                    <p>From having a different creed of our own, and always encountering the heathen
                        mythology in a poetical and fabulous shape, we are apt to have a false idea
                        of the religious feeling of the ancients. We are in the habit of supposing,
                        whatever we allow when we come to reason upon the point, that they regarded
                        their fables in the same poetical light as ourselves; that they could not
                        possibly put faith in <persName key="Jupiter" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q11024" cert="high" type="mythological">Jupiter</persName>,
                        <persName key="Neptune" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q39851" cert="high" type="mythological">Neptune</persName>, and <persName key="Pluto" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q41675" cert="high" type="mythological">Pluto</persName>;
                        in the sacrifice of innocent turtle doves, the libation of wine, and the
                        notions about <placeName key="Tartarus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q183602" cert="high" type="mythological">Tartarus</placeName> and <persName key="Ixion" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q272302" cert="high" type="mythological">Ixion</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Undoubtedly there were multitudes of free thinkers in the ancient world. Most
                        of the Greek poets and philosophers appear to have differed with the literal
                        notions of the many.<note type="hunt">* It is remarkable that <persName key="Aeschylus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q40939" cert="high" type="real">Æschylus</persName> and <persName key="Euripides" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q48305" cert="high" type="real">Euripides</persName>, the two dramatists whose faith in the national religion was most doubted, are said to have met with strange and violent deaths.—The latter was torn to pieces by dogs, and the former killed by a tortoise which an eagle let fall upon his bald head in mistake for a stone. These exits from the scene look very like the retributive death-beds which the bigots of all religions are so fond of ascribing to one another.</note> A system of refined theism is understood to have been taught to
                        the initiated in the celebrated Mysteries. The doctrines of <persName key="Epicurus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q43274" cert="high" type="real">Epicurus</persName> were
                        so prevalent in the most intellectual age of <placeName key="Rome" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q220" cert="high" type="city">Rome</placeName>, that <persName key="Lucretius" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1936" cert="high" type="real">Lucretius</persName>
                        wrote a poem upon them, in which he treats their founder as a divinity; and
                        <persName key="Virgil" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1398" cert="high" type="real" xml:id="virgil">Virgil</persName>, in a well-known passage of the <title level="m" key="Georgics" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q216127">Georgics</title>, <q type="foreign" xml:lang="latin">"Felix qui
                            potuit"</q> &amp;c. exalts either <persName key="Epicurus" ref="#Epicurus">Epicurus</persName> or <persName key="Lucretius" ref="#Lucretius">Lucretius</persName> as a blessed being, who put
                        hell and terror under his feet. A sickly temperament appears to have made
                        him wish, rather than be able, to carry his own scepticism so far: yet he
                        insinuates his disbelief in <placeName key="Tartarus" ref="#Tartarus">Tartarus</placeName> in the sixth book of his epic poem, where <persName key="Aeneas" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q100808" cert="high" type="mythological">Æneas</persName> and the <persName key="Sibyl" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q240673" cert="high" type="mythological">Sybil</persName>, after the description of the lower
                        world, go out through the ivory gate, which was the passage of false
                            visions.<note type="hunt">† Did <persName key="Dante Alighieri" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1067" cert="high" type="real">Dante</persName> forget this, when he took <persName ref="#virgil">Virgil</persName> for his guide through the <title level="m" key="Inferno" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1313360">Inferno</title>?</note>
                        <persName key="Julius Caesar" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1048" cert="high" type="real">Cæsar</persName>, according to a speech of his in Sallust, derided the same
                        notions in open Senate; and <persName key="Cicero" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1546" cert="high" type="real" xml:id="cicero">Cicero</persName>, in other parts of his writings, as well as
                        in a public pleading, speaks of them as fables and impertinence,—<q type="foreign" xml:lang="latin">"ineptiis ac fabulis."</q></p>
                    <pb n="114" />
                    <p>But however this plain-dealing may look on the part of the men of letters,
                        there is reason to believe that even in those times, the people in general
                        were strong upon points of faith. The extension of the Greek philosophy may
                        have insensibly rendered them familiar with latitudes of interpretation on
                        the part of others. They would not think it impious in <persName ref="#cicero">Cicero</persName> and
                        <persName key="Cato the Younger" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q281895" cert="high" type="real">Cato</persName> to have notions of the Supreme Being more consistent
                        with the elevation of their minds. But for themselves, they adhered, from
                        habit, to the literal creed of their ancestors, as the Greek populace had
                        done before them. The jealous enemies of <persName key="Socrates" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q913" cert="high" type="real">Socrates</persName> contrived to
                        have him put to death on a charge of irreverence for the gods. A frolic of
                        the libertine <persName key="Alcibiades" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q200725" cert="high" type="real">Alcibiades</persName>, which to say the least of it, was in
                        very bad taste,—the defacing the <objectName key="statues of Mercury" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q204423" cert="high" type="sculpture">statues of
                            Mercury</objectName>,—was followed with important consequences. The history
                        of <persName key="Socrates" ref="#Socrates">Socrates</persName> had the effect, in after times, at least in the ancient world,
                        of saving philosophical speculators from the vindictive egotism of opinion.
                        But even in the days of <persName key="Augustus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1405" cert="high" type="real">Augustus</persName>, <persName key="Ovid" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1403" cert="high" type="real">Ovid</persName> wrote a
                        popular work full of mythological fables; and <persName ref="#virgil">Virgil</persName> himself,
                        whose creed perhaps only rejected what was unkindly, gave the hero of his
                        intended popular epic, the particular appellation of Pious. That <persName key="Augustus" ref="#Augustus">Augustus</persName> should pique himself on the same attribute, proves
                        little; for he was a cold-blooded man of the world, and could play the
                        hypocrite for the worst and most despotic purposes. Did he now and then
                        lecture his poetical friends upon this point, respecting their own
                        appearances with the world ? There is a curious ode of <persName key="Horace" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q6597" cert="high" type="real">Horace</persName> (<title level="a" key="Ode 34" ref="https://www.google.com/search?q=Horace+Odes+Book+1+Ode+34">Book 1. Od. 34.</title>) in which he says that he finds himself compelled to give up his sceptical notions, and to attend more to public worship, because it had thundered one day when, the sky was cloudless. The critics are divided in their opinion of his object in this ode. Some think him in earnest, others in jest. It is the only thing of the sort in his works; and is, at all events, of an equivocal character that would serve his purpose on either side of the question.</p>
                    <p>The opinions of the ancients upon religion may be divided into three general
                        classes. The great multitude believed any thing; the very few disbelieved
                        every thing, the philosophers and poets entertained a refined natural
                        religion, which while it pronounced upon nothing, rejected what was evidently
                        unworthy of the spirit; of the creation, and regarded the popular deities, as
                        personifications of it's various workings. All these classes had their
                        extravagances, in proportion to their ignorance, or viciousness, or
                        metaphysical, perplexity. The multitude, whose notions were founded on
                        ignorance, habit, and fear, admitted many absurd and some cruel
                        imaginations. The mere man of the world measured every thing by his own vain
                        and petty standard, and thought the whole goods of the universe a scramble
                        for the cunning and hypocritical. The over-refining followers of <persName key="Plato" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q859" cert="high" type="real">Plato</persName>,
                        endeavouring to pierce into the nature of things by the mere effort of the
                        will, arrived at conclusions visible to none but their own yearning and
                        impatient eyes; and lost themselves in the ethereal dogmatisms of <persName key="Plotinus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q193026" cert="high" type="real">Plotinus</persName> and <persName key="Porphyry" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q213233" cert="high" type="real">Porphyry</persName>.</p>
                    <p>The greatest pleasure arising to a modern imagination from the</p>
                    <pb n="115" />
                    <p>ancient mythology, is in a mingled sense of the old popular belief and of the
                        philosophical refinements upon it. We take <persName key="Apollo" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q34417" cert="high" type="mythological">Apollo</persName>, and <persName key="Mercury" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q11023" cert="high" type="mythological">Mercury</persName>, and <persName key="Venus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q47657" cert="high" type="mythological">Venus</persName>, as shapes that existed in popular
                        credulity, as the greater fairies bf the ancient world; and we regard them,
                        at the same time, as personifications of all that is beautiful and genial in
                        the forms and tendencies of creation. But the result, coming as it does too
                        through avenues of beautiful poetry, both ancient and modern, is so entirely
                        <choice><orig>chearful</orig><reg>cheerful</reg></choice>, that we are apt to think it must have wanted gravity to more
                        believing eyes. We fancy that the old world saw nothing in religion but
                        lively and graceful shapes, as remote from the more obscure and awful
                        hintings of the world unknown, as physics appear to be from the
                        metaphysical;—as the eye of a beautiful woman is from the inward
                        speculations of a <persName key="Brahmin" cert="low" type="group">Brahmin</persName>; or a lily at noon-day from the wide
                        obscurity of night-time.</p>
                    <p>This supposition appears to be carried a great deal too far. We will not
                        enquire in this place, how far the mass of mankind, when these shapes were
                        done away, did or did not escape from a despotic anthropomorphitism; nor how
                        far they were driven by the vaguer fears, and the opening of a more visible
                        eternity, into avoiding the whole subject, rather than courting it; nor how
                        it is, that the nobler practical religion which was afforded them, has been
                        unable to bring back their frightened theology from the angry and avaricious
                        pursuits into which they fled for refuge. But setting aside the portion of
                        terror, of which heathenism partook in common with all faiths originating in
                        uncultivated times, the ordinary run of pagans were perhaps more impressed
                        with a sense of the invisible world, in consequence of the very visions
                        presented to their imagination, than the same description of men under a more
                        shadowy system. There is the same difference between the two things, as
                        between a populace believing in fairies, and a populace not believing. The
                        latter is in the high road to something better, if not drawn aside into new
                        terrors on the one hand, or mere worldliness on the other. But the former is
                        led to look out of the mere worldly commonplaces about it, twenty times to the
                        other's once. It has a sense of a supernatural state of things, however gross.
                        It has a link with another world, from which somethink like gravity is sure to
                        strike into the most <choice><orig>chearful</orig><reg>cheerful</reg></choice> heart. Every forest, to the mind's eye of a Greek,
                        was haunted with superior intelligences. Every stream had it's presiding
                        nymph, who was thanked for the draught of water. Every house had it's
                        protecting gods, which had blessed the inmate's ancestors; and which would
                        bless him also, if he cultivated the social affections: for the same word
                        which expressed piety towards the Gods, expressed love towards relations and
                        friends. If in all this there was nothing but the worship of a more graceful
                        humanity, there may be worships much worse as well as much better. And the
                        divinest spirit that ever appeared on earth has told us, that the extension
                        of human sympathy embraces all that is required of us, either to do or to
                        foresee.</p>
                    <p>Imagine the feelings with which an ancient believer must have gone by the
                        <placeName key="Dodona" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q827993" cert="high" type="physical">oracular oaks of Dodona</placeName>, or the <placeName key="Groves of the Eumenides" cert="medium" type="physical">calm groves of the
                            Eumenides</placeName>, or the fountain where <persName key="Proserpine" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q151978" cert="high" type="mythological">Proserpine</persName> vanished
                        underground with <persName key="Pluto" ref="#Pluto">Pluto</persName>; or the <placeName key="Eleusis" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q216960" cert="high" type="building">Great Temple of the
                            Mysteries at Eleusis</placeName>; or the <placeName key="Mount Parnassus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q105267" cert="high" type="physical">laurelled mountain Parnassus</placeName>, on the side of
                        which was the <placeName key="Delphi" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q131442" cert="high" type="building">temple of Delphi</placeName>, where <persName key="Apollo" ref="#Apollo">Apollo</persName> was supposed to be present
                        in person. Imagine <persName key="Plutarch" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q174176" cert="high" type="real">Plutarch</persName>, a devout and yet a liberal believer, when
                        he went to study theology and philosophy at <placeName key="Delphi" ref="#Delphi">Delphi</placeName>: with what feelings must he not
                        have passed along the woody paths of the hill, approaching nearer every
                        instant to the presence of the divinity, and not sure that a glance of light
                        through the trees was not the lustre of the god himself going by. This is
                        mere poetry to us, and very fine it is; but to him it was poetry, and
                        religion, and beauty, and gravity, and hushing awe, and a path as from one
                        world to another.</p>
                    <p>With similar feelings he would cross the ocean, an element that naturally
                        detaches the mind from earth, and which the ancients regarded as especially
                        doing so. He had been in the <placeName key="Carpathian Sea" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2333038" cert="high" type="physical">Carpathian sea</placeName>, the favourite
                        haunt of <persName key="Proteus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q213491" cert="high" type="mythological">Proteus</persName>, who was supposed to be gifted above every
                        other deity with a knowledge of the causes of things. Towards evening, when
                        the winds were rising, and the sailors had made their vows to <persName key="Neptune" ref="#Neptune">Neptune</persName>, he would think of the old <q type="distinct">"shepherd of the seas, of
                            yore,"</q> and believe it possible that he might become visible to his
                        eyesight, driving through the darkling waters, and turning the sacred
                        wildness of his face towards the blessed ship.</p>
                    <p>In all this, there is a deeper sense of another world, than in the habit of
                        contenting oneself with a few vague terms and embodying nothing but <persName key="Mammon" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q723930" cert="high" type="mythological">Mammon</persName>. There is a deeper sense of another world, precisely
                        because there is a deeper sense of the present; of it's varieties, it's
                        benignities, it's mystery. It was a strong sense of this, which made a
                        living poet, who is accounted very orthodox in his religious opinions, give
                        vent, in that fine sonnet, to his impatience at seeing the beautiful planet
                        we live upon, with all it's starry wonders about it, so little thought of,
                        compared with what is ridiculously called the world. He seems to have dreaded
                        the symptom, as an evidence of materialism, and of the planets being dry
                        self-existing things, peopled with mere successive mortalities, and
                        unconnected with any superintendance or consciousness in the universe about
                        them. It is abhorrent from all we think and feel, that they should be so: and
                        yet Love might make heavens of them, if they were.</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en" rend="center">
                                <l><q type="spoken">"The world is too much with us. Late and soon,</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Getting and spending, we lay waste our powers:</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Little we see in Nature that is ours:</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">We have given our hearts away, a sordid boon!</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">This Sea that bares her bosom to the moon;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">The Winds that will be howling at all hours,</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">And are <choice><orig>npgathered</orig><reg>ungathered</reg></choice> now like sleeping flowers;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">For this, for every thing, we are out of tune;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">It moves us not.—Great God! I'd rather be</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">A Pagan suckled in a creed outworn,</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">So might I, standing on this pleasant lea,</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Have glimpses that would make me less forlorn;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Have sight of <persName key="Proteus" ref="#Proteus">Proteus</persName> coming from the sea;</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Or hear old <persName key="Triton" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q163884" cert="high" type="mythological">Triton</persName> blow his wreathed horn."</q></l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl>
                                <author><persName key="William Wordsworth" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q46777" cert="high" type="real">William Wordsworth</persName></author>
                                <title level="a" key="The world is too much with us" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2900746">The world is too much with us</title>
                            </bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <pb n="117" />
                    <head type="header" rend="uppercase">GETTING UP ON COLD MORNINGS.</head>
                    <p>An Italian author,—<persName key="Giulio Cordara" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1527712" cert="high" type="real">Giulio Cordara</persName>, a Jesuit,—has written a <title level="m" key="De natura et usu insectorum" ref="https://books.google.com/books/about/De_natura_et_usu_insectorum_poemation.html?id=oJzJjVqQkQIC">poem upon Insects</title>, which he begins by insisting, that those troublesome and abominable little animals were created for our annoyance, and that they were certainly not inhabitants of Paradise. We of the North may dispute this piece of theology; but on the other hand, it is as clear as the snow on the house-tops, that <persName key="Adam" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q79549" cert="high" type="biblical">Adam</persName> was not under the necessity of shaving; and that when <persName key="Eve" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q540509" cert="high" type="biblical">Eve</persName> walked out of her delicious bower, she did not step upon ice three inches thick.</p>
                    <p>Some people say it is a very easy thing to get up of a cold morning. You have
                        only, they tell you, to take the resolution; and the thing is done. This may
                        be very true; just as a boy at school has only to take a flogging, and the
                        thing is over. But we have not at all made up our minds upon it; and we find
                        it a very pleasant exercise to discuss the matter, candidly, before we get
                        up. This at least is not idling, though it may be lying. It affords an
                        excellent answer to those, who ask how lying in bed can be indulged in by a
                        reasoning being,—a rational creature. How? Why with the argument calmly at
                        work in one's head, and the clothes over one's shoulder. Oh—it is a fine
                        way of spending a sensible, impartial half-hour.</p>
                    <p>If these people would be more charitable, they would get on with their
                        argument better. But they are apt to reason so ill, and to assert so
                        dogmatically, that one could wish to have them stand round one's bed of a
                        bitter morning, and lie before their faces. They ought to hear both sides of
                        the bed, the inside and out. If they cannot entertain themselves with their
                        own thoughts for half an hour or so, it is not the fault of those who can.
                        If their will is never pulled aside by the enticing arms of imagination, so
                        much the luckier for the stage-coachman.</p>
                    <p>Candid inquirers into one's decumbency, besides the greater or less
                        privileges to be allowed a man in proportion to his ability of keeping early
                        hours, the work given his faculties, &amp;c., will at least concede their
                        due merits to such representations as the following. In the first place, says
                        the injured but calm appealer, I have been warm all night, and find my system
                        in a state perfectly suitable to a warm-blooded animal. To get out of this
                        state into the cold, besides the inharmonious and uncritical abruptness of the
                        transition, is so unnatural to such a creature, that the poets, refining upon
                        the tortures of the damned, make one of their greatest agonies consist in
                        being suddenly transported from heat to cold,—from fire to ice. They are
                        <q type="spoken">"haled"</q> out of their <q type="spoken">"beds,"</q> says <persName key="John Milton" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q13904" cert="high" type="real">Milton</persName>, by <q type="spoken">"harpy-footed furies,"</q>—fellows who come to call them.—On my first
                        movement towards the anticipation of getting up, I find that such parts of the
                        sheets and bolster, as are exposed to the air of the room, are stone cold. On
                        opening my eyes, the first thing that meets them is my own breath rolling
                        forth, as if in the open air, like smoke out of a cottage-chimney. Think of
                        this symptom. Then I turn my eyes sideways and see the window all frozen over.
                        Think of that. Then the servant comes in. <q type="spoken">"It is very cold this
                            morning, is it not?"</q>—</p>
                    <pb n="118" />
                    <p><q type="spoken">"Very cold, Sir."</q>—<q type="spoken">"Very cold indeed, isn't it?"</q>—<q type="spoken">"Very cold indeed, Sir."</q>—<q type="spoken">"More than usually so, isn't
                            it, even for this weather?"</q> (Here the servant's wit and good nature are
                        put to a considerable test, and the inquirer lies on thorns for the answer.)
                        <q type="spoken">"Why, Sir- - - -I think it is."</q> (Good creature! There is not a better, or more
                        truth-telling servant going.) <q type="spoken">"I must rise however—Get me some
                            warm water."</q>—Here comes a fine interval between the departure of the
                        servant and the arrival of the hot water; during which, of course, it is of
                        <q type="distinct">"no use"</q> to get up. The hot water comes. <q type="spoken">"Is it quite hot?"</q>—<q type="spoken">"Yes, Sir."</q>—<q type="spoken">"Perhaps too hot for shaving: I must wait a
                            little ?"</q>—<q type="spoken">" No, Sir; it will just do."</q> (There is an over-nice propriety
                        sometimes, an officious zeal of virtue, a little troublesome.) <q type="spoken">"Oh— the
                            shirt—you must air my clean shirt:—linen gets very damp this
                            weather."</q>—<q type="spoken">Yes, Sir."</q> Here another delicious five minutes. A knock at
                        the door. <q type="spoken">"Oh, the shirt—very well. My stockings—I think the
                            stockings had better be aired too."</q> —<q type="spoken">" Very well. Sir."</q>—Here another
                        interval. At length every thing is ready, except myself. I now, continues
                        our incumbent (a happy word, by the bye, for a country vicar)—I now cannot
                        help thinking a good deal—who can?—upon the unnecessary and villainous
                        custom of shaving: it is a thing so unmanly (here I nestle closer)—so
                        effeminate (here I recoil from an unlucky step into the colder part of the
                        bed.)—No wonder, that the <persName key="Queen Marie Antoinette" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q46200" cert="high" type="real">Queen of France</persName> took part with the rebels
                        against that <persName key="Louis XVI of France" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q7732" cert="high" type="real">degenerate King, her husband</persName>, who first affronted her smooth visage with a face like her own.
                        The <persName key="Julian the Apostate" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q134106" cert="high" type="real">Emperor Julian</persName> never showed the luxuriancy of his
                        genius to better advantage than in reviving the flowing beard. Look at
                        <persName key="Pietro Bembo" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q469857" cert="high" type="real">Cardinal Bembo's</persName> picture—at <persName key="Michelangelo" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5592" cert="high" type="real">Michael Angelo's</persName>—at <persName key="Titian" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q42327" cert="high" type="real">Titian's</persName>—at <persName key="William Shakespeare" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q692" cert="high" type="real">Shakspeare's</persName>—at <persName key="John Fletcher (playwright)" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q333060" cert="high" type="real">Fletcher's</persName>—at <persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="#EdmundSpenser">Spenser's</persName>—at <persName key="Geoffrey Chaucer" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5667" cert="high" type="real">Chaucer's</persName>—at <persName key="Alfred the Great" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q82895" cert="high" type="real">Alfred's</persName>—at <persName key="Plato" ref="#Plato">Plato's</persName>.—I could name a great man for every
                        tick of my watch.— Look at the Turks, a grave and otiose people.—Think of
                        <persName key="Harun al-Rashid" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q193655" cert="high" type="real">Haroun Al Raschid</persName> and <persName key="Bed-ridden Hassan" cert="medium" type="fictional">Bed-ridden Hassan</persName>—Think of <persName key="Edward Wortley Montagu (1713-1776)" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q3048866" cert="high" type="real">Wortley Montague</persName>, the worthy son of his mother, a man above the
                        prejudice of his time—Look at the Persian gentlemen, whom one is ashamed of
                        meeting about the suburbs, their dress and appearance are so much finer than
                        our own—Lastly, think of the razor itself—how totally opposed to every
                        sensation of bed—how cold, how edgy, how hard! how utterly different frond
                        any thing like the warm and circling amplitude, which</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en" rend="center">
                                <l><q type="spoken">Sweetly recommends itself</q></l>
                                <l><q type="spoken">Unto our gentle senses.</q></l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl>
                                <author><persName key="William Shakespeare" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q692" cert="high" type="real">William Shakespeare</persName></author>
                                <title level="m" key="Macbeth" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q130870">Macbeth</title>
                                <biblScope unit="act">Act I</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="scene">Scene VI</biblScope>
                            </bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p>Add to this, benumbed fingers, which may help you to cut yourself, a quivering
                        body, a frozen towel, and an ewer full of ice; and he that says there is
                        nothing to oppose in all this, only shews, at any rate, that he has no merit
                        in opposing it.</p>
                    <p><persName key="James Thomson (poet)" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q363840" cert="high" type="real">Thomson the poet</persName>, who exclaims in his <title level="m" key="The Seasons (Thomson)" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2567990">Seasons</title>—</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en" rend="center">
                                <l><q type="spoken">Falsely luxurious! Will not man awake?</q></l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl>
                                <author><persName key="James Thomson (poet)" ref="#JamesThomsonPoet">James Thomson</persName></author>
                                <title level="m" key="The Seasons (Thomson)" ref="#TheSeasonsThomson">The Seasons</title>
                                <biblScope unit="book">Spring</biblScope>
                            </bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p>used to lie in bed till noon, because he said he had no motive in getting
                        up. He could imagine the good of rising; but then he could also imagine the
                        good of lying still and his exclamation, it must be</p>
                    <pb n="119" />
                    <p>allowed, was made upon summer-time, not winter. We must proportion the
                        argument to the individual character. A money-getter may be drawn out of his
                        bed by three and four-pence; but this will not suffice for a student. A proud
                        man may say <q type="spoken">"What shall I think of myself, if I don't get
                            up?"</q> but the more humble one will be content to waive this prodigious
                        notion of himself, out of respect to his kindly bed. The mechanical man shall
                        get up without any ado at all; and so shall the barometer. An ingenious lier
                        in bed will find hard matter of discussion even on the score of health and
                        longevity. He will ask us for our proofs and precedents of the ill effects of
                        lying later in cold weather; and sophisticate much on the advantages of an
                        even temperature of body; of the natural propensity (pretty universal) to
                        have one's way; and of the animals that roll themselves up and sleep all the
                        winter. As to longevity, he will ask whether the longest life is of necessity
                        the best; and whether <placeName key="Holborn" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1008684" cert="high" type="street">Holborn</placeName> is the handsomest street in London.</p>
                    <p>We only know of one confounding, not to say confounded argument, fit to
                        overturn the huge luxury, the <q type="distinct">"enormous bliss"</q>—of the vice in
                        question. A lier in bed may be allowed to profess a disinterested
                        indifference for his health or longevity; but while he is shewing the
                        reasonableness of consulting his own, or one person's comfort, he must admit
                        the proportionate claim of more than one; and the best way to deal with him
                        is this, especially for a lady; for we earnestly recommend the use of that
                        sex on such occasions, if not somewhat over-persuasive; since extremes have
                        an awkward knack of meeting. First then, admit all the ingeniousness of what
                        he says, telling him that the bar has been deprived of an excellent lawyer.
                        Then look at him in the most goodnatured manner in the world, with a mixture
                        of assent and appeal in your countenance, and tell him that you are waiting
                        breakfast for him; that you never like to breakfast without him; that you
                        really want it too; that the servents want theirs; that you shall not know
                        how to get the house into order, unless he rises; and that you are sure he
                        would do things twenty times worse, even than getting out of his warm bed, to
                        put them all into good humour and a state of comfort. Then, after having
                        said this, throw in the comparatively indifferent matter, to him, about his
                        health; but tell him that it is no indifferent matter to you; that the sight
                        of his illness makes more people suffer than one; but that if nevertheless,
                        he really does feel so very sleepy and so very much refreshed by----Yet
                        stay; we hardly know whether the frailty of a— Yes, yes; say that too,
                        especially if you say it with sincerity; for if the weakness of human nature
                        on the one hand, and the <hi rend="italic">vis inertiæ</hi> on the other, should lead him to
                        take advantage of it once or twice, good-humour and sincerity form an
                        irresistible junction at last; and are still better and warmer things than
                        pillows and blankets.</p>
                    <p>Other little helps of appeal may be thrown in, as occasion requires. You may
                        tell a lover for instance, that lying in bed makes people corpulent; a father,
                        that you wish, him to complete the fine manly example he sets his children; a
                        lady, that she will injure her bloom or her shape, which M. or W., admires so
                        much; and a student or</p>
                    <pb n="120" />
                    <p>artist, that he is always so glad to have done a good day's work, in his best
                        manner.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reader.</hi> And pray, Mr. Indicator, how do you behave
                        yourself in this respect ?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Indic.</hi> Oh, Madam, perfectly, of course; like all
                        advisers.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reader.</hi> Nay, I allow that your mode of argument does
                        not look quite so suspicious as the old way of sermonizing and severity, but
                        I have my doubts, especially from that laugh of yours. If I should look in
                        to-morrow morning---</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Indic.</hi> Ah, Madam, the look in of a face like yours
                        does any thing with me. It shall fetch me up at nine, if you please----six,
                        I meant to say.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="correspondents"> <!-- Appended notes to correspondents -->
                    <head type="header" rend="uppercase">TO CORRESPONDENTS.</head>
                    <p>It does not enter within the plan, or perhaps we should rather say, the
                        understood promises, of this little weekly publication, to relieve the Editor
                        with much correspondence; but he is glad when he can indulge himself, in
                        proportion; and he inserts with pleasure the following piece of poetry, which
                        is very much to his heathenish taste.</p>
                    <lg xml:lang="en" rend="center">
                        <head type="title">VOX ET PRÆTEREA NIHIL.</head>
                        <l>Oh! what a voice is silent. It was soft</l>
                        <l>As mountain-echoes, when the winds aloft</l>
                        <l>(The gentle winds of summer) meet in caves;</l>
                        <l>Or when in sheltered places the white waves</l>
                        <l>Are 'waken'd into music, as the breeze</l>
                        <l>Dimples and stems the current: or as trees</l>
                        <l>Shaking their green locks in the days of June:</l>
                        <l>Or <placeName key="Delphi" ref="#Delphi">Delphic</placeName> girls when to the maiden moon</l>
                        <l>They sang harmonious pray'rs: or sounds that come</l>
                        <l>(However near) like a faint distant hum</l>
                        <l>Out of the grass, from which mysterious birth</l>
                        <l>We guess the busy secrets of the earth.</l>
                        <l>— Like the low voice of <persName key="Syrinx" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q175376" cert="high" type="mythological">Syrinx</persName>, when she ran</l>
                        <l>Into the forests from <placeName key="Arcadia" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q180045" cert="high" type="region">Arcadian</placeName> <persName key="Pan" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q163777" cert="high" type="mythological">Pan</persName>:</l>
                        <l>Or sad <persName key="Oenone" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1137021" cert="high" type="mythological">Œnone's</persName>, when she pined away</l>
                        <l>For <persName key="Paris (mythology)" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q172151" cert="high" type="mythological">Paris</persName>, or (and yet 'twas not so gay)</l>
                        <l>As <persName key="Helen of Troy" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q161747" cert="high" type="mythological">Helen's</persName> whisper when she came to <placeName key="Troy" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q22648" cert="high" type="city">Troy</placeName>,</l>
                        <l>Half sham'd to wander with that, blooming boy.</l>
                        <l>Like air-touch'd harps in flowery casements hung;</l>
                        <l>Like unto lovers' ears the wild words sung</l>
                        <l>In garden bowers at twilight: like the sound</l>
                        <l>Of <persName key="Zephyr" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q181297" cert="high" type="mythological">Zephyr</persName> when he takes his nightly round</l>
                        <l>In May, to see the roses all asleep:</l>
                        <l>Or like the dim strain which along the deep</l>
                        <l>The sea-maid utters to the sailors' ear,</l>
                        <l>Telling of tempests, or of dangers near.</l>
                        <l>Like <persName key="Desdemona" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2424367" cert="high" type="fictional">Desdemona</persName>, who (when fear was strong</l>
                        <l>Upon her soul) chaunted the willow song.</l>
                        <l>Swan-like before she perish'd: or the tone</l>
                        <l>Of flutes upon the waters heard alone:</l>
                        <l>Like words that come upon the memory</l>
                        <l>Spoken by friends departed; or the sigh</l>
                        <l>A gentle girl breathes when she tries to hide</l>
                        <l>The love her eyes betray to all beside.</l>
                        <l><seg rend="right">XXX.</seg></l>
                    </lg>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="colophon"> <!-- Publisher and printer information -->
                    <p>Orders received by the Booksellers, by the Newsmen, and by the Publisher, <persName key="Joseph Appleyard" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q125501865" cert="high" type="real">JOSEPH APPLEYARD</persName>,<lb/>
                        No. 19, <placeName key="Catherine Street, Strand" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q125503006" cert="high" type="street">Catherine-street, Strand</placeName>.— Price 2d.<lb/>
                        Printed by <persName key="C. H. Reynell" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q125503028" cert="high" type="real">C. H. REYNELL</persName>, No. 45, <placeName key="Broad Street, Golden Square" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q125503075" cert="high" type="street">Broad-street, Golden-square</placeName>, <placeName key="London" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q84" cert="high" type="city">London</placeName>.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>