<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <!-- File Description -->
    <fileDesc>
      <!-- Title of the work -->
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Indicator</title>
        <title type="subtitle">No. XLI.— WEDNESDAY, JULY 19th, 1820.</title>
        <author>
                        <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                        <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                        <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                    </author>
      </titleStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
        <p />
      </publicationStmt>

      <!-- Author information -->
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>
                        <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                        <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                        <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                    </author>
          <title>The Indicator</title>
          <date when="1820-07-19">JULY 19th, 1820</date> <!-- The publication date of this issue ({Month} {Day}, {Year}) -->
          <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
          <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher> <!-- Publisher details if available -->
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <!-- Encoding Description -->
    <encodingDesc>
      <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
      <p>
        Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers are
        included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
        preservation.
      </p>
    </encodingDesc>

    <!-- Profile Description -->
    <profileDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div1 type="issue" n="41">
        <pb n="321"/> <!-- Page beginning -->
        <div2 type="forematter"> <!-- Title, epigraph, and catalogue -->
          <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
          <epigraph>
            <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
            <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
            <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
            <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055"
                cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
          </epigraph>
          <head type="catalogue" rend='center'>No. XLI.<date when="1820-07-19"> —WEDNESDAY, July 19th, 1820</date>.</head>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" n="1"> <!-- Header and content -->
          <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">The Destruction of the Cenci Family, and Tragedy on that Subject.</head>
           <p>
           We lay before our readers in the present number the substance of a remarkable document, containing the authorities for the tragedy which has lately appeared on the same subject, and which we shall afterwards proceed to notice. Criticism is not intended to be a feature in this our very competent and agreeable miscellany, especially criticism of a hostile nature. But like our illustrious predecessors the <title level="j">Tatler</title> and <title level="j">Spectator</title>, and their fine old father Montaigne, we shall not hesitate now and then to notice some new and excellent work, or to indicatfe some great endeavours on the part of a friend, the natupe of which may require a more than ordinary introduction to the public.</p> 
<p>It has been supposed by some, we understand, that the author of the <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName> has overcharged his story; and these and other persons think that it is too horrible to tell. We are no admirers of horrid stories in general, as we have observed in the prefatory remarks to our own grim perpetration, the <title>Tale for a Chimney Corner</title>, <bibl>(<series><title>Indicator</title><biblScope unit="page">73</biblScope><ref target="theIndicator10.xml"/></series>.)</bibl><note>The reference points to the 10th Issue in the present edition.</note> There are some books in very good request, and with very delicate people too, —such as <persName key="Clarissa Harlowe" type="fictional">Clarissa Harlowe</persName>,— which with all their undoubted genius we would as soon read again, as see a man run the gauntlet from here to <placeName type="landmark" corresp="England" key="Land's End">Land's End</placeName>. The pain is too long drawn out, and the author's <choice><sic>portait</sic><corr>portrait</corr></choice> looks too fat and comfortable. There are also plays, not so clever, such as <title>George Barnwell</title> and <title>the Fatal Marriage</title>, full of half-witted morals and gratuitous agonies, which we would as <choice><orig>lief</orig><reg>gladly</reg></choice> pay to have our legs tortured, as go to see : — admittance to the red hot pincers, three and sixpence; half-torture, two shillings. But as we would avoid mean and unnecessary pain, so it appears to us to be a sort of moral cowardice not to look the most appalling stories in the face, that come to beckon us towards hidden treasures of thought, or to point out to us some great and awful endeavour for good. As <persName key="Proteus" type="fictional">Proteus</persName>, when his consulters grappled with him, changed himself into figures of beasts and serpents, to frighten them from their hold, but gave them their answer if he found it of no avail, so it is with these stories. They are the Gods wrestling with us in fearful shapes. Their final aspect is patient, human, and oracular.</p> 
<p>The moral of the terrible story of the <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>, whether told in history or poetry, is a lesson against the enormities arising from bad education,
<pb n="322"/> 
from long indulged self-will, from the impunities of too much wealth and authority, and from tyrannical and degrading notions of the Supreme Being. It is nothing but the old story of the Neros and Ezzelins in another shape. It is will driven mad by the power of indulging itself. As to the impossibility of the story, let those names and the writings of the elder dramatists answer all objections on that score. It is not the abstract crime that is the subject of consideration, but the excess proportioned to the excess of the will and to the bitterness of the contradiction. It is the enormity that proves the case. The unhappy patient is insane with self-will and with the fury of being opposed; and he will do the worst and most horrible things, precisely because he, as well as others, knows them to be the worst. His very outrages are testimonies to the beauty of virtue. He does not say this to himself. If he did, he would not do it, unless he were in a state of bodily as well as moral disease. But such is the instinct of his habits. The question then is, not how far we can loathe to hear about the frenzies of a fellow-creature, but how we can get at the causes of his frenzy, and help society to guard against them in all their shapes, great or small. We have thousands of <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>s among us in a lesser way, — petty home tyrants, sullen degraders of the deity they worship, impudent and callous men of the world, people that hate and would vex others in proportion as their merits mortify their own want of merit, tempers that work their wretched pleasure out of the pains of those they can worry,- in short, all that come under the poet's description of "the household fiend," — all the spoiled children of power, high and low, - the victims of indulged perversity and of an induced bad opinion of God and man.</p> 
<p>Upon these grounds, after giving way to our first impulse of horror and indignation at the ruffian old man of the following story, we can pity him. — But to the story itself.</p> 
<p>The <title>Manuscript</title> was copied by an Italian gentleman from a library at <placeName type="city" corresp="Italy" key="Rome" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q220">Rome</placeName>, and is entitled, <title>An Account of the Death of the Cenci Family.</title></p> 
<p><persName key="Francesco Cenci" type="real" xml:id="cenci">Francesco Cenci</persName> was the only son of a Roman lord, who had been Treasurer to <persName key="Pope Pius V" type="real" xml:id="pope">Pope Pius the Fifth</persName>, and who left him a clear annual income of a hundred and sixty thousand scudi.<note type="hunt">We know not the precise value of this coin, which does not appear among the current money of <placeName type="country" corresp="Italy" key="Italy">Italy</placeName>: nor can we refer to books for it at this moment. But there were <hi rend="italic">scudi</hi> of gold; and <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>'s fortune was accounted enormous.</note> Besides this, our miserable inheritor of wealth and impunity married a rich woman. After the death of this lady, he took for his second wife <persName key="Lucrezia Petroni" type="real" xml:id="lucrezia">Lucrezia Petroni</persName>, of a noble family in the same city. By the former, he had seven children. By the latter none.</p> 
<p><persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Francesco</persName> hated these children. It is a dreadful thing to say so in so many words; but the cause is easily seen through. He led a life of the most odious profligacy, and was as full of sullenness as vice. His children were intelligent; their father's example disgusted them; and he saw, and could not bear this contrast. The account of his ill-treatment of them begins with his refusing his sons enough to live decently upon, while pursuing their studies at <placeName type="city" corresp="Spain" key="Salamanca">Salamanca</placeName>. They were obliged to return to their miserable home; and here he treated them
<pb n="323"/> 
so much worse, denying them even common food and clothing, that they applied in despair to the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName>, who made him allow them a separate provision, with which they retired to another dwelling. Previously to this period, <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName> had been convicted of a crime twice over, and been suffered to compound for it with the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName> in two several sums of a hundred thousand scudi, nearly two thirds of his annual income. His third mortal crime now took place, and the sons by this time were so embittered by the constant wretchedness and infamy in which he kept his family, that they entreated the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Sovereign Pontiff</persName>  to put an end to his life and villainies at once. The <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName>, says the narrative, was inclined to give him the death he merited, but not at the request of his own offspring, and for the third time he allowed him, to make his usual composition of a hundred thousand scudi.</p> 
<p>The wretched man now hated his children worse <choice><sic>then</sic><corr>than</corr></choice> ever, as he had some better reason to do. But not content with cursing his sons, he visited his two daughters with blows, and otherwise so trampled upon their feelings, that not being able to bear his treatment longer, the elder one applied to the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName>, begging him either to marry her according to his discretion, or to put her in a nunnery. The <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName> took pity on the unhappy girl, and married her to a gentleman of rank named <persName key="Carlo Gabrielli" type="fictional">Carlo Gabrielli</persName>, making the father at the same time give her a suitable dowry.</p> 
<p>This event so gnawed into <persName key="Cenci" type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>'s mind, that fearing his other daughter would follow her sister's example when she grew old enough, he cast in his diabolical thoughts how he might prevent it most assuredly, short of taking away her life. It has been thought by some, that <persName type="real" key="Percy Bysshe Shelley">Mr. Shelley</persName>'s tragedy must be an exaggeration. The fact is, that the historical narrative is much worse. The details of his conduct fill up the poet's outline with horrors not to be thought of. We cannot repeat what this mad and grey-headed horror (for he was now an old man) both preached and practised in order to break down his daughter's virtues as well as heart; but he first kept her locked up in a solitary apartment, where none saw her but himself, and where he brought her stripes as well as food: and his last action –––</p>
<p>About this period the terrible old man received news of the death of two of his sons, <persName type="real" key="Rocco Cenci">Rocco</persName> and <persName type="real" key="Cristofero Cenci">Cristofero</persName>, who by some means or other both came to violent ends. He welcomed it with delight, saying that nothing could make him happier but to hear the same thing of all his children; and that whenever the last should die, he would keep open house to all comers for joy. To <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> his hatred the more openly, he would not give the least pittance towards interring them.</p> 
<p><persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName> was now beyond despair. She collected her thoughts, and sent off a letter to the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName> which the author of the <title>Manuscript</title> describes as excellently written. Let us stop here a moment, to speak more particularly of the extraordinary girl. "<persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName>," says the close of the Narrative, <q>"was of a make rather large <choice><sic>then</sic><corr>than</corr></choice> small. Her complexion was fair. She had two dimples in her cheeks, which added to the beauty of her countenance especially when she smiled, and gave it a grace that enchanted all who saw her. Her hair was like threads of gold; and because it was very long, she used to fasten it up; but when she let it flow loosely, the wavy splendour of it was <pb n="324"/>
astonishing. She had blue eyes, very pleasing, of a sprightliness mixed with dignity: and in addition to all these graces, her conversation, as well as all that she did, had a spirit in it, and a sparkling polish (un brio signorile) which made every one in love with her. She was then under twenty years of age."</q></p> 
<p>The letter to the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName> had no effect. The <choice><abbr><title>MS</title>.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> says that it was found in the office of the Secretary of Memorials; but supposes that it never could have been laid before his Holiness. The reader may be allowed, under all the circumstances to suspect otherwise. <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName> was still rich and powerful; and there is no knowing how many thousands of scudi he may have had to pay now.</p> 
<p>What renders the conduct of the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName> the more suspicious, is that the criminal somehow or other got intelligence of the application. It made him more furious <choice><sic>then</sic><corr>than</corr></choice> ever; and besides locking up his daughter, he incarcerated in the same manner, and apparently in the same room, his wife her mother-in-law, who had already drunk largely of the family cup of bitterness. Finding every avenue of relief shut against them, and taught by the old man himself, as well as their own awful thoughts, to forego the ties of relationship, they finally resolved upon dispatching him.</p> 
<p>There was a visitor in the <placeName type="landmark" corresp="Italy" key="Cenci Palace" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q55981364">Cenci Palace</placeName> , a young prelate of the name of <persName key="Guerra" type="fictional">Guerra</persName>, who, says the <choice><abbr><title>MS</title>.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> was "a young man of an agreeable presence, well-bred, and one that easily accommodated himself to any proposal, good or bad." He was well acquainted with the wickedness of <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>, who hated him for the attentions he paid his family; so that he used to come there at such times only as he knew the old man had gone out. How he gained admittance to the wife and daughter in the present instance does not appear; but he did; and finding their miseries augmented at every visit, his interest in their wretched state increased in proportion. The <choice><abbr><title>MS</title>.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> says that he was not without a love for <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName>; but it does not appear that she returned it. Be this as it may, having gathered their intentions about the old man from some words which <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName> let fall, he not only approved them, but declared his willingness to co-operate in the catastrophe. The design was then communicated to <persName type="real" key="Giacomo Cenci">Giacomo</persName>, one of her brothers, who instantly fell in with it. He had felt his fathers ill treatment still more <choice><sic>then</sic><corr>than</corr></choice> the rest of his sons, having a wife and children whom the stipend assigned him by the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName> was insufficient to support.</p> 
<p><persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName> had taken for the summer residence of himself and his family a castle called the Rock of <placeName type="region" corresp="Italy" key="castle of Petrella" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q224297">Petrella</placeName>. The first plan of the conspirators was to hire a banditti to surprise and kill him in his way thither. The banditti were hired accordingly, but the notice of <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>'s coming was given them too late, and he got into the Castle. Neither did they lurk in the thicket about the place to any purpose; for being now seventy years of age, (and probably aware of the state of the neighbourhood, no unusual thing in those times) he never stirred out of doors. It was therefore determined to put him to death in the castle. For this purpose, they hired two of his vassals, named <persName key="Marzio" type="fictional">Marzio</persName> and <persName key="Olimpio" type="fictional">Olimpio</persName>, who either had or thought they had cause of offence with him. The reward offered for the deed was a thousand scudi, one third to be paid before-hand by Monsignor <persName key="Guerra" type="fictional">Guerra</persName>, and the remainder by the ladies when all 
<pb n="325"/>
was over. The assassins were introduced into the Rock on the 8th of September 1598; <q>"but as it happened to be the day of the Nativity of the Blessed Virgin, <persName key="Lucrezia" type="real" corresp="#lucrezia">Signora Lucrezia</persName> restrained by her veneration for that solemn anniversary, put off the execution, with the consent of her daughter-in-law, till he day following."</q> On the evening of that day, an opiate was put into <persName key="Cenci" type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>'s drink. He went to bed, and fell into a profound sleep; and at midnight, <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName> herself took the assassins into his chamber. Having told them what to do, she retired into an anti-room where her mother was waiting. In a little while, the assasins returned, and said that their compassion had overcome them, and that they could not conquer their repugnance to kill in cold blood, a miserable old man who was sleeping. <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName> heard them with scorn and indignation. " If you are afraid," said she, "to put to death a man in his sleep, I, myself, will kill my father; but your own lives shall not have long to run." The men intimidated at this, returned to the chamber. In a little time they came back. The deed was done. The assassins received the rest of their reward; and to <persName key="Marzio" type="fictional">Marzio</persName> (for what reason does not appear; probably because he had been the least backward) <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName> gave a mantle laced with gold. The body was thrown over a terrace into the garden, so that it might seem to have fallen by accident, while the old man was moving about in the night-time.</p>
<p>The women next day affected great sorrow. A sumptuous burial was given to the deceased; and the family, after a little stay, returned to <placeName type="city" corresp="Italy" key="Rome" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q220">Rome</placeName>, where they are described as living in tranquillity for some time. In the mean while, the youngest son of <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName> died, so that there remained but two, <persName type="real" key="Giacomo Cenci">Giacomo</persName> and <persName type="real" key="Bernardo Cenci">Bernardo</persName>.</p> 
<p><orgName>The Court of Naples</orgName> however, whose interference at this point of time is not accounted for, unless the banditti, who were from that kingdom, had let the secret transpire, sent a commissioner to make enquiries into the nature of <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>'s death. The usual petty circumstances of suspicion came out, and were laid before the Court of <placeName type="city" corresp="Italy" key="Rome" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q220">Rome</placeName>; yet the latter took no further steps for several months. <persName key="Guerra" type="fictional">Guerra</persName>, who was afraid that the assassins might turn evidence, hired others to get them out of the way; but <persName key="Marzio" type="fictional">Marzio</persName> escaped. He got imprisoned however at <placeName type="city" corresp="Italy" key="Naples" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2634">Naples</placeName>; and having made an ample confession, was sent to <placeName type="city" corresp="Italy" key="Rome" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q220">Rome</placeName>. Here he was confronted with the <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>, who denied all that he said, particularly <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName>. Her extraordinary firmness and presence of mind is described as so astonishing the man, that he retracted every thing he had deposed at <placeName type="city" corresp="Italy" key="Naples" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2634">Naples</placeName>; and rather than confess, chose to expire under the torment.</p> 
<p>The law being now perplexed how to proceed, the <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName> were transferred to the Castle, where they lived uninterruptedly for several months. Unluckily, one of the bravoes who had killed <persName key="Olimpio" type="fictional">Olimpio</persName> was taken up, and confessed that he had been employed by Monsignor <persName key="Guerra" type="fictional">Guerra</persName>. Timely notice, by some means or other, was given to the bishop, and he escaped. He had difficulty in doing so, because he was a remarkable looking man with a fair face and hair, and the officers were on the alert: but he contrived it. He changed clothes with a coal-man, smutted his face and shaved his head, and driving two asses before him, with an onion and a piece of bread in his hand, passed 
<pb n="326"/>
out of the city under their very eyes. He encountered with equal good luck the officers who were on the look out in the neighbourhood; and got safe into another country.</p> 
<p>The flight of the prelate however, together with the confession of <persName key="Olimpio" type="fictional">Olimpio</persName>'s murderer, brought the hand of the law heavily upon the <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName>. They were now put to the torture. The courage of the men was prostrated at once (<q>"cederono vilmente,"</q> says the <title>Manuscript</title>), and they remained convicted. <q>"<persName type="real" corresp="#lucrezia">Signora Lucrezia</persName>, a woman of fifty years of age and large in person, not being able to resist the Torment of the Cord — (Here the Original is wanting) — But not one single criminating word,"</q> continues the document, <q>"either by fair means or foul, by threats or by tortures, could be got out of the lips of <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName>. Her vivacity and eloquence confounded even the judges."</q> One of them, <persName key="Signor Ulisse Morcati" type="fictional">Signor Ulisse Morcati</persName>, represented the matter to the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName>, who suspected him of having been overcome by the sufferer's beauty, and appointed another in his room. The new judge ordered a fresh torture to be applied, called the Torture of the Hair; and when she was tied up ready for it, the rest of the family were brought in and entreated her to confess. At first she refused. "You would all die then," said she, "and extinguish our honour and our house? This ought not to be; but since it pleases you, so be it." She then turned to the officers to let her loose, and asked for copies of the several examinations; adding, "What I should confess, I will confess: — what I should approve, I will approve: — what I should deny, I will deny." After this fashion, says the <choice><abbr><title>MS</title>.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice>, she stood convicted, though she did not confess.</p>
<p>The affair rested here again in a very extraordinary manner. Probably (though the <choice><abbr><title>MS</title>.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> is far from hinting such a thing) some money matters were under the consideration of his Holiness, — deep questions as to the difference of fines and confiscations. The parties were separated from each other for five months. They were then allowed to meet one day at dinner; and then again they were divided. At length, the Holy Father, after having seen them all confronted, and examined the confession, sentenced them to be drawn at the cart's tail and beheaded.</p> 
<p>Great interest was made, by princes and cardinals, for allowing the criminals a legal defence. The <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName>, who had <choice><orig>shewn</orig><reg>shown</reg></choice> himself hostile from the first, answered these requests with severity, and asked, "what defence <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName> had, when he was so barbarously murdered in his sleep." At last he yielded the point, and gave them five-and-twenty days to look about them. The most eminent advocates in <placeName type="city" corresp="Italy" key="Rome" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q220">Rome</placeName> prepared the defence, and appeared before him at the proper time with their respective papers. The first that spoke was impatiently interrupted by his Holiness, who said he was astonished to find in <placeName type="city" corresp="Italy" key="Rome" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q220">Rome</placeName> children so barbarous as to kill their father, and advocates so bold as to defend such a villainy. At these words all the counsel were struck dumb, with the exception of the <persName key="Advocate Tarrinacci" type="fictional">Advocate Tarrinacci</persName>, who replied, "Holy Father, we are not here at your feet to defend the brutality of the deed itself, but to save the lives of such as may be innocent nevertheless, if your Holiness will listen to us." The <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName>, upon this, listened patiently for four hpurs. Tarinucci's defence proceeded 
<pb n="327"/>
upon the only possible ground, and appears to have contained a strength and eloquence worthy of his spirit. He balanced the wrongs of father and children against each other. The sons were made out to be the least concerned, and the weight of the murder thrown purposely upon <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName>, who had been so atrociously and unspeakably outraged. The <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName> sat up all the following night with one of the Cardinals, considering the defence point by point; and the upshot was, that he gave the criminals a hope of escaping death, and ordered that they should again be at comparative liberty.</p> 
<p>Unfortunately for this new and unexpected turn in their affairs, a nobleman of the name of <persName>Paolo Santa Croce</persName> assassinated, at this point of time, his own mother, for not bequeathing him her inheritance. This renewed the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName>'s bitterness against those who had set an example of parricide; and what increased it, was the flight of <persName type="real" key="Paolo Santa Croce">Santa Croce</persName> who eluded the hands of justice. He sent for the Governor of the city, and ordered the <persName type="real" corresp="#cenci">Cenci</persName> to be publicly executed forthwith. Many of the nobility hastened to his different palaces to implore at least a private death for the ladies; but he would not consent. They could only obtain the pardon of <persName type="real" key="Bernardo Cenci">Bernardo</persName>, whom the <choice><abbr><title>MS</title>.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> calls "the innocent <persName type="real" key="Bernardo Cenci">Bernardo</persName>," and whose treatment both past and to come is thus rendered inexplicable.</p> 
<p>The sentence was executed next day, <date when="1599-05-11">Saturday, the 11th of May 1599</date> on the bridge of <placeName type="landmark" corresp="Italy" key=" Sant'Angelo Bridge" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q870476">St. Angelo</placeName>. <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName>, on receiving news of the sentence, felt, for the first time, her young heart fail her; and burst into bitter and wild lamentations on the necessity of dying. "Oh God!" she cried out, "how is it possible to die so suddenly!" Her mother-in-law, whose greater age and perhaps less hope of escaping death, had softened more into patience, comforted her in the most affectionate manner, and got her quietly into the chapel. <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName> soon recovered herself, and behaved with a gentle firmness proportionate to the wildness of her first grief. She made a will, in which she left fifteen thousand scudi to <orgName>the Confraternity of the Sacred Stigmas</orgName> (the Wounds of Christ), and the whole of her dowry to portion fifty-female orphans in marriage. <persName type="real" corresp="#lucrezia">Lucrezia</persName> left a will in the same spirit. They then recited psalms, litanies, and other prayers; and at eight o'clock confessed themselves, heard mass, and received the sacrament. The funeral procession called for them on <choice><sic>it's</sic><corr>its</corr></choice> way, having already taken up the two brothers, to the younger of whom the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName>'s pardon was announced, informing him at the same time that he must witness the executions. <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName> and <persName type="real" corresp="#lucrezia">Lucrezia</persName> were, habited like nuns. On their way to the scaffold a striking thing was observed. <persName type="real" corresp="#lucrezia">Lucrezia</persName>'s handkerchief was continually applied to wipe away her tears; <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName>'s only to dry up the moisture on her forehead.</p> 
<p>When the procession arrived at the scaffold, and the criminals withdrew for a while to a chapel, the poor young <persName type="real" key="Bernardo Cenci">Bernardo</persName>, condemned to see his nearest relations executed before his very eyes, fell into an agony and fainting fit, and was recovered only to be placed opposite the block. The first who mounted the scaffold was <persName type="real" corresp="#lucrezia">Lucrezia</persName>. In preparing for death, the drapery was discomposed about her bosom, which though she was fifty years of ago, was still beautiful. She blushed and cast down her eyes, but raised them again in prayer; and then adjust<pb n="328"/>ing herself to the block, was in the act of repeating the words, in the 51st psalm, " According to the multitude of thy tender mercies," when her head was struck off. While the blocks was being prepared for <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName>, a place on which some of the spectators stood broke down, to their great hurt. <persName type="real" key="Beatrice Cenci">Beatrice</persName> hearing the noise, asked if her mother had died well, and being told she had, kelt down before a crucifix, and said, "Thanks without end be to thee, O most merciful Redeemer, for having given in the good death of my mother a sure proof of thy pity towards me." Then rising on her feet, "all courage and devotion," she walked towards the scaffold, putting up prayers as she went with such a fervour of spirit, that all who heard her melted into tears. Having ascended the scaffold, she accommodated her head to the block, and looking up once more towards heaven, prayed thus: — "O most affectionate Jesus, who abandoning thy divinity, didst become human; and didst will, in thy love, to purge from <choice><sic>it's</sic><corr>its</corr></choice> mortal blot even this my sinful soul with thy precious blood; ah, grant, I pray thee, that that which I am now about to shed, may suffice before thy merciful tribunal to do away my great misdeeds, and to save me from some part of the punishment which is justly my due." Having said thus, she laid down her head again on the block and began the 130th Psalm — "Out of the depths have I cried unto thee, O Lord. Lord, hear my voice: let thine ears" — At these words her head was severed from her body. The latter underwent such a violent convulsion, that one of the legs is said to have almost leaped up. At sight of his sister's death, <persName type="real" key="Bernardo Cenci">Bernardo</persName> swooned away again, and did not recover his senses for a quarter of an hour. It was now the turn, of the last sufferer, <persName type="real" key="Giacomo Cenci">Giacomo</persName>. He first gave a stedfast look at <persName type="real" key="Bernardo Cenci">Bernardo</persName>, and then said aloud, that if he went into a state of bliss instead of punishment he would pray for the welfare of the <persName type="real" corresp="#pope">Pope</persName>, who had remitted the tormenting part of his just sentence and saved his brother's life; and that the only affliction he had in his last moments, was that his brother was compelled to look upon a scene so dreadful: "but," added he, "as it has so pleased thee, O my God, thy will be done." He then knelt down, and was killed with a blow of a leaded club. The executions being over, <persName type="real" key="Bernardo Cenci">Bernardo</persName> was taken back to prison, where he fell into a long and violent fever. He was kept there four months," when at the request of the Venerable Arch-Confraternity of the Most Holy Crucifix of St. Marcello he obtained the favour of being set at liberty, after paying to the Hospital of the <placeName type="building" corresp="Italy" key="Church of the Most Holy Trinity of the Pilgrims" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1852769">Most Holy Trinity of the Pilgrims</placeName> the sum of 25,000 scudi." He lived to have a son, named <persName key="Cristofero" type="real">Cristofero</persName>, at the time when the <choice><abbr><title>MS</title>.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> was written; but we know not how long the family stock survived.</p> 
<p>Thus ended this dreadful tragedy of mistakes; in which the most privileged were made fiends, the most virtuous murderers, and the customs that undertook to punish them were the cause of all.
           </p>
      </div2> 
           
        <div2 type="colophon"> <!-- Publisher and printer information -->
        <p>Printed and published by <hi rend="smallcaps"><persName type="real" key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName></hi>, No. 19, Catherine-street, Strand. 
            Price 2d. — And sold also by <hi rend="smallcaps"><orgName cert="low">A. Gliddon</orgName></hi>, Importer of Snuffs, No. 31, Tavistock-street, Covent-garden. Orders received at the above places, and by all Booksellers and Newsmen.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
