<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!-- Template Version 1.1 [FOR REFERENCE - DO NOT DELETE] -->
<!-- This template is intended to be used as a starting point for encoding a new text.
        It is not intended as a fixed structure, but rather collects some of the most common
        structural elements for convenience and uniformity. Please add/remove elements as
        necessary for your use case. -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <!-- File Description -->
        <fileDesc>
            <!-- Title of the work -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Indicator</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                    <surname>
                    Hunt</surname>, <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <p>
                    This electronic edition is part of a larger project to digitize and make
                    accessible the complete run of Leigh Hunt's periodical, The Indicator.
                </p>
            </publicationStmt>

            <!-- Author information -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>
                        <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                        <surname>
                    Hunt</surname>, <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                    </author>
                    , <title level="j">The Indicator</title>
                    <date
                        when="1820-01-12">January 12, 1820</date>
                    <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>
                    , <country>England</country></pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <!-- Encoding Description -->
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
            <p>
                Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers
                are
                included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
                preservation. Specific entities like persons, places, and literary works are
                identified and linked to external authorities where possible. Typographical errors
                are marked using &lt;choice&gt; tags with &lt;sic&gt; and &lt;corr&gt; elements.
                Old spellings are marked using &lt;choice&gt; tags with &lt;orig&gt; and &lt;reg&gt;
                elements.
            </p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <!-- Profile Description -->
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="issue" n="14">
                <pb n="" /> <!-- Unnumbered title page for the issue -->
                <div2 type="title">
                    <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                    <epigraph>
                        <lg>
                            <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
                            <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                            <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser"
                                ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055" cert="high"
                                type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                    </epigraph>
                    <head type="catalogue">No. <hi rend="smallcaps">XIV</hi>.— <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        WEDNESDAY</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">JANUARY</hi> 12th, 1820.</head>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="1">
                    <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">A FEW THOUGHTS ON SLEEP.</head>
                    <p>This is an article for the reader to think of, when he or she is warm in bed,
                        a little before he goes to sleep, the clothes at his ear, and the wind
                        moaning in some distant crevice.</p>
                    <p><q type="spoken">Blessings</q>, exclaimed <persName key="Sancho Panza"
                            ref="#" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Sancho</persName>, <q type="spoken">on him that first
                        invented sleep! It wraps a man all round like a cloak.</q> It is a delicious
                        moment certainly,—that of being well nestled in bed, and feeling that you
                        shall drop gently to sleep. The good is to come, not past: the limbs have
                        been just tired enough, to render the remaining in one posture delightful:
                        the labour of the day is done. A gentle failure of the perceptions comes
                        creeping over one:--the spirit of consciousness disengages itself more and
                        more, with slow and hushing degrees, like a mother detaching her hand from
                        that of her sleeping child;—the mind seems to have a balmy lid closing over
                        it, like the eye;—'tis closing; —'tis more closing;—'tis closed. The
                        mysterious spirit has gone to take it's airy rounds.</p>
                    <p>It is said that sleep is best before midnight: and Nature herself, with her
                        darkness and
                        chilling dews, informs us so. There is another reason for going to bed
                        betimes : for it is universally acknowledged that lying late in the morning
                        is a great shortener of life. At least, it is never found in company with
                        longevity. It also tends to make people corpulent. But these matters belong
                        rather to the subject of early rising, than of sleep.</p>
                    <p>Sleep at a late hour in the morning, is not half so pleasant as the more
                        timely one. It is sometimes however excusable, especially to a, watchful or
                        over-worked head; neither can we deny the seducing merits of <q
                            type="distinct">t' other doze</q>,— the pleasing wilfulness of nestling
                        in a new posture, when you know you ought to be up, like the rest of the
                        house. But then you cut up the day, and your sleep the next night.</p>
                    <p>In the course of the day, few people think of sleeping, except after dinner ;
                        and then it is often rather a hovering and nodding on the borders of sleep,
                        than a sleep itself. This is a privilege, allowable, we think, to none but
                        the old, or the sickly, or the very tired and care-worn ; and it should be
                        well understood, before it is exercised in company. To escape into slumber
                        from an argument; or to take</p>
                    <pb n="106" />
                    <p>it as an affair of course, only between you and your biliary duct; or to
                        assent with involuntary nods to all that you have just been disputing; is
                        not so well: much less, to sit nodding and tottering beside a lady; or to be
                        in danger of dropping your head into the fruit-plate or your host's face; or
                        of waking up, and saying <q type="spoken">Just so</q> to the bark of a dog,
                        or <q
                            type="spoken"
                        >Yes, Madam</q> to the black at your elbow.</p>
                    <p>Care-worn people however might refresh themselves oftener with day-sleep than
                        they do; if their bodily state is such as to dispose them to it. It is a
                        mistake to suppose that all care is wakeful. People sometimes sleep, as well
                        as wake, by reason of their sorrow. The difference seems to depend upon the
                        nature of their temperament ; though in the <hi rend="italic">most</hi>
                        excessive cases, sleep is perhaps Nature's never-failing relief, as swooning
                        is upon the rack. A person with jaundice in his blood shall lie down and go
                        to sleep at noon-day, when another of a different complexion shall find his
                        eyes as uncloseable as a statue's, though he has had no sleep for nights
                        together. Without meaning to lesson the dignity of suffering, which has
                        quite enough to do with it's waking hours, it is this that may often account
                        for the profound sleeps enjoyed the night before hazardous battles,
                        executions, and other demands upon an over-excited spirit.</p>
                    <p>The most complete and healthy sleep that can be taken in the day, is in
                        summer-time, out in a field. There is perhaps no solitary sensation so
                        exquisite as that of slumbering on the grass or hay, shaded from the hot sun
                        by a tree, with the consciousness of a fresh but light air running through
                        the wide atmosphere, and the sky stretching far overhead upon all sides.
                        Earth, and heaven, and a placid humanity, seem to have
                        the creation to themselves. There is nothing between the slumberer, and the
                        naked and glad innocence of nature.</p>
                    <p>Next to this, but at a long interval, the most relishing snatch of
                        slumber out of bed, is the one which a tired person takes, before he retires
                        for the night, while lingering in his sitting-room. The consciousness of
                        being very sleepy and of having the power to go to bed immediately, gives
                        great zest to the unwillingness to move. Sometimes he sits nodding in his
                        chair; but the sudden and leaden jerks of the head to which a state of great
                        sleepiness renders him liable, are generally too painful for so luxurious a
                        moment; and he gets into a more legitimate posture, sitting sideways with
                        his head on the chair-back, or throwing his legs up at once on another
                        chair, and half reclining. It is curious however to find, how long an
                        inconvenient posture will be borne for the sake of this foretaste of repose.
                        The worst of it is, that on going to bed, the charm sometimes vanishes;
                        perhaps from the colder temperature of the chamber; for a fireside is a
                        great opiate.</p>
                    <p>Speaking of the painful positions into which a sleepy lounger will get
                        himself, it is amusing to think of the more fantastic attitudes that so
                        often take place in bed. If we could add any thing to the numberless things
                        that have been said about sleep by the poets, it would be upon this point.
                        Sleep never shews himself a greater <pb n="107" /> leveller. A man in his
                        waking moments may look as proud and self-possessed as he pleases. He may
                        walk proudly, he may sit proudly, he may eat his dinner proudly; he may
                        shave himself with an air of infinite superiority; in a word, he may shew
                        himself grand and absurd upon the most trifling occasions. But Sleep plays
                        the petrifying magician. He arrests the proudest lord as well as the
                        humblest clown in the most ridiculous postures: so that if you could draw a
                        grandee from his bed without waking him, no limb-twisting fool in a
                        pantomime should create wilder laughter. The toy with the string between
                        it's legs is hardly a posture-master more extravagant. Imagine a despot
                        lifted up to the gaze of his valets, with his eyes shut, his mouth open, his
                        left hand under his right ear, his other twisted and hanging helplessly
                        before him like an ideot's, one knee lifted up, and the other leg stretched
                        out, or both knees huddled up together; what a scarecrow to lodge majestic
                        power in!</p>
                    <p>But Sleep is kindly, even in his tricks; and the poets have treated him with
                        proper reverence. According to the ancient mythologists, he had even one of
                        the <persName
                            key="Graces (mythology)" ref="#" type="mythological"
                        >Graces</persName> to
                        wife. He had a thousand sons, of whom the chief were <persName
                            key="Morpheus" ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="mythological"
                        >Morpheus</persName>, or the <emph>Shaper</emph>
                        ; <persName key="Icelos" ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="mythological">Icelos</persName>, or the <emph>Likely</emph>
                        ; <persName key="Phantasus" ref="#" cert="high"
                            type="mythological"
                        >Phantasus</persName>, the <emph>Fancy</emph>; and <persName
                            key="Phobetor" ref="#" cert="high" type="mythological">Phobetor</persName>,
                        the <emph>
                            Terror</emph>. His dwelling some writers place in a dull and darkling
                        part of the earth; others, with greater compliment, in heaven; and others,
                        with another kind of propriety, by the sea-shore. There is a good
                        description of it in <persName key="Ovid"
                            ref="#" cert="high" type="real"
                        >Ovid</persName>; but in these abstracted
                        tasks of poetry, the moderns outvie the ancients; and there is nobody who
                        has built his bower for him so finely as <persName
                            key="Edmund Spenser"
                            ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055" cert="high" type="real"
                        >
                        Spenser</persName>. <persName key="Archimago" ref="#" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Archimago</persName> in the first book of the <title
                            level="m" key="The Faerie Queene"
                            ref="#">Faery Queen</title>, (Canto 1, St. 39.) sends a little spirit
                        down to <persName key="Morpheus" ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="mythological">Morpheus</persName> to fetch him a
                        Dream.</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l>He, making speedy way through spersed ayre,</l>
                                <l>And through the world of waters, wide and <choice>
                                        <orig>deepe</orig>
                                        <reg>deep</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>To <persName key="Morpheus" ref="#" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological"
                                    >
                                        Morpheus'</persName> house <choice>
                                        <orig>doth</orig>
                                        <reg>does</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    hastily <choice>
                                        <orig>repaire</orig>
                                        <reg>repair</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    .</l>
                                <l>Amid the bowels of the earth full <choice>
                                        <orig>steepe</orig>
                                        <reg>steep</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>And low, where dawning day <choice>
                                        <orig>doth</orig>
                                        <reg>does</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    never <choice>
                                        <orig>peepe</orig>
                                        <reg>peep</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>His dwelling is. There, <persName key="Tethys" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological">Tethys</persName> his wet bed</l>
                                <l><choice>
                                        <orig>Doth</orig>
                                        <reg>Does</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ever wash; and <persName key="Cynthia (mythology)" cert="high"
                                        type="mythological">Cynthia</persName> still <choice>
                                        <orig>doth</orig>
                                        <reg>does</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    <choice>
                                        <orig>steepe</orig>
                                        <reg>steep</reg>
                                    </choice></l>
                                <l>In silver dew his <choice>
                                        <orig>ever-drouping</orig>
                                        <reg>ever-drooping</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    head,</l>
                                <l>Whiles sad Night over him her mantle black <choice>
                                        <orig>doth</orig>
                                        <reg>does</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    <choice>
                                        <orig>spred</orig>
                                        <reg>spread</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    .</l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl><author>Edmund Spenser</author>, <title level="m">The Faerie
                                    Queene</title>, <biblScope unit="book">Book 1</biblScope>, <biblScope
                                    unit="canto">Canto 1</biblScope>, <biblScope
                                    unit="stanza">Stanza 39</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l>And more to lull him in his <choice>
                                        <orig>slumber</orig>
                                        <reg>slumbers</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    soft</l>
                                <l>A trickling <choice>
                                        <orig>streame</orig>
                                        <reg>stream</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    from high <choice>
                                        <orig>rocke</orig>
                                        <reg>rock</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    tumbling <choice>
                                        <orig>downe</orig>
                                        <reg>down</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>And <choice>
                                        <orig>ever-dringling</orig>
                                        <reg>ever-drizzling</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    rain upon the loft,</l>
                                <l>Mixed with a murmuring winde, much like the <choice>
                                        <orig>soune</orig>
                                        <reg>sound</reg>
                                    </choice></l>
                                <l>Of swarming bees, did cast him in a <choice>
                                        <orig>swoune</orig>
                                        <reg>swoon</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    .</l>
                                <l>No other noise, nor people's troublous <choice>
                                        <orig>cryes</orig>
                                        <reg>cries</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>As still are wont to annoy the walled <choice>
                                        <orig>towne</orig>
                                        <reg>town</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    .</l>
                                <l>Might there be heard, but <choice>
                                        <orig>carelesse</orig>
                                        <reg>careless</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    Quiet <choice>
                                        <orig>lyes</orig>
                                        <reg>lies</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    .</l>
                                <l>Wrapt in eternall silence, farre from <choice>
                                        <orig>enimyes</orig>
                                        <reg>enemies</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    .</l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl><author>Edmund Spenser</author>, <title level="m">The Faerie
                                    Queene</title>, <biblScope unit="book">Book 1</biblScope>, <biblScope
                                    unit="canto">Canto 1</biblScope>, <biblScope
                                    unit="stanza">Stanza 40</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p><persName key="Geoffrey Chaucer" ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="real">Chaucer</persName> has drawn the cave of the
                        same god with greater simplicity; but nothing can have a more deep and
                        sullen effect than his cliffs and cold running waters. It seems as real as
                        an actual solitude, or some quaint old picture in a book of travels in <placeName
                            key="Tartary" ref="#" cert="high" type="region">Tartary</placeName>. He
                        is telling the story of <persName key="Ceyx" ref="#" cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Ceyx</persName> and <persName key="Alcyone" ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="mythological">Alcyone</persName> in the poem called
                        his <title level="m" key="The Book of the Duchess"
                            ref="#">Dream</title>. <persName
                            key="Juno" ref="#" cert="high" type="mythological">Juno</persName> tells
                        a messenger to go to <persName key="Morpheus" ref="#" cert="high"
                            type="mythological"
                        >Morpheus</persName> and <q type="spoken">bid him
                            creep into</q></p>
                    <pb n="108" />
                    <p>the body<q type="spoken"> of the drowned king, to let his wife know the fatal
                        event by his apparition.</q></p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l>This messenger <choice>
                                        <orig>tooke</orig>
                                        <reg>took</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    leave, and went</l>
                                <l>Upon his way; and never he <choice>
                                        <orig>stent</orig>
                                        <reg>stint</reg>
                                    </choice></l>
                                <l>Till he came to the dark valley,</l>
                                <l>That <choice>
                                        <orig>stant</orig>
                                        <reg>stands</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    betweene <choice>
                                        <orig>rockes</orig>
                                        <reg>rocks</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    <choice>
                                        <orig>twey</orig>
                                        <reg>two</reg>
                                    </choice>.</l>
                                <l>There never yet grew <choice>
                                        <orig>corne</orig>
                                        <reg>corn</reg>
                                    </choice>,
                                    ne <choice>
                                        <orig>gras</orig>
                                        <reg>grass</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>Ne tree, ne <choice>
                                        <orig>nought</orig>
                                        <reg>naught</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    that <choice>
                                        <orig>aught</orig>
                                        <reg>aught</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    was,</l>
                                <l>Beast ne man, ne <choice>
                                        <orig>naught</orig>
                                        <reg>naught</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    else;</l>
                                <l>Save that there were a few <choice>
                                        <orig>wells</orig>
                                        <reg>wells</reg>
                                    </choice></l>
                                <l>Came running fro the the cliffs <choice>
                                        <orig>adowne</orig>
                                        <reg>down</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>That made a deadly sleeping <choice>
                                        <orig>soune</orig>
                                        <reg>sound</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>And runnen <choice>
                                        <orig>downe</orig>
                                        <reg>down</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    right by a cave,</l>
                                <l>That was under a <choice>
                                        <orig>rocke</orig>
                                        <reg>rock</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    <choice>
                                        <orig>ygrave</orig>
                                        <reg>engraved</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>Amid the valley, wonder-<choice>
                                        <orig>deepe</orig>
                                        <reg>deep</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    .</l>
                                <l>There these <choice>
                                        <orig>goddis</orig>
                                        <reg>gods</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    lay <choice>
                                        <orig>asleepe</orig>
                                        <reg>asleep</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l><persName key="Morpheus" ref="#" cert="high" type="mythological"
                                    >
                                    Morpheus</persName> and <persName key="Eclympasteire" ref="#"
                                        cert="high" type="mythological"
                                    >Eclynipasteire</persName>,</l>
                                <l>That was the god of Sleepis <choice>
                                        <orig>heire</orig>
                                        <reg>heir</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    ,</l>
                                <l>That slept and did none other <choice>
                                        <orig>worke</orig>
                                        <reg>work</reg>
                                    </choice>
                                    .</l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl><author>Geoffrey Chaucer</author>, <title level="m">The Book of
                                    the Duchess</title>, <biblScope unit="line">lines
                                    153-169</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p>Where the credentials of this new son and heir, <persName
                            key="Eclympasteire" ref="#" cert="high" type="mythological"
                        >Eclympasteire</persName>,
                        are to be found, we know not; but he acts very much, it must be allowed,
                        like an heir presumptive, in sleeping, and doing <q type="written">none
                            other work.</q></p>
                    <p>We dare not trust ourselves with many quotations upon sleep from the poets;
                        they are so numerous as well as beautiful. We must content ourselves with
                        mentioning that our two most favourite passages are one in the <title
                            level="m" key="Philoctetes" ref="#"
                            cert="high">Philoctetes</title> of <persName key="Sophocles"
                            ref="#" cert="high" type="real"
                        >
                            Sophocles</persName>, admirable for it's contrast to a scene of terrible
                        agony, which it closes<note type="hunt">
                            <bibl>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">We do not translate it here, as we intend to
                        present the reader with the whole scene in an article upon <title level="a">
                        Philoctetes</title>.</hi>
                            </bibl>
                        </note>:
                        and the other the following address in <persName
                            key="Francis Beaumont" ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="real">Beaumont</persName> and <persName
                            key="John Fletcher" ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="real">Fletcher's</persName> tragedy of <title
                            level="m" key="Valentinian (play)"
                            ref="#" cert="high"
                        >Valentinian</title>, the hero of which is also a
                        sufferer under bodily torment. He is in a chair, slumbering; and these most
                        exquisite lines are gently sung with music.</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg xml:lang="en">
                                <l>Care-charming Sleep, thou easer of all
                                    woes,</l>
                                <l>Brother to Death, sweetly thyself
                                    dispose</l>
                                <l>On this afflicted <persName key="Valentinian" ref="#" cert="high"
                                        type="fictional">prince</persName>. Fall like a cloud</l>
                                <l>In gentle showers: give nothing that is loud</l>
                                <l>Or painful to his slumbers: easy, light,</l>
                                <l>And as a purling stream, thou son of, Night,</l>
                                <l>Pass by his troubled senses: sing his pain</l>
                                <l>Like hollow murmuring wind, or silver rain:</l>
                                <l>Into this <persName key="Valentinian" ref="#" cert="high"
                                        type="fictional">prince</persName>, gently, oh gently slide;</l>
                                <l>And kiss him into slumbers, like a bride.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <note type="source">
                            <bibl>
                                <author>Francis Beaumont</author> and <author>John Fletcher</author>
                                , <title level="m">Valentinian</title> , <biblScope unit="act"
                                >Act 5</biblScope>
                                , <biblScope unit="scene">Scene
                                    2</biblScope>.</bibl>
                        </note>
                    </cit>
                    <p>How earnest and prayer-like are these pauses! How lightly sprinkled, and yet
                        how deeply settling, like rain, the fancy! How quiet, affectionate, and
                        perfect the conclusion!</p>
                    <p>Sleep
                        is most graceful in an infant; soundest, in one who has been tired in the
                        open air; completest, to the seaman after a hard voyage; most welcome, to
                        the mind haunted with one idea; most touching to look at, in the parent that
                        has wept; lightest, in the playful child; proudest, in the bride adored.</p>
                </div2>
                <pb n="109" />
                <div2 type="section" n="2">
                    <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">THE FAIR REVENGE.</head>
                    <p>The elements of this story are to be found in the old poem called <title
                            level="m" key="Albion's England"
                            ref="#" cert="high"
                        >Albion's
                            England</title>, to which we referred in the article on <persName
                            key="Charles Brandon"
                            ref="#" cert="high" type="real"
                        >Charles
                            Brandon</persName> and <persName key="Mary Tudor, Queen of France"
                            ref="#" cert="high" type="real"
                        >Mary
                            Queen of France</persName>,</p>
                    <p><persName key="Aganippus" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional"
                        >Aganippus</persName>,
                        king of <placeName key="Argos"
                            ref="#" cert="high" type="city"
                        >
                            Argos</placeName>, dying without heirs male, bequeathed his throne to
                        his only daughter, the beautiful and beloved <persName key="Daphles" ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName>. This female succession
                        was displeasing to a nobleman who held large possessions on the frontiers;
                        and he came for the first time towards the court, not to pay his respects to
                        the new queen, but to give her battle. <persName key="Doracles" ref="#"
                            cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Doracles</persName> (for that was his name) was not
                        much known by the people. He had distinguished himself for as jealous an
                        independence as a subject could well assume; and though he had been of use
                        in repelling invasion during the latter years of the king, had never made
                        his appearance to receive his master's thanks personally. A correspondence
                        however was understood to have gone on between him and several noblemen
                        about the court ; and there were those, who in spite of his inattention to
                        popularity, suspected that it would go hard with the young queen, when the
                        two armies came face to face.</p>
                    <p>But neither these subtle statesmen, nor the ambitious young soldier <persName
                            key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>,
                        were aware of the effects to be produced by a strong personal attachment.
                        The young queen, amiable as she was beautiful, had involuntarily baffled his
                        expectations from her courtiers, by exciting in the minds of some a real
                        disinterested regard, while others nourished a hope of sharing her throne
                        instead. At least, they speculated upon becoming, each the favourite
                        minister; and held it a better thing to reign under that title and a
                        charming mistress, than be the servants of a master, wilful and domineering.
                        By the people she was adored; and when she came riding out of her palace, on
                        the morning of the fight, with an unaccustomed spear standing up in it's
                        rest by her side, her diademed hair flowing a little off into the wind, her
                        face paler than usual, but still tinted with it's roses, and a look in which
                        confidence in the love of her subjects, and tenderness for the wounds they
                        were going to encounter, seemed to contend for the expression, —the shout
                        which they sent up would have told a stouter heart than a traitor's, that
                        the royal charmer was secure.</p>
                    <p>The queen, during the conflict, remained in a tent upon an eminence, to which
                        the younger leaders vied who should best spur up their smoking horses, to
                        bring her good news from time to time. The battle was short and bloody. <persName
                            key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>
                        soon found that he had miscalculated his point; and all his skill and
                        resolution could not set the error to rights. It was allowed, that if either
                        courage or military talent could entitle him to the throne, he would have
                        had a right to it; but the popularity of <persName key="Daphles" ref="#"
                            cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Daphles</persName> supplied her cause with all the
                        ardour, which a lax state of subjection on the part of the more powerful
                        nobles might have denied it. When her troops charged, or made any other
                        voluntary movement, they put all their hearts into their blows; and when
                        they were compelled to await the enemy, they stood as inflexible as walls of
                        iron. It was like hammering upon</p>
                    <pb n="110" />
                    <p>metal statuary; or staking their fated horses upon spears rivetted in stone. <persName
                            key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>
                        was taken prisoner. The queen, re-issuing from her tent, crowned with
                        laurel, came riding down the eminence, and remained at the foot with her
                        generals, while the prisoners were taken by. Her pale face kept as royal a
                        countenance of composed pity as she could manage, while the commoner rebels
                        passed along, aching with their wounded arms fastened behind, and shaking
                        back their bloody and blinding locks for want of a hand to part them. But
                        the blood mounted to her cheeks, when the proud and handsome <persName
                            key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>,
                        whom she now saw for the first time, blushed deeply as he cast a glance at
                        his female conqueror, and then stepped haughtily along, handling his gilded
                        chains as if they were an indifferent ornament. <q type="thought">I have
                        conquered him,</q> thought she: <q type="thought">it is a heavy blow to
                            so proud a head; and as he looks not unamiable, it might be politic as
                        well as courteous and kind in me to turn his submission into a more
                            willing one.</q> Alas! pity was helping admiration to a kinder set of
                        offices, than the generous-hearted queen suspected. The captive went to his
                        prison, a conqueror after all; for <persName key="Daphles" ref="#"
                            cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Daphles</persName> loved him.</p>
                    <p>The second night, after having exhibited in her manners a strange mixture of
                        joy and seriousness, and signified to her counsellors her intention of
                        setting the prisoner free, she released him with her own hands. Many a step
                        did she hesitate as she went down the stairs; and when she came to the door,
                        she shed a full, but soft, and as it seemed to her a wilful and refreshing
                        flood of tears, humbling herself for her approaching task. When she had
                        entered, she blushed deeply, and then turning as pale, stood for a minute
                        silent and without motion, She then said, <q type="spoken">Thy queen, <persName
                                key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional"
                            >Doracles</persName>,
                        has come to shew thee how kindly she can treat a great and gallant subject,
                        who did not know her</q> and with these words, and almost before she was
                        aware, the prisoner was released, and preparing to go. He appeared
                        surprised, but not off his guard, nor in any temper to be over-grateful. <q
                            type="spoken">
                            Name,</q> said he, <q
                            type="spoken">O queen, the conditions on </q></p>
                    <p><q type="spoken">which I depart, and they will be faithfully kept.</q>
                            <persName
                            key="Daphles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName>
                        moved her lips, but they spoke not. She waved her head and hand with a
                        deadly smile, as if free- ing him from all conditions; and he was turning to
                        go, when she fell senseless on the floor. The haughty warrior raised her
                        with more impatience than goodwill. He could guess at love in a woman; but
                        he had but a mean opinion both of it and her sex; and the deadly struggle in
                        the heart of <persName key="Daphles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional"
                        >
                        Daphles</persName> did not help him to distinguish the romantic passion,
                        which had induced her to put all her past and virgin notions of love into
                        his person, from the commonest liking that might flatter his soldierly
                        vanity.</p>
                    <p>The queen, on awaking from her swoon, found herself compelled, in very
                        justice to the intensity of a true passion, to explain how pity had brought
                        it upon her. <q type="spoken">I might ask it,</q> said she, <q type="spoken"
                        ><persName
                                key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional"
                            >Doracles</persName>,
                        in return;</q> and here she resumed something of her queen-like dignity; <q
                            type="spoken">but I feel that my modesty will
                            be sufficiently saved by the name of your wife: and a substantial
                            throne, with a return that shall nothing perplex or, interfere with
                            thee,
                            I do now accordingly</q></p>
                    <pb n="111" />
                    <p><q type="spoken">offer thee, not as the condition of thy freedom, but as a
                        diversion of men's eyes and thoughts from what they will think ill in
                            me, if they find me rejected.</q> And in getting out that hard word, her
                        voice <choice>
                            <orig>£aultered</orig>
                            <reg>faltered</reg>
                        </choice> a little, and <choice>
                            <orig>hfer</orig>
                            <reg>her</reg>
                        </choice> eyes filled with tears.</p>
                    <p><persName key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional">Doracles</persName>,
                        with the best grace his lately defeated spirit could assume, spoke in
                        willing terms of accepting her offer. They left the prison; and his full
                        pardon having been proclaimed, the courtiers, with feasts and
                        entertainments, vied who should seem best to approve their mistress's
                        choice; for so they were quick to understand it. The late captive, who was
                        really as graceful and accomplished as a proud spirit would let him be,
                        received and returned all their attention in princely sort; and <persName
                            key="Daphles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName>
                        was beginning to hope that he might turn a glad eye upon her some day, when
                        news was brought her that he had gone from court, nobody knew whither. The
                        next intelligence was too certain. He had passed the frontiers, and was
                        leaguing with her enemies for another struggle.</p>
                    <p>From that day, gladness, though not kindness, went out of the face of <persName
                            key="Daphles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName>.
                        She wrote him a letter, without a word of reproach in it, enough to bring
                        back the remotest heart that had the least spark of sympathy; but he only
                        answered it in a spirit, which shewed that he regarded • the deepest love
                        but as a wanton trifle. That letter touched her kind wits. She had had a
                        paper drawn up, leaving him her throne in case she should die; but some of
                        her ministers, availing themselves of her enfeebled spirit, had summoned a
                        meeting of the nobles, at which she was to preside in the dress she wore on
                        the day of victory; the sight of which, it was thought, with the arguments
                        which they meant to use, would prevail upon the assembly to urge her to a
                        revocation of the bequest. Her women dressed her, while she was almost
                        unconscious of what they were doing, for she had now began to fade quickly,
                        body as well as mind. They put on her the white garments edged with silver
                        waves, in remembrance of the stream of <persName key="Inachus" ref="#"
                            cert="high"
                            type="mythological">Inachus</persName>, the founder of the <placeName
                            key="Argos" ref="#" cert="high"
                            type="city">Argive</placeName> monarchy; the spear was brought out, to
                        be stuck by the side of the throne, instead of the sceptre; and their hands
                        prepared to put the same laurel on her head, which bound it's healthy white
                        temples, when she sat on horse-back, and saw the prisoner go by. But at
                        sight of it's twisted and withered green, she took it in her hand; and
                        looking about her in her chair with an air of momentary recollection, began
                        picking it, and letting the leaves fall upon the floor. She went on thus,
                        leaf after leaf, looking vacantly downwards; and when she had stripped <choice>
                            <orig>thie</orig>
                            <reg>the</reg>
                        </choice> circle half round, she
                        leaned her cheek against the side of her sick chair; and shutting her eyes
                        quietly, so died.</p>
                    <p>The envoys from Argos went to the court of Calydon, where Doracles then was,
                        and bringing him the diadem upon a black cushion, informed him at once of
                        the death of the queen, and her nomination of him to the throne. He shewed
                        little more than a ceremonious gravity at the former news; but could ill
                        contain his joy at the latter, and set off instantly to take possession.
                        Among the other nobles who feasted him, was one who, having been the
                        particular companion of the late king, had become like a second father to
                        his unhappy</p>
                    <pb n="112" />
                    <p>daughter. The new prince observing the melancholy which he scarcely affected
                        to repress, and seeing him look up occasionally at a picture which had a
                        veil over it, asked him what the picture was that seemed to disturb him so,
                        and why it was veiled. <q type="spoken">If it be the portrait of the late
                        king,</q> said <persName key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional"
                        >
                        Doracles</persName> ,<q type="spoken"> pray think me worthy of doing honour
                        to it, for he was a noble prince. Unveil it, pray. I insist upon it. What?
                        Am I not worthy to look upon my predecessors, <persName key="Phorbas"
                                ref="#"
                                cert="high"
                                type="fictional"
                            >Phorbas</persName>?</q> And at these words, he
                        frowned impatiently. <persName key="Phorbas" ref="#" cert="high"
                            type="fictional"
                        >
                            Phorbas</persName>, with a trembling hand, but not for want of courage,
                        withdrew the black covering; and the portrait of <persName key="Daphles"
                            ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="fictional">Daphles</persName>, in all her youth and
                        beauty, flashed upon the eyes of <persName key="Doracles" ref="#"
                            cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Doracles</persName>. It was not a melancholy face. It
                        was drawn before misfortune had touched it, and sparkled with a blooming
                        beauty, in which animal spirits and good-nature contended for predominance. <persName
                            key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional"
                        >Doracles</persName>
                        paused, and seemed struck. <q type="spoken">The
                            possessor of that face,</q> said he, inquiringly, <q type="spoken"
                        >could
                        never have been so sorrowful, as I have heard?</q>—<q
                            type="spoken">Pardon me, Sir,</q> answered <persName key="Phorbas"
                            ref="#"
                            cert="high" type="fictional">Phorbas</persName>; <q type="spoken">I was
                        as another father to her, and knew all.</q><q type="spoken"> It cannot
                            be,</q> returned the <persName key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high"
                            type="fictional">prince</persName>. The old man begged his other guests
                        to withdraw a while, and then told <persName key="Doracles" ref="#"
                            cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Doracles</persName> how many fond and despairing things
                        the queen had said of him, both before her wits began to fail, and after. <q
                            type="spoken">Her wits to fail?</q> murmured the <persName
                            key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional">king</persName>: <q
                            type="spoken">I have known what it is to feel almost a mad impatience of
                        the will; but I knew not that these — -- gentle creatures, women, could
                            so feel for such a trifle.</q><persName key="Phorbas" ref="#"
                            cert="high"
                            type="fictional">Phorbas</persName> brought out the laurel-crown, and
                        told him how it was that the half of it became bare. The impatient blood of <persName
                            key="Doracles" ref="#" cert="high" type="fictional"
                        >Doracles</persName>
                        mounted, but not in anger, to his face; and breaking up the party, he
                        requested that the picture might be removed to his own chamber, promising to
                        return it.</p>
                    <p>A whole year however did he keep it; and as he had no foreign enemies to
                        occupy his time, nor was disposed to enter into the common sports of peace,
                        it was understood that he spent the greatest part of his time, when he was
                        not in council, in the room where the picture hung. In truth, the image of
                        the once smiling <persName key="Daphles" cert="high" type="fictional"
                        >Daphles</persName>
                        haunted him wherever he went; and to ease himself of the yearning of wishing
                        her alive again and seeing her face, he was in the habit of being with it as
                        much as possible. His self-will turned upon him, even in that gentle shape.
                        Millions of times did he wish back the loving author of his fortunes, whom
                        he had treated with so clownish an ingratitude; and millions of times did
                        the sense of the impotence of his wish run up in red hurry to his cheeks,
                        and help to pull them into a gaunt melancholy. But this is not a repaying
                        sorrow to dwell upon. He was one day, after being in vain expected at
                        council, found lying madly on the floor of the room, dead. He had torn the
                        portrait from the wall. His dagger was in his heart; and his cheek lay upon
                        that blooming and smiling face, which had it been living, would never have
                        looked so at being revenged.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="colophon">
                    <p>Orders received by the Newsmen, by the Booksellers, and by the <orgName
                            type="publisher">Publisher</orgName>, <persName 
                            key="Joseph Appleyard" type="real">JOSEPH APPLEYARD</persName>, No. 19, <placeName
                            key="Catherine Street, Strand" corresp="United Kingdom"
                            ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_Street_(London)"
                            cert="high" type="street">Catherine-street, Strand</placeName>.— Price
                        2d. .Printed by <persName key="C. H. Reynell" type="real">C. H. Reynell</persName>,
                        No. 45, <placeName key="Broad Street, Golden Square"
                            corresp="United Kingdom" type="street">Broad-street, Golden-square</placeName>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
