<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://cwrc.ca/templates/css/tei.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <tei<persName key="He">He</persName>ader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>THE INDICATOR.</title>
                <title type="sub">No. XX.--WEDNESDAY, FEBRUARY 23rd, 1820.</title>
                <author>Leigh Hunt</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p />
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p />
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </tei<persName key="He">He</persName>ader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="issue" n="20">
                <pb n="153" />
                <div2 type="forematter"> 
                <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                <epigraph>
                    <l>There he arriving round about doth flie</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                    <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.<note type="citation">
                            <bibl>
                                <ref
                                    target="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Elizabeth_Spencer,_Baroness_Hunsdon" />
                            </bibl>
                        </note></l>
                    <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055"
                            cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                </epigraph>
                <head type="subtitle">No. XX.—<date when="1820-02-23" cert="high">WEDNESDAY,
                    FEBRUARY 23rd, 1820</date>.</head>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="1">
                <head type="header">RONALD OF THE PERFECT HAND.</head>
                <p>[The following tale is founded upon a tradition in <persName key="Anne Grant"
                        ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4768392" cert="high" type="real"><persName key="Mrs">Mrs</persName>.
                    Grant</persName>'s <title
                        key="Essays on the Superstitions of the Highlanders of <placeName key='Scotland'>Scotland</placeName>"
                        ref="https://archive.org/details/essaysonsuperst00grangoog/page/n12/mode/2up"
                        level="s">Superstitions of the <placeName key='Highlands'>Highlands</placeName></title>. It was originally intended
                    to be written in verse; which will account for it's present appearance.]</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>THE stern old shepherd of the air,</l>
                    <l>The spirit of the whistling hair,</l>
                    <l>The wind, has risen drearily</l>
                    <l>In the <placeName key='Northern'>Northern</placeName> evening sea,</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> is piping long and loud</l>
                    <l>To many a heavy upcoming cloud,—</l>
                    <l>Upcoming heavy in many a row,</l>
                    <l>Like the unwieldy droves below</l>
                    <l>Of seals, and horses of the sea,</l>
                    <l><persName key="That">That</persName> gather up as drearily,</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> watch with solemn-visaged eyes</l>
                    <l>Those mightier movers in the skies.</l>
                </lg>
                <lb />
                <lg>
                    <l>Tis evening quick;—tis <persName key="night:—the">night:—the</persName> rain</l>
                    <l>Is sowing wide the fruitless main,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Thick">Thick</persName>, thick;–no sight remains the while</l>
                    <l>From the farthest <placeName key='Orkney'>Orkney</placeName> isle,</l>
                    <l>No sight to sea-horse, or to seer,</l>
                    <l>But of a little pallid sail,</l>
                    <l><persName key="That">That</persName> seems as if twould struggle near,</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> then as if it's pinion pale</l>
                    <l><persName key="Gave">Gave</persName> up the battle to the gale.</l>
                    <l>Four chiefs there are of special note,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Labouring">Labouring</persName> in that earnest boat;</l>
                    <l>Four <placeName key='Orkney'>Orkney</placeName> chiefs, that yesterday</l>
                    <l><persName key="Coming">Coming</persName> in their pride away</l>
                    <l>From the smote Norwegian king,</l>
                    <l>Led their war-boats triumphing</l>
                    <l>Straight along the golden line</l>
                    <l>Made by moring's eye divine.</l>
                    <l><placeName key='Stately'>Stately</placeName> came they, one by one,</l>
                    <l>Every sail beneath the sun,</l>
                    <pb n="154" />
                    <l>As if he their admiral were</l>
                    <l><persName key="Lo">Lo</persName>oking down from the lofty air,</l>
                    <l><placeName key='Stately'>Stately</placeName>, stately through the gold.–</l>
                    <l>But before that day was done,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Lo">Lo</persName>, his eye grew vexed and cold;</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> every boat, except that one,</l>
                    <l>A tempest trampled in it's roar;</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> every man, except those four,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Was">Was</persName> drenched and driving, far from home,</l>
                    <l>dead and swift, through the <placeName key='Northern'>Northern</placeName> foam.</l>
                </lg>
                <lb />
                <lg>
                    <l>Four are they, who wearily</l>
                    <l>Have drunk of toil two days at sea;</l>
                    <l><persName key="Duth Maruno">Duth Maruno</persName>, steady and dark,</l>
                    <l><placeName key='Cormar'>Cormar</placeName>, Soul of the Winged Bark;</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> bright <persName key="Clan Alpin">Clan Alpin</persName>, who could leap</l>
                    <l>Like a torrent from steep to steep;</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> he, the greatest of that great band,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> of the Perfect Hand.</l>
                </lg>
                <lb />
                <lg>
                    <l>Dumbly strain they for the shore,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Foot">Foot</persName> to board, and grasp on oar,</l>
                    <l>The billows, panting in the wind,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Seem">Seem</persName> instinct with ghastly mind,</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> climb like crowding savages</l>
                    <l>At the boat that dares their seas.</l>
                    <l>Dumbly strain they, though and through,</l>
                    <l>Dumbly, and half blindly too,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Drench'd">Drench'd</persName>, and buffeted, and bending</l>
                    <l>Up and down without an ending,</l>
                    <l>Like ghostly things that could not cease</l>
                    <l>To row among those savages.</l>
                </lg>
                <lb />
                <lg>
                    <l><persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> of the Perfect Hand</l>
                    <l>Has rowed the most of all that band;</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> now he's resting for a space</l>
                    <l>At the helm, and turns his face</l>
                    <l>Round and round on every side</l>
                    <l>To see what cannot be descried,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Shore">Shore</persName>, nor sky, nor light, nor even</l>
                    <l>HOPE, whose feet are last in heaven.</l>
                    <l><persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> thought him of the roar</l>
                    <l>Of the fight the day before,</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> of the young Norwegian prince</l>
                    <l><persName key="Whome">Whome</persName> in all the worryings</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> hot vexations of the fray,</l>
                    <l><persName key="He">He</persName> had sent with life away,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Because">Because</persName> he told him of a bride</l>
                    <l><persName key="That">That</persName> if she lost him, would have died;</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> then, in bitter case,</l>
                    <l>Though of his own sweet lady's face,</l>
                    <l>Which upon this very night</l>
                    <l>Should have blushed with bridal light,</l>
                    <pb n="155" />
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> of her downward eyelids meek,</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> of her voice, just heard to speak,</l>
                    <l>As at the altar, hand in hand,</l>
                    <l>On ceasing of the organ grand,</l>
                    <l>'Twould have bound her, for weal or woe,</l>
                    <l>With delicious answers low.</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> more he though of, grave and sweet,</l>
                    <l><persName key="That">That</persName> made the thin tears start, and meet</l>
                    <l>The wetting of the insolent wave;</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>, who though all so brave,</l>
                    <l><persName key="Had">Had</persName> often that hard day before</l>
                    <l><persName key="Wished">Wished</persName> himself well housed on shore,</l>
                    <l>Felt a sharp impatient start</l>
                    <l>Of homesick wilfulness at heart,</l>
                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> steering with still firmer hand,</l>
                    <l>As if the boat could feel command,</l>
                    <l><placeName key='Thrilled'>Thrilled</placeName> with a fierce and forward motion,</l>
                    <l>As though 'twould shoot it through the ocean.</l>
                </lg>
                <lb />
                <p>"Some spirit," exclaimed <persName key="Duth Maruno">Duth Maruno</persName>, "must pursue us, and perpetually urge the
                    boat out of it's way, or we must have arrived by this time at <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName>."*<note>The
                    old name for the <placeName key='Orkney'>Orkney</placeName>s.</note> <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> took him at his owrd, and turn- ing
                    hastily round, thought he saw an armed figure behind the stern. His anger rose
                    with his despair; and with all his strength he dashed his arm at the moveless
                    and airy shape. At that instant a fierce blast of wind half turned the boat
                    round. The chieftains called out to <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> to set his whole heart at the rudder;
                    but the wind beat back their voices, like young birds into the nest; and no
                    answer followed it. The boat seemed less and less manageable, and at last to be
                    totally left to themselves. In the intervals of the wind they again called out
                    to <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>, but still received no answer. One of them crept forward, and felt for
                    him through the blinding wet and darkness. His place was void. "It was a ghost,"
                    said they, "which came to fetch him to the spirits of his fathers. <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> of the
                    Perfect Hand is gone, and we shall follow him as we did in the fight. Hark! The
                    wind is louder and louder: it is louder and many-voiced. Is it his voice which
                    has roused up the others? Is he calling upon us, as he did in the battle, when
                    his followers shouted after his call?"</p>
                <p>It was the rocks of an isle beyond <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName>, which made that mul-
                    titudinous roaring of the wind. The chieftains found that they were
                    not destined to perish in the mid ocean; but it was fortunate for
                    them that the wind did not set in directly upon the island, or they
                    would have been dashed to pieces upon the rocks. With great diffi-
                    culty they stemmed their way obliquely; and at length were thrown
                    violently to shore, bruised, wounded, and half inanimate. They
                    remained on this desolate island two days, during the first of which
                    the storm subsided. On the third, they were taken away by a boat
                    of seal-hunters.</p>
                <p>The chiefs, on their arrival at home, related how <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> of the <pb n="156" />
                    Perfect Hand had been summoned away by a loud-voiced spirit, and disappeared.
                    Great was the mourning in <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName> for the Perfect Hand; for the Hand that with
                    equal skill could throw the javelin and traverse the harp; could build the
                    sudden hut of the hunter; and bind up the glad locks of the maiden tired in the
                    dance. There- fore was he called the Perfect Hand; and therefore with great
                    mourning was he mourned; yet with non half as great as by his love, his
                    betrother bride <placeName key='Moilena'>Moilena</placeName>; by her of the Beautiful <placeName key='Voice'>Voice</placeName>, who had latterly begun
                    to be called the Perfect <placeName key='Voice'>Voice</placeName>, because she was to be matched with him of the
                    Perfect Hand. Perfect Hand and Per- fect <placeName key='Voice'>Voice</placeName> were they called; but the Hand
                    was now gone, and the <placeName key='Voice'>Voice</placeName> sang brokenly for tears.</p>
                <p>A dreary winter was it, though a victorious, to the people of Inis-
                    tore. Their swords had conquered in <persName key="Lo">Lo</persName>chlin; but most of the
                    hands that wielded them had never come back. Their warm pressure
                    was felt no more. The last which they had given their friends was
                    now to serve them all their lives. "Never, with all my yearning,"
                    said <placeName key='Moilena'>Moilena</placeName>, "shall I look upon his again, as I have looked at it a
                    hundred times, when nobody suspected. Never." <persName key="And">And</persName> she turned
                    from the sight of the destructive ocean, which seemed as interminable
                    as her thoughts.</p>
                <p>But winter had now passed away. The tears of the sky at least
                    were dried up. The sun looked out kindly again; and the spring
                    had scarcely re-appeared, when <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName> had a proud and a gladder
                    day, from the arrival of the young prince of <persName key="Lo">Lo</persName>chlin with his bride.
                    It was a bitter one to <placeName key='Moilena'>Moilena</placeName>, for the prince came to thank <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>
                    for sparing his life in the war, and had brought his lady to thank him
                    too. They thanked <placeName key='Moilena'>Moilena</placeName> instead; and proud, in the midst of her
                    unhappiness, of being the representative of the Perfect Hand, she
                    lavished hundred of smiles upon them from her pale face. But she
                    wept in secret. She could not bear this new addition to the store of
                    noble and kind memories respecting her <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>. <persName key="He">He</persName> had spared the
                    bridegroom for his bride. <persName key="He">He</persName> had hoped to come back to his own.
                    She looked over to the north; and thought that her home was as
                    much there as in <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName>.
                </p>
                <p>Meantime, <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> was not drowned. A Scandinavian boat, bound for an island called
                    the <placeName key='Island of the Circle'>Island of the Circle</placeName>, had picked him up. The crew, which consisted chiefly
                    of priests, were going thither to propitiate the deities, on account of the late
                    defeat of their country- men. They recognized the victorious chieftain, who on
                    coming to his senses freely confessed who he was. Instantly they raised a
                    chorus, which rose sternly through the tempest. "We carry," said they, "an
                    acceptable present to the <persName key="Gods">Gods</persName>. <persName key="Odin">Odin</persName>, stay thy hand from the slaughter of the
                    obscure. <persName key="Thor">Thor</persName>, put down the mallet with which thou beatest, like red hail, on
                    the skulls of thin enemies. Ye other feasters in <placeName key='Valhalla'>Valhalla</placeName>, set down the skulls
                    full of mead, and pledge a health out of a new and noble one to the King of <persName key="Gods">Gods</persName>
                    and Men, that the twilight of heaven may come late. We bring an acceptable
                    present: we bring <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> of the Perfect Hand." Thus they sang in the boat, <pb
                        n="157" /> labouring all the while with the winds and waves, but surer now
                    than ever of reaching the shore. <persName key="And">And</persName> they did so, by the first light of the
                    morning. When they came to the circle of sacred stones, from which the island
                    took it's name, they placed their late conquer- or by the largest, and kindled a
                    fire in the middle. The warm smoke rose thickly against the cold white morning.
                    "Let me be offered up to your gods," said <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>, "like a man, by the sword; and
                    not like food, by the fire." "We know all," answered the priests: "be thou
                    silent." "Treat not him," said <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>, "who spared your prince, unworthily. If
                    he must be sacrificed, let him die as your prince would have died by this hand."
                    Still they answered nothing, but "We know all: be thou silent." <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> could not
                    help wit- nessing these preparations for a new and unexpected death with an
                    emotion of terror; but disdain and despair were uttermost. Once, and but once,
                    his cheek turned deadly pale in thinking of <placeName key='Moilena'>Moilena</placeName>. <persName key="He">He</persName> shifted his posture
                    resolutely, and thought of the spirit of the dead whom he was about to join. The
                    priests then encircled the fire and the stone at which he tood, with another
                    devoting song; and <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> looked earnestly at the ruddy flames, which gave to
                    his cold body, as in mockery, a kindly warmth. The priests however did not lay
                    hands on him. They respected the sparer of their prince so far as not to touch
                    him themselves; they left him to be dispatched by the supernatural beings, whom
                    they confidently expected to come down for that purpose as soon as they had
                    retired.</p>
                <p><persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>, whose faith was of another description, saw their departure
                    with joy; but it was damped the next minute. What was he to do in
                    winter-time on an island, inhabited only by the aphibious creatures
                    of the <placeName key='northern sea'>northern sea</placeName>, and never touched at but for a purpose hostile
                    to his hopes? For he now recollected, that this was the island he
                    ad so often heard of, as the chief seat of the Scandivnavian religion;
                    whose traditions had so influenced countries of a different faith, that
                    it was believed in <placeName key='Scotland'>Scotland</placeName> as well as the continetn, that no human
                    being could live there many hours. Spirits, it was thought, appeared
                    in terrible superhuman shapes, like the bloody idols which the priests
                    worshipped; and carried him off.</p>
                <p>The warrior of <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName> had soon too much reason to know the extent of this
                    belief. <persName key="He">He</persName> was not without fear himself, but disdained to yield to any
                    circumstances without a struggle. <persName key="He">He</persName> refreshed himself with some snow-water; and
                    after climbing the highest part of the island to look for a boat in vain
                    (nothing was to be seen but the waves tumbling on all sides after the storm) he
                    instantly set about preparing a habitation. <persName key="He">He</persName> saw at a little distance, on a
                    slope, the mouth of a rocky cave. This he destined for his shelter at night; and
                    looking round for a defence for the door, as he knew not whether bears might not
                    be among the inhabitants, he cast his eyes upon the thinnest of the stones which
                    stood upright about the fire. The heart of the warrior, though of a different
                    faith, misgave him as he thought of appropriating this mystical stone, carved
                    full of strange figures; but half in courage, and half in the very despair of
                    fear, he suddenly <pb n="158" /> twisted it from it's place. No one appeared.
                    The fire altered not. The noise of the fowl and other creatures was no louder on
                    the shore. <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> smiled at his fears, and knew the undiminished vigour of the
                    Perfect Hand.</p>
                <p><persName key="He">He</persName> found the cavern already fitted for shelter; doubtless by the
                    Scandinavian priests. <persName key="He">He</persName> had bitter reason to know how well it
                    sheltered him; for day after day he hoped in vain that some boat
                    from <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName> would venture upon the island. <persName key="He">He</persName> beheld sails at a
                    distance, but they never came. <persName key="He">He</persName> piled stone upon stone, joined
                    old pieces of boats together, and made flags of the sea-weed; but all
                    in vain. The vessels, he thought, came nearer, but none so near as
                    to be of use; and a new and sickly kind of impatience cut across the
                    stout heart of <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>, and set it beating. <persName key="He">He</persName> knew not whether it
                    was with the cold or with misery, but his frame would shake for an
                    hour together, when he lay down on his dried weeds and feathers to
                    rest. <persName key="He">He</persName> remembered the happy sleeps that used to follow upon toil;
                    and he looked with double activity for the eggs and sliell-fish on which
                    he sustained himself, and smote double the number of seals, half
                    in the very exercise of his anger: and then he would fall dead asleep
                    with fatigue.</p>
                <p>In this way he bore up against the violences of the winter season,
                    which had now past. The sun looked out with a melancholy smile
                    upon the moss and the poor grass, checquered here and there with
                    flowers almost as poor. There was the buttercup, struggling from a
                    dirty white into a yellow; and a faint-coloured poppy, neither the
                    good nor the ill of which was then known; and here and there by the
                    thorny underwood a shrinking violet. The lark alone seemed chear-
                    ful, and startled the ear of the desolate chieftain with it's climbing
                    triumph in the air. <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> looked up. His fancy had been made
                    wild and wilful by strange habits and sickened blood; and he thought
                    impatiently, that if he were up there like the lark, he might see his
                    friends and his love in <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Being naturally however of a gentle as well as courageous disposi-
                    tion, the Perfect Hand found the advantage as well as necessity of
                    turning his violent impulses into noble matter for patience. <persName key="He">He</persName> had
                    heard of the dreadful bodily sufferings which the Scandinavian heroes
                    underwent from their enemies with triumphant songs. <persName key="He">He</persName> knew
                    that no such sufferings, which were fugitive, could equal the agonies
                    of a daily martyrdom of mind; and he cultivated a certain humane
                    pride of patience, in order to bear them.</p>
                <p>His only hope of being delivered from the island now depended on the Scandinavian
                    priests; but it was a moot point whether they would respect him for surviving,
                    or kill him on that very account, out of a mixture of personal and superstitious
                    resentment. <persName key="He">He</persName> thought his death the more likely; but this at least was a termi-
                    nation to the dreary prospect of a solitude for life; and partly out of that
                    hope, and partly from a courageous patience, he produced as many pleasant
                    thoughts and objects about him as he could. <persName key="He">He</persName> adorned his cavern with shells
                    and feathers; he made himself a cap <pb n="159" /> and cloak of the latter, and
                    boots and a vest of seal-skin, girding it about with the glossy sea-weed; he
                    cleared away a circle before the cavern, planted it with the best grass, and
                    heaped about it the mos- siest stones: he strung some bones of a fish with
                    sinews, and fitting a shell beneath it, the Perfect Hand drew forth the first
                    gentle music that had ever been heard in that wild island. <persName key="He">He</persName> touched it one day
                    in the midst of a flock of seals, who were basking in the sun; they turned their
                    heads towards the sound; he thought he saw in their mild faces a human
                    expression; and from that day forth no seal was ever slain by the Perfect Hand.
                    <persName key="He">He</persName> spared even the huge and cloudy-visaged walrusses, in whose societies he
                    beheld a dull resem- blance to the gentler affections; and his new intimacy with
                    these possessors of the place was completed by one of the former animals, who
                    having been rescued by him from a contest with a larger one, followed him about,
                    as well as it's half-formed and dragging legs would allow, with the officious
                    attachment of a dog.</p>
                <p>But the summer was gone and no one had appeared. The new thoughts,
                    and deeper insight into things, which solitude and sorrow-
                    ful necessity had produced, together with a diminution of his activity,
                    had not tended to strengthen him against the approach of winter;
                    and autumn came upon him like the melancholy twilight of the year.
                    <persName key="He">He</persName> had now no hope of seeing even the finishers of his existence be-
                    fore the spring. The rising winds among the rocks, and the noise
                    of the whales blowing up the spouted water till the hollow caverns
                    thundered with their echoes, seemed to be like heralds of the stern
                    season which was to close him in against all approach. <persName key="He">He</persName> had tried
                    one day to move the stone at the mouth of his habitation a little
                    further in, and found his strength fail him. <persName key="He">He</persName> laid himself half
                    reclining on the chilly ground, full of such melancholy thoughts as
                    half bewildered him. Things by turn appeared a fierce dream and a
                    fiercer reality. <persName key="He">He</persName> was leaning and looking on the ground, and
                    idly twisting his long hair, when his eyes fell upon the hand that
                    held it. It was livid and emaciated. <persName key="He">He</persName> opened and shut it, opened
                    and shut it again, turned it round, and looked at it's ribbed thin-
                    ness and laid-open machinery; many thoughts came upon him,
                    some which he understood not, and some which he recognized but
                    too well; and a turbid violence seemed rising at his heart, when the
                    seal his companion drew nigh, and began licking that weak memorial
                    of the Perfect Hand. A shower of self-pitying tears fell upon the
                    seal's face and the hand together.</p>
                <p>On a sudden, he heard a voice. It was a deep and loud one, and
                    distinctly called out, <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>! <persName key="He">He</persName> looked up, gasping with wonder.
                    Three times it called out, as if with peremptory command; and three
                    times the rocks and caverns echoed the word with a dim sullenness.</p>
                <p><persName key="Recollecting">Recollecting</persName> himself, he would have risen and answered, but the sudden change of
                    sensations had done what all his sufferings had not been able to do; and he
                    found himself unable either to rise or to speak. The voice ealled again and
                    again, but it was now more dis- tant; and <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>'s heart sickened as he heard it
                    retreating. His <pb n="160" /> strength seemed to fail him in proportion as it
                    became necessary. Suddenly the voice came back again. It advances. Other voices
                    are heard, all advancing. In a short time, figures come hastily down the slope
                    by the side of his cavern, looking over into the area before it as they descend.
                    They enter. They are before him and about him. Some of them, in a Scandinavian
                    habit, prostrate themselves at his feet, and address him in an unknown language.
                    But these are sent away by another, who remains with none but two youths. <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>
                    has risen a little, and leans his back against the rock. One of the youths puts
                    his arm between his neck and the rock, and half kneels beside him, turning his
                    face away and weeping. "I am no god, nor a favourite of gods, as these people
                    supposed me," said Ro- nald, looking up at the chief who was speaking to the
                    other youth :– "if thou wilt dispatch me then, do so. I only pray thee to let
                    the death be fit for a warrior, such as I once was." The chief appeared
                    agitated. "Speak not ill of the gods, <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>," said he, "although thou wert
                    blindly brought up. A warrior like thee must be a fa- vourite of heaven. I come
                    to prove it to thee: Dost thou not know me? I come to give thee life for life."
                    <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> looked more stead- fastly. It was the Scandinavian prince whom he had
                    spared, be- cause of his bride, in battle. <persName key="He">He</persName> smiled, and lifted up his hand to
                    him, which was intercepted and kissed by the youth who held his arm round his
                    neck. "Who are these fair youths?" said <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName>, half turning his head to look in
                    his supporter's face. "This is the bride I spoke of," answered the prince, "who
                    insisted on sharing this voyage with me, and put on this dress to be the bolder
                    in it." "<persName key="And">And</persName> who is the other?" The other, with dried eyes, looked smiling into
                    his, and intercepted the answer also.–"Who," said the sweetest voice in the
                    world, "can it be, but one?"–With a quick and almost fierce tone, <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> cried
                    out aloud "I know the voice;" and he would have fallen flat on the earth, if
                    they had not all three sup- ported him.</p>
                <p>It was a mild return to <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName>, <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> gathering strength all the
                    way at the eyes and voice of <placeName key='Moilena'>Moilena</placeName>, and the hands of all three.
                    Their discovery of him was easily explained. The crews of the ves-
                    sels, who had been afraid to come nearer, had repeatedly seen a figure
                    on the island making signs. The Scandinavian priests related how
                    they had left <persName key="Ronald">Ronald</persName> there, but insisted that no human being could
                    live upon it, and that some god wished to manifest himself to his
                    faithful worshippers. The heart of <placeName key='Moilena'>Moilena</placeName> was quick to guess the
                    truth. The prince proposed to accompany the priests. His bride
                    and the destined bride of his saviour went with him, and returned as
                    you heard; and from that day forth many were the songs in <placeName key='Inistore'>Inistore</placeName>,
                    upon the fortunes of the Perfect Hand and the kindness of the Per-
                    fect <placeName key='Voice'>Voice</placeName>. Nor were those forgotten, who forgot not others.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="colophon">
                <p>Orders received by the Booksellers, by the Newsmen, and by the Publisher, <persName type="real" key="Joseph Appleyard">J. Appleyard</persName>, 19, Catherin-street, Strand.–Price 2d.</p>
                <p>Printed by <persName type="real" key="<persName key="C. H. Reynell">C. H. Reynell</persName>"><persName key="C. H. Reynell">C. H. Reynell</persName></persName>, No. 45, Broad-street, Golden-square.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>