<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
    <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
        <teiHeader>
            <!-- File Description -->
            <fileDesc>
                <!-- Title of the work -->
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>The Indicator</title>
                    <author>Hunt, James <persName key="Henry">Henry</persName> Leigh (1784-1859)</author>
                </titleStmt>

                <publicationStmt>
                    <p />
                </publicationStmt>

                <!-- Author information -->
                <sourceDesc>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hunt, James <persName key="Henry">Henry</persName> Leigh (1784-1859)</author>
                        <title>The Indicator</title>
                        <date when="1819-11-24">NOVEMBER 24th, 1819</date> <!-- The publication date of this issue ({Month} {Day}, {Year}) -->
                        <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher> <!-- Publisher details if available -->
                    </bibl>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>

            <!-- Encoding Description -->
            <encodingDesc>
                <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
                <p>
                    Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers are
                    included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
                    preservation.
                </p>
            </encodingDesc>

            <!-- Profile Description -->
            <profileDesc>
            </profileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div1 type="issue" n="7">
                    <pb n="49" /> <!-- Page beginning -->
                    <div2 type="forematter"> <!-- Title, epigraph, and catalogue -->
                        <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                        <epigraph>
                            <p>There  is  a  bird  in  the  interior  of  <placeName key="Africa" corresp="Africa">Africa</placeName>,  whose  habits  would  rather  seem  to  belong  to  the  interior  of Fairy-land:  but  they  have  been,  well  authenticated.  It  indicates  to  honey-hunters  where  the  nests  of  wild bees  are  to  be  found.  It  calls  them  with  a  cheerful  cry,  which  they  answer;  and  on  finding  itself  recognized, flies  and  hovers  over  a  hollow  tree  containing  the  honey.  While  they  are  occupied  in  collecting  it,  the  bird goes  to  a  little  distance,  where  he  observes  all  that  passes;  and  the  hunters,  wnen  they  have  helped  themselves, take  care  to  leave  him  his  portion  of  the  food. — This  is  the  <hi rend="smallcaps">Cuculus Indicator  of  Linnæus</hi>,  otherwise called  the  Moroc,  Bee  Cuckoo,  or  Honey  Bird.</p>
                                <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
                                <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                                <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
                                <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055"
                                        cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                            </epigraph>
                            <head type="catalogue">No. I. <date when="1819-11-24">—WEDNESDAY, NOVEMBER 24th, 1819</date>.</head>
                        </div2>
                        <div2 type="section" n="1"> <!-- Header and content -->
                            <head type="header">LUDICROUS EXAGGERATION. </head>

    <p>Men of wit sometimes like to pamper a favourite joke into exaggeration  
    — into a certain corpulence of facetiousness. Their relish  
    of the thing makes them wish it as large as possible : and the social  
    enjoyment of it is doubled by it's becoming more visible to the eyes  
    of others. It is for this reason that jests in company are sometimes  
    built up by one hand after another, — <q type="emph">three-piled hyperboles,</q> — :  
    till the over-done <placeName type="fictional" key="Babel" corresp="Babylon">Babel</placeName> topples and tumbles down amidst a merry  
    confusion of tongues. </p>

    <p><persName type="fictional" key="Sir John Falstaff">Falstaff</persName> was a great master of this art. He loved a joke as large as  
    himself; witness his famous account of the men in <placeName type="fictional" key="buckram">buckram</placeName>. Thus he  
    tells <persName type="fictional" key="the Lord Chief Justice">the Lord Chief Justice</persName>, that he had lost his voice <q type="spoken">with singing  
    of anthems;</q><note type="source"><bibl><author><persName key="William Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName></author>, <title level="m">Henry IV</title> part 2, Act1 Scene2 </bibl></note> and he calls <persName type="fictional" key="Bardolph">Bardolph</persName>'s red nose <q type="spoken">a perpetual triumph,  
    an everlasting bonfire light</q><note type="source"><bibl><author><persName key="William Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName></author>, <title level="m">Henry IV part 1</title>, Act3 Scene3</bibl></note> and says it has saved him <q type="spoken">a thousand  
    marks in links and torches,</q><note type="source"><bibl><author><persName key="William Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName></author>, <title level="m">Henry IV part 1</title>, Act3 Scene3</bibl></note> walking with it <q type="spoken">in the night betwixt  
    tavern and tavern.</q><note type="source"><bibl><author><persName key="William Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName></author>, <title level="m">Henry IV part1</title>, Act3 Scene3</bibl></note> See how he goes heightening the account of  
    his recruits at every step : — <q type="spoken">You would think I had a hundred and  
    fifty tattered prodigals, lately come from swine-keeping, from eating  
    draff and husks. — A mad fellow met me on the way, and told me, I  
    had unloaded all the gibbets, and pressed the dead bodies. — No eye  
    hath seen such scare-crows. — I'll not march through <placeName key="Coventry" corresp="England">Coventry</placeName> with  
    them, that's flat.— Nay, and the villains march wide betwixt the  
    legs, as if they had gyves on; for indeed I had most of them out of  
    prison.— There's but a shirt and a half in all my company; — and the  
    half-shirt is two napkins, tacked together, and thrown over the  
    shoulders like a herald's coat without sleeves.</q><note type="source"><bibl><author><persName key="William Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName></author>, <title level="m">Henry IV</title> part1, Act4 Scene2</bibl></note> </p>

    <p>An old schoolfellow of ours, (who by the way, was more fond of  
    quoting <persName type="fictional" key="Sir John Falstaff">Falstaff</persName> than any other of <persName key="William Shakspeare">Shakspeare</persName>'s chararacters) used to  
    be called upon for a story, with a view to a joke of this sort; it  
    being an understood thing that he had a privilege of exaggeration,  
    without committing his abstract love of truth. The reader knows  

    <pb n="50"/>

    the old blunder attributed to <persName key="Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName> about a dish of green peas.  
    Somebody had been applauded in company for advising his cook to  
    take some ill-drest peas to <placeName key="Hammersmith" corresp="England">Hammersmith</placeName>, <q type="spoken">because that was the  
    way to turn'em Green;</q> upon which <persName key="Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName> is said to have gone  
    and repeated the pun at another table in this fashion; — <q type="spoken">John should  
    take those peas, I think, to <placeName key="Hammermsith" corresp="England">Hammersmith</placeName>.</q> <q type="spoken">Why so. Doctor?</q>  
    <q type="spoken">Because that is the way to make 'em green.</q> Now our friend  
    would give the blunder with this sort of additional dressing. At  
    sight of the dishes of vegetables.<persName key="Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName>, who was at his own  
    house, took off the covers, one after another, with great anxiety, till  
    he found that peas were among them; upon which he rubbed his  
    hands with an air of infinite and prospective satisfaction. <q type="spoken">You are  
    fond of peas. Sir?</q> said one of the company. <q type="spoken">Yes, Sir,</q> said  
    <persName key="Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName>, <q type="spoken">particularly so: — I eat them all the year round; — I  
    mean. Sir, every day in the season. I do not think there is any body  
    so fond of peas as I am!</q> <q type="spoken">Is there any particular reason, Doctor,</q>  
    asked a gentleman present, <q type="spoken">why you like peas so much, beyond the  
    usual one of their agreeable taste?</q> — <q type="spoken">No, Sir, none whatsoever : —  
    none I assure you</q> (here <persName key="Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName> shewed a great wish to impress  
    this fact on his guests): <q type="spoken">I never heard any particular, encomium  
    or speech about them from any one else : but they carry their own  
    eloquence with them: they are things. Sir, of infinite taste.</q> (Here  
    a laugh, which put <persName key="Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName> in additional spirits.) <q type="spoken">But, bless  
    me!</q> he exclaimed, looking narrowly into the peas: — <q type="spoken">I fear they are  
    very ill-done: they are absolutely yellow instead of green</q> (here he  
    put a strong emphasis on green); <q type="spoken">and you know, peas should be  
    emphatically green: — greenness in a pea is a quality as essential, as  
    whiteness in a lily. The cook has quite spoilt them : — but I'll give  
    the rogue a lecture, gentlemen, with your permission.</q> <persName key="Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName>  
    then rose and rang the bell violently for the cook, who came in, ready  
    booted and spurred. <q type="spoken">Ha!</q> exclaimed <persName key="Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName>, <q type="spoken">those boots and  
    spurs are your salvation, you knave. Do you know. Sir, what you  
    have done?</q> — <q type="spoken">No, Sir.</q> — <q type="spoken">Why, you have made the peas yellow.  
    Sir. Go instantly, and take 'em to <placeName key="Hammermsith" corresp="England">Hammersmith</placeName>.</q> <q type="spoken">To <placeName key="Hammermsith" corresp="England">Hammersmith</placeName>,  
    Sir?</q> cried the man, all in astonishment, the guests being no  
    less so : — <q type="spoken">please Sir, why am I to take 'em to <placeName key="Hammermsith" corresp="England">Hammersmith</placeName>?</q> —  
    <q type="spoken">Because, Sir,</q> and here <persName key="Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName> looked round with triumphant  
    anticipation, <q type="spoken">that is the way to render those peas green.</q> </p>

    <p>There is a very humourous piece of exaggeration in <persName key="Samuel Butler">Butler</persName>'s  
    remains,— a collection, by the bye, well worthy of <title level="a">Hudibras</title> and  
    indeed of more interest to the general reader. <persName key="Samuel Butler">Butler</persName> is defrauded of  
    his fame with readers of taste who happen to be no politicians, when  
    <title level="a">Hudibras</title> is printed without this appendage. The piece we allude  
    to is a short Description of <placeName key="Holland" corresp="The Netherlands">Holland</placeName> : — </p>

    <cit>
        <quote>
    <lg>
    <l>A country that draws fifty foot of water,  </l>
    <l>In which men live as in the hold of nature; </l> 
    <l>And when the sea does in upon them break, </l>
    <l>And drowns a province, does but spring a leak. </l>
    <metamark function="multilineEllipsis"> - - - - - - - </metamark>
    <pb n="51"/>

    <l>That feed, like cannibals, on other fishes, </l>
    <l>And serve their cousin-germans up in dishes. </l> 
    <l>A land that rides at anchor, and is moored. </l> 
    <l>In which they do not live, but go aboard. </l></lg>
        </quote>
        <note type="source"> 
            <bibl><author>Samuel Butler</author><title level="a">Description of Holland</title><ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Genuine_Remains_in_Verse_and_Prose_of_Mr._Samuel_Butler/Volume_1/Description_of_Holland"/></bibl>
        </note>
    </cit>

    <p>We do not know, and perhaps it would be impossible to discover,  
    whether <persName key="Samuel Butler">Butler</persName> wrote his minor pieces before those of the great  
    patriot <persName key="Andrew Marvell">Andrew Marvell</persName>, who rivalled him in wit and excelled him in  
    poetry. <persName key="Andrew Marvell">Marvell</persName>, though born later, seems to have been known earlier  
    as an author. He was certainly known publicly before him. But in  
    the political poems of <persName key="Andrew Marvell">Marvell</persName> there is a ludicrous Character of  
    <placeName key="Holland" corresp="The Netherlands">Holland</placeName>, which might be pronounced to be either the copy or the original  
    of <persName key="Samuel Butler">Butler</persName>'s, if in those Anti-Batavian times the Hollander had  
    not been baited by all the wits; and were it not probable, that the  
    unwieldy monotony of his character gave rise to much the same  
    ludicrous imagery in many of their fancies. <persName key="Andrew Marvell">Marvell</persName>'s wit has the  
    advantage of <persName key="Samuel Butler">Butler</persName>'s, not in learning or multiplicity of contrasts (for  
    nobody ever beat him there), but in a greater variety of them, and  
    in being able, from the more poetical turn of his mind, to bring graver   
    and more imaginative things to wait upon his levity. </p>

    <p>He thus opens the battery upon our amphibious neighbour : — </p>
    
    <cit>
        <quote>
    <lg xml:id="verse1"><l><placeName key="Holland" corresp="The Netherlands">Holland</placeName>, that scarce deserves the name of land, </l>
    <l>As but the off-scouring of the British sand;  </l>
    <l>And so much earth as was contributed  </l>
    <l>By English pilots, when they heaved the lead; </l> 
    <l>Or what by the ocean's slow alluvion fell.  </l>
    <l>Of shipwrecked cockle and the muscle-shell. </l></lg>

    <lg xml:id="verse2"><l>Glad then, as miners who have found the ore. </l>
    <l>They, with mad labour, <note type="hunt" place="foot"><persName key="John Dryden">Dryden</persName> afterwards, of fighting for gain, in his song of <q type="mentioned">Come, if you dare:</q>  <l>The Gods from above the mad labour behold, </l></note> fished the land to shore; </l>
    <l>And dived as desperately for each piece  </l>
    <l>Of earth, as if it had been of ambergreece; </l>
    <l>Collecting anxiously small loads of clay.  </l>
    <l>Less than what building swallows bear away;  </l>
    <l>Or than those pills which sordid beetles rowl. </l> 
    <l>Transfusing into them their dunghill soul. </l></lg>
        </quote>
        <note type="source"> 
            <bibl><author>Andrew Marvell</author><title level="a">The Character of Holland</title><ref target="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/44678/the-character-of-holland"/></bibl>
        </note>
    </cit>
    <p>He goes on in a strain of exquisite hyperbole : — </p>

    <cit><quote>
    <lg xml:id="verse3"><l>How did they rivet with gigantic piles  </l>
    <l>Thorough the centre <hi rend="italic">their new-catched miles;</hi> </l> 
    <l>And to the stake a <hi rend="italic">struggling country</hi> bound.  </l>
    <l>Where barking waves still bait the forced ground;  </l>
    <l>Building their wat'ry <persName type="fictional" key="Babel">Babel</persName> far more high </l>
    <l>To catch the waves, than those to scale the sky. </l> 
    <l>Yet still his claim the injured ocean layed.  </l>
    <l>And oft at leap frog o'er their steeples played; </l>
    <l>As if on purpose it on land had come  </l>
    <l>To shew them what's their <hi xml:lang="latin">Mare Liberum</hi>; <note type="translation-hunt" place="foot"> A <hi rend="italic">Free</hi> Ocean. </note></l>
    <l>A dayly deluge over them does boil;  </l>
    <l>The earth and water play at level-coyl;  </l>

    <pb n="52"/>

    <l>The fish oft-times the burgher dispossessed.  </l>
    <l>And sat, not as a meat, but as a guest :  </l>
    <l>And oft the Tritons, and the Sea-nymphs, saw  </l>
    <l>Whole shoals of Dutch served up for cabillau.  </l>
    <l>Or, as they over the new level ranged,  </l>
    <l>For pickled herring, pickled Heeren changed.  </l>
    <l>Nature, it seemed, ashamed of her mistake.  </l>
    <l>Would throw their land away at duck and drake :  </l>
    <l>Therefore necessity, that first made kings.  </l>
    <l>Something like government among them brings:  </l>
    <l>For as with Pigmys, who best kills the crane.  </l>
    <l>Among the hungry he that treasures grain.  </l>
    <l>Among the blind the one-eyed blinkard reigns. </l> 
    <l>So rules among the drowned he that drains.  </l>
    <l>Not who first sees the rising sun, commands;  </l>
    <l>But who could first discern the rising lands;  </l>
    <l>Who best could know to pump an earth so leak.  </l>
    <l>Him they their lord and country's father speak; </l> 
    <l>To make a bank was a great plot of state; —  </l>
    <l>Invent a shovel, and be a magistrate. </l></lg>
</quote>
<note type="source"> 
    <bibl><author>Andrew Marvell</author><title level="a">The Character of Holland</title><ref target="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/44678/the-character-of-holland"/></bibl>
</note>
</cit>

    <p>We can never read these or some other ludicrous verses of <persName key="Andrew Marvell">Marvell</persName>,  
    even when by ourselves, without laughter; but we must curtail our  
    self-indulgence for the present. </p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="2">
    <head type="header">GILBERT! GILBERT! </head>

    <p>The idea generally conveyed to us by historians of <persName key="Thomas Becket">Thomas à Becket</persName>  
    is that of a mere haughty priest, who tried to elevate the religious  
    power above the civil. But in looking more narrowly into the accounts  
    of him, it appears that for a great part of his life he was a  
    merry layman, was a great falconer, feaster, and patron, as well as  
    man of business; and he wore all characters with such unaffected  
    pleasantness to all ranks, that he was called the Delight of the  
    Western World. </p>

    <p>All on a sudden, to every body's surprise, <persName key="King Henry II">Henry the 2nd</persName>, from  
    Chancellor made him Archbishop; and with equal suddenness, though  
    retaining his affability, <persName key="Thomas Becket">the new head of the English church</persName> put off  
    all his worldly graces and pleasures (save and except a rich gown  
    over his sackcloth); — and in the midst of a gay court, became the  
    most mortified of ascetics. Instead of hunting and hawking, he  
    paced a solitary cloister; instead of his wine, he drank fennel-water;  
    and in lieu of soft clothing, he indulged his back in stripes. </p>

    <p>This phenomenon has divided the opinions of the moral critics.  
    Some insist that <persName key="Thomas Becket">Becket</persName> was religiously in earnest, and think the  
    change natural to a man of the world whose heart had been struck  
    with reflection. Others see in it nothing but ambition. We certainly  
    think that three parts of the truth are with the latter; and  
    that <persName key="Thomas Becket">Becket</persName>, suddenly enabled to dispute a kind of sovereignty with  
    his prince and friend, gave way to the new temptation, just as he had  
    done to his falconry, and fine living. But the complete alteration of  
    his way of life — the enthusiasm which enabled him to set up so  

    <pb n="53"/>

    different a greatness against his former one, — shews, that his character  
    partook at least of as much sincerity, as would enable him to delude  
    himself in good taste. In proportion as his very egotism was  
    concerned, it was likely that such a man would exalt the gravity and  
    importance of his new calling. He had flourished at an earthly court :  
    he now wished to be as great a man in the eyes of another; and  
    worldly power, which was at once to be enjoyed and despised by virtue  
    of his religious office, had a zest given to it's possession, of which the  
    incredulousness of mere insincerity could know nothing. </p>

    <p><persName key="Thomas Becket">Thomas à Becket</persName> may have inherited his portion of the romantic  
    from his mother, whose story is a singular one. His father, <persName key="Gilbert Becket">Gilbert  
    Becket</persName>, who was afterwards a flourishing citizen, was in his youth  
    a soldier in the crusades; and being taken prisoner, became slave to  
    an Emir or Saracen prince. By degrees he obtained the confidence  
    of his master, and was admitted to his company, where he met a  
    personage who became more attached to him. This was the Emir's  
    daughter. Whether by her means or not does not appear; but after  
    some time he contrived to escape. The lady with her loving heart  
    followed him. She knew, they say, but two words of his language, —  
    <placeName key="London" corresp="England">London</placeName> and <persName key="Gilbert Becket">Gilbert</persName>; and by repeating the former, she obtained a  
    passage in a vessel, arrived in <placeName key="England" corresp="England">England</placeName>, and found her trusting way  
    to the metropolis. She then took to her other talisman, and went  
    from street to street pronouncing <persName key="Gilbert Becket">Gilbert</persName>. A crowd collected about  
    her wherever she went, asking of course a thousand questions, and  
    to all she had but one answer — <persName key="Gilbert Becket">Gilbert</persName>! <persName key="Gilbert Becket">Gilbert</persName>! She found her  
    faith in it sufficient. Chance, or her determination to go through  
    every street, brought her at last to the one, in which he who had  
    won her heart in slavery, was living in prosperous condition. The  
    crowd drew the family to the window; his servant recognized her;  
    and <persName key="Gilbert Becket">Gilbert Becket</persName> took to his arms, and his bridal bed, his far-come  
    princess, with her solitary fond word. </p>

    <p>These are better histories than the quarrels of kings and archbishops. </p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="3">
    <head type="header">FATAL MISTAKE OF NERVOUS DISORDERS FOR INSANITY. </head>

    <p>Some affecting catastrophes in the public papers induce us to say  
    a few words on the mistaken notions, which are so often, in our  
    opinion, the cause of their appearance. It is much to be wished  
    that some physician, truly so called, and philosophically competent  
    to the task, would write a work on this subject. We have plenty of  
    books on symptoms and other alarming matters, very useful for  
    increasing the liarm already existing. We believe also there are some  
    works of a different kind, if not written in direct counteraction; but  
    the learned authors are apt to be so prodigiously grand and etymological  
    in their title-pages, that they must frighten the general understanding  
    with their very advertisements. </p>

    <pb n="54"/>

    <p>There is this great difFeience between what is generally understood  
    by the word insanity, and the nervous or melancholy disorders, the  
    excess of which is so often confounded with it. Insanity is a consequence  
    of malformation of the brain, and is by no means of necessity  
    attended with melancholy or even ill health. The patient, in the  
    very midst of it, is often strong, healthy, and even chearful. On the  
    other hand, nervous disorders or even melancholy in it's most aggravated  
    state, is nothing but the excess of a state of stomach and  
    blood, extremely common. The mind no doubt will act upon that  
    state, and exasperate it; but there is great reaction between mind  
    and body; and as it is a common thing for a man in an ordinary  
    fever, or fit of the bile, to be melancholy, and even to do or feel  
    inclined to do an extravagant thing, so it is as common for him to get  
    well and be quite chearful again. Thus it is among witless people  
    that the true insanity will be found. It is the more intelligent that  
    are subject to the other disorders; and a proper use of their  
    intelligence will shew them what the disorders are. </p>

    <p>But weak treatment may frighten the intelligent. A kind persbn  
    for instance, in a fit of melancholy, may confess that he feels an  
    inclination to do some desperate or even cruel thing. This is  
    often treated at once as insanity, instead of an excess of the kind  
    just mentioned; and the person seeing he is thought mad, begins to  
    think himself so, and at last acts as if he were. This is a lamentable  
    evil; but it does not stop here. The children or other relatives  
    of the person may become victims to the mistake. They think there  
    is madness, as the phrase is, <q type="soCalled">in the family;</q> and so whenever they  
    feel ill, or meet with a misfortune, the thought will prey upon their  
    minds; and this may lead to catastrophes, with which they have really  
    no more to do than any other sick or unfortunate people. How  
    many persons have committed an extravagance in a brain fever, or  
    undergone hallucinations of mind in consequence of getting an ague,  
    or taking opium, or fifty other causes; and yet the moment the least   
    wandering of mind is observed in them, others become frightened;  
    their fright is manifested beyond all necessity; and the patients and  
    their family must suffer for it. They seem to think, that no disorder  
    can properly be held a true Christian sickness, and fit for charitable  
    interpretation, but where the patient has gone regularly to  
    bed, and had curtains, and caudle-cups, and nurses about him,  
    like a well-behaved respectable sick gentleman. But this state of  
    things implies muscular weakness, or weakness of that sort which  
    renders the bodily action feeble. Now, in nervous disorders, the  
    muscular action may be as strong as ever; and people may reasonably  
    be allowed a world of illness, sitting in their chairs, or even  
    walking or running. </p>

    <p>These mistaken pronouncers upon disease ought to be told, that  
    when they are thus unwarrantably frightened, they are partaking of  
    the very essence of what they misapprehend; for it is fear, in all it's  
    various degrees and modifications, which is at the bottom of nervousness  
    and melancholy; not fear in it's ordinary sense, as opposed to  

    <pb n="55"/>

    cowardice, (for ainan who would shudder at a bat or a vague idea, may  
    be bold as a lion against an enemy), but imaginative fear ; — fear  
    either of something known, or of the patient knows not what; — a  
    vague sense of terror, — an impulse, — an apprehension of ill, —  
    dwelling upon some painful and worrying thought. Now this suffering  
    is inevitably connected with a weak state of the body in some  
    respects, particularly of the stomach. Hundreds will be found to  
    have felt it, if patients enquire; but the mind is sometimes afraid of  
    acknowledging it's apprehensions even to itself ; and thus fear  
    broods over and hatches fear. </p>

    <p>These disorders, generally speaking, are greater or less in their  
    effects according to the exercise of reason. But do not let the word  
    be misunderstood : we should rather say, according to the extent  
    of the information. A very imaginative man will indeed be  
    likely to suffer more than otheis; but if his knowledge is at all in  
    proportion, he will also gfet through his evil better than an  
    uninformed man suffering great terrors. And the reason is, that he  
    knows how much bodily unhealthiness has to do with it. The very  
    words that frighten the unknowing, might teach them better, if  
    understood. Thus insanity itself properly means nothing but  
    unhealthiness or unsoundness. Derangement explains itself, and may surely  
    mean very harmless things. melancholy is compounded of two  
    words, which signify dark bile. Hypochondria is the name of one   
    of the regions of the stomach, — a very instructive etymology. And  
    lunacy refers to effects, real or imaginary, of particular states of  
    the moon; which if any thing after all, are nothing more than what  
    every delicate constitution feels in its degree from particular states  
    of the weather; for weather, like the tides, is apt to be in such and  
    such a condition, when the moon presents such and such a face. </p>

    <p>It has been said. </p>
    <l>Great wits to madness nearly are allied.</l>

    <p>It is curious that he who wrote the saying (<persName key="John Dryden">Dryden</persName>) was a very  
    sound wit to the end of his life; while his wife, who was of a weak  
    understanding, became insane. An excellent writer (<persName key="William Wordsworth">Wordsworth</persName>) has  
    written an idle couplet about the insanity of poets : </p>

    <q>We poets enter on our path with gladness,  
    But thereof comes in the end despondency and madness. </q>

    <p>If he did not mean madness in the ordinary sense, he should not  
    have written this line; if he did, he ought not to have fallen, in the  
    teeth of his information, into so vulgar an error. There are very  
    few instances of insane poets, or of insane great understandings  
    of any sort. <persName key="Francis Bacon">Bacon</persName>, <persName key="Milton">Milton</persName>, <persName key="Newton">Newton</persName>, <persName key="William Shakspeare">Shakspeare</persName>, <persName key="Cervantes">Cervantes</persName>, etc.  
    were all of minds as sound as they were great. So it has been with  
    the infinite majority of literary men of all countries. If <persName key="Torquato Tasso">Tasso</persName> and a  
    few others were exceptions, they were but exceptions; and the  
    derangement in these eminent men has very doubtful characters about  
    it, and is sometimes made a question.  It may be pretty safely  

    <pb n="56"/>

    affirmed, at least, upon an examination of it, that had they not been  
    the clever men they were, it would have been much worse and less  
    equivocal. <persName key="Collins">Collins</persName>, whose case was after all one of inanition rather  
    than insanity, had been a free liver; and seems to have been hurt by  
    having a fortune left him. <persName key="Cowper">Cowper</persName> was weak-bodied, and beset  
    by Methodists. <persName key="Jonathan Swift">Swift</persName>'s body was full of bad humours. He  
    himself attributed his disornered system to the effects of a surfeit of  
    fruit on his stomach; and in his last illness he used to break out in  
    enormous biles and blisters. This was a violent effort of nature to  
    help and purify the current of his blood, — the main object in all  
    such cases. <persName key="Samuel Johnson">Dr. Johnson</persName>, who was subject to mists of melancholy,  
    used to fancy he should go mad; but he never did. </p>

    <p>Exercise, conversation, cheerful society, amusements of all sorts, or  
    a kind, patient, and gradual helping of the bodily health, till the mind  
    be capable of amusement (for it should never foolishly be told <q>not to  
    think</q> of melancholy things, without having something done for it  
    to mend the bodily health), — these are the cures, the only cures, and  
    in our opinion the almost infallible cures of nervous disorders,  
    however excessive. Above all, the patient shoidd be told, that there has  
    often been an end to that torment of one haunting idea, which is  
    indeed a great and venerable suffering. Many persons have got over  
    it in a week, a few weeks, or a month, some in a few months, some  
    not for years, but they have got over it at last. There is a remarkable  
    instance of this in the life of our great <persName key="King Alfred the Great">king Alfred</persName>. He was  
    seized, says his contemporary biographer, with such a strange illness,  
    while sitting at table in the twenty-fifth year (we think) of his age,  
    that he shrieked aloud; and for twenty years afterwards this illness  
    so preyed upon him, that the relief of one hour was embittered by  
    what he dreaded would come the next. His disorder is conjectured  
    by some to have been an internal cancer; by others, with more  
    probability, the black bile, or melancholy. The physicians of those  
    times knew nothing about it; and the people shewed at once their  
    ignorance, and their admiration of <persName key="King Alfred the Great">the king</persName>, by saying that the devil  
    had caused it out of jealousy. It was probably produced by anxiety  
    for the state of his country; but the same thing which wounded him  
    might have helped to keep him up; for he had plenty of business to.  
    attend to, and fought with his own hand in fifty-six pitched battles.  
    Now exactly twenty years after, in the forty-fifth year of his age (if  
    our former recollection is right) this disorder totally left him; and  
    his great heart was where it ought to be, in a heaven of health and  
    calmness. </p>
    </div2>

    <div2 type="correspondents"> <!-- Publisher and printer information -->
                    <p>[ As this publication is unstamped, it will not circulate by means of the  
                    general post without a heavy expense. Persons in the country who  
                    wish to become subscribers, should therefore order it of booksellers who  
                    send weekly or monthly parcels to their respective places of residence.  
                    The delay would be of little consequence with a work not containing  
                    any thing of merely temporary interest. ] </p> 
                    </div2>
<div2 type="colophon" rend="center">
                <p>Orders received by the Booksellers, by the Newsmen, and by the Publisher, <persName type="real" key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName>, <placeName type="address" key="19, Catherine-street, Strand" corresp="England">19, Catherine-street, Strand</placeName>. –Price Two-pence.</p>
                <p>Printed by <persName type="real" key="C. H. Reynell">C. H. Reynell</persName>, <placeName type="address" key="No. 45, Broad-street, Golden-square, London" corresp="England">No. 45, Broad-street, Golden-square, London</placeName>.</p>
            </div2>
                </div1>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    
