<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <!-- File Description -->
        <fileDesc>
            <!-- Title of the work -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Indicator</title>
                <author>Hunt, James Henry Leigh (1784-1859)</author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <p />
            </publicationStmt>

            <!-- Author information -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Hunt, James Henry Leigh (1784-1859)</author>
                    <title>The Indicator</title>
                    <date when="1819-10-20">OCTOBER 20th", 1819</date> <!-- The publication date of this issue ({Month} {Day}, {Year}) -->
                    <pubPlace><settlement><placeName key='London'>London</placeName></settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher> <!-- Publisher details if available -->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <!-- Encoding Description -->
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
            <p>
                Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers are
                included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
                preservation.
            </p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <!-- Profile Description -->
        <profileDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="issue" n="2">
                <pb n="9" /> <!-- Page beginning -->
                <div2 type="forematter"> <!-- Title, epigraph, and catalogue -->
                    <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                    <epigraph>
                    <p>There  is  a  bird  in  the  interior  of  <placeName key='Africa'>Africa</placeName>,  whose  habits  would  rather  seem  to  belong  to  the  interior  of Fairy-land:  but  they  have  been,  well  authenticated.  It  indicates  to  honey-hunters  where  the  nests  of  wild bees  are  to  be  found.  It  calls  them  with  a  cheerful  cry,  which  they  answer;  and  on  finding  itself  recognized, flies  and  hovers  over  a  hollow  tree  containing  the  honey.  While  they  are  occupied  in  collecting  it,  the  bird goes  to  a  little  distance,  where  he  observes  all  that  passes;  and  the  hunters,  wnen  they  have  helped  themselves, take  care  to  leave  him  his  portion  of  the  food. — This  is  the  <hi rend="smallcaps">Cuculus Indicator  of  Linnæus</hi>,  otherwise called  the  Moroc,  Bee  Cuckoo,  or  Honey  Bird.</p>
                        <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
                        <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                        <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
                        <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055"
                                cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                    </epigraph>
                    <head type="catalogue">No. II. <date when="1819-10-20">—WEDNESDAY, OCTOBER 20th, 1819</date>.</head>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="1"> <!-- Header and content -->
                    <head type="header"> THE INDICATOR AND EXAMINER. — AUTUMNAL COMMENCEMENT 
OF FIRES. — MANTLE-PIECES. — APARTMENTS FOR STUDY. </head>
<p>One or two persons, we understand, have supposed that the present  
periodical work will interfere with the literary part of another, in  
which the Editor has long been concerned. This is a great mistake.  
The Examiner will continue to be- more literary, as well as painstaking  
in every other respect, than it has ever been. It will have  
more than the usual literature, for instance, connected with politics  
and criticism, — especially the latter. Indeed, should the new paper  
injure the old one, it would be dropped. The fact is, that as far as  
the Editor is concerned, the Examiner is to be regarded as the  
reflection of his public literature, and the Indicator of his private.  
In the one he has a sort of public meeting with his friends : in the  
other, a more retired one. The Examiner is his tavern-room for  
politics, for political pleasantry, for criticism upon the theatres and   
living writers. The Indicator is his private room, his study, his  
retreat from public care and criticism, with the reader who chuses  
to accompany him.</p>

<p>Here we are then, this chilly weather, with a warm fire. How  
pleasant it is to have fires again ! We have not time to regret summer,  
when the cold fogs begin to force us upon the necessity of having  
a new kind of warmth; — a warmth not so fine as sunshine, but as  
manners go, more sociable. The English get together over their  
fires, as the Italians do in their summer-shade. We do not enjoy our  
sunshine as we ought: our climate in general seems to render us  
almost unaware that the weather is fine, when it really becomes so:  
but for the same reason, we make as much of our winter as the  
anti-social habits that have grown upon us from other causes will allow.  
And for a similar reason, the southern European is unprepared for a  
cold day. The houses in <placeName key='Italy'>Italy</placeName> are almost all summer-houses, letting  
in the air on every side; so that when a fit of cold weather comes  
on the dismayed inhabitant, walking and shivering about with a  

<pb n="10"/>

little brazier in his hands, presents an awkward image of insufficiency  
and perplexity. A few of our fogs, shutting up the sight of  
every thing out of doors, and making the trees and the eves of the  
houses drip like rain, would soon admonish him to get warm in good  
earnest. If "the web of our life" is always to be of a mingled  
yarn," a good warm hearth-rug is not the worst part of the manufacture.</p>

<p>Here we are then again, with our fire before us, and our books on  
each side. What shall we do? Shall we take out a Life of somebody,  
or a <persName key="Theocritus">Theocritus</persName>, or <persName key="Dante">Dante</persName>, or <persName key="Ariosto">Ariosto</persName>, or <persName key="Montaigne">Montaigne</persName>, or <persName key="Marcus Aurelius">Marcus Aurelius</persName>,  
or <persName key="Horace">Horace</persName>, or <persName key="william Shakspeare">Shakspeare</persName> who includes them all? Or shall we  
read an engraving from <persName key="Poussin">Poussin</persName> or <persName key="Raphael">Raphael</persName>? Or shall we sit with  
tilted chairs, planting our wrists upon our knees, and toasting the  
up-turned palms of our hands, <hi rend="italic">while we discourse of manners and of  
mans heart and hopes, with at least a sincerity, a good intention, and  
good nature,</hi> that shall warrant what we say with the sincere, the  
good-intentioned, and the good-natured?</p>

<p>Ah — take care. You see what that old looking saucer is, with  
a handle to it. It is a venerable piece of earthenware, which may  
have been worth, to an Athenian, about two-pence; but to an author,  
is worth a great deal more than ever he could — deny for it. And  
yet he would depy it too. It will fetch his imagination more than  
ever it fetched potter or penny-maker. It's little shallow circle  
overflows for him with the milk and honey of a thousand pleasant  
associations. This is one of the uses of having mantle-pieces. You  
may often see on no very rich mantle-piece a representative body of  
all the elements, physical and intellectual,— a shell for the sea, a  
stuffed bird or some feathers for the air, a curious piece of mineral  
for the earth, a glass of water with some flowers in it for the visible  
process of creation, — a cast from sculpture for the mind of man;—  
and underneath all, is the bright and ever-springing fire, running  
up through them heavenwards, like hope through materiality. We  
like to have any little curiosity of the mantle-piece kind within our  
reach and inspection. For the same reason, we like a sniall study,  
where we are almost in contact with our books. We like to feel  
them about us, — to be in the arms of our mistress Philosophy, rather   
than see her at a distance. To have a huge apartment for a study  
is like lying in the great bed at <placeName key='Ware' corresp="England">Ware</placeName>, or being snug on a milestone  
upon <placeName key='Hounslow Heath' corresp="England">Hounslow Heath</placeName>. It is space and physical activity, not  
repose and concentration. It is fit only for grandeur and ostentation,  
— for those who have secretaries, and are to be approached like gods  
in a temple. The archbishop of <placeName key='Toledo'>Toledo</placeName>, no doubt, wrote his homilies  
in a room ninety feet long. The <persName key="Marquis Marialva">Marquis Marialva</persName> must have been  
approached by GU Bias through whole ranks of glittering authors,  
standing at due distance. But <persName key="Ariosto">Ariosto</persName>, whose mind could fly out of  
it's nest over all nature, wrote over the house he built, <q xml:lang="italian">"<placeName key='Parva'>Parva</placeName>, sed  
apta mihi"</q> — Small, but suited to me. However, it is to be observed,  
that he could not afford a larger. He was a Duodenarian, in that  
respect, like ourselves.  We do not know how our ideas of a study  	

<pb n="11"/>

might exparid With our walls. <persName key="Montaigne">Montaigne</persName>, who was <persName key="Montaigne">Montaigne</persName>  
"of that ilk,"" and lord of a great chateau, had a study "sixteen  
paces in diameter, with three noble and free prospects." He congratulates  
himself, at the same time, on it's circular figure, evidently  
from a feeling allied to the one in favour of smallness." The figure  
of my study," says he, "is round, and has no more flat (bare)  
wall, than what is taken up by my table and my chairs; so that the  
remaining parts of the circle present me with a view of all my books at  
once, set upon five degrees of shelves round about me." (Cotton's  
<persName key="Montaigne">Montaigne</persName>. B.3. Ch. 3.) A great prospect we hold to be a very disputable  
advantage, upon the same reasoning as before; but we like to have  
some green boughs about our windows, and to fancy ourselves as  
much as possible in the country when we are not there. Milton  
expressed a wish with regard to his study, extremely suitable to our  
present purpose. He would have the lamp in it seen; thus letting  
others into a share of his enjoyments, by the imagination of them.</p>

<cit><quote><lg><l>And let my lamp at midnight hour </l>
<l>Be seen in some high lonely tower. </l>
<l>Where I may oft outwatch the Bear </l>
<l>With thrice-great <persName key="Hermes">Hermes</persName>; or unsphere </l>
<l>The Spirit of <persName key="Plato">Plato</persName>, to unfold </l>
<l>What world or what vast regions hold </l>
<l>The immortal mind, that hath forsook </l>
<l>Her mansion in this fleshy nook. </l></lg></quote><note type="source"><bibl><author><persName key="John Milton">John Milton</persName></author>: <title>Il Penseroso</title></bibl></note></cit>

<p>There is a fine passionate burst of enthusiasm oh the subject of a 
study in <persName key="Fletcher">Fletcher</persName>'s play of the <bibl><title>Elder Brother</title>, <ref>Act. 1. Scene 2</ref></bibl>.</p>

<lg><l><placeName key='Sordid'>Sordid</placeName> and dunghill minds, composed of earth, </l>
<l>In that gross element fix all their happiness : </l>
<l>But purer spirits, purged and refined. </l>
<l>Shake off that clog of human frailty. Give me </l>
<l>Leave to enjoy myself. That place, that does </l>
<l><placeName key='Contain'>Contain</placeName> my books, the best companions, is </l>
<l>To me a glorious court, where hourly I </l>
<l>Converse with the old sages and philosophers; </l>
<l>And sometimes for variety, I confer </l>
<l>With kings and emperors, and weigh their counsels; </l>
<l>Calling their victories, if unjustly got. </l>
<l>Unto a strict account; and in my fancy. </l>
<l>Deface their ill-placed statues.  Can I then </l>
<l>Part with such constant pleasures, to embrace </l>
<l><placeName key='Uncertain'>Uncertain</placeName> vanities?  No : be it your care </l>
<l>To augment a heap of wealth : it shall be mine </l>
<l>To increase in knowledge. Lights there for my study! </l></lg>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2">
<head type="header" rend="center">ACONTIUS AND CYDIPPE,</head>
<head type="subheader" rend="center">A LOVE STORY IN THE ANTIENT WRITERS.</head>
<p>Acontius was a youth of the island <placeName key='Cea'>Cea</placeName> (now <placeName key='Zia'>Zia</placeName>), who at the  
sacrifices in honour of <persName key="Diana">Diana</persName> fell in love with this beautiful virgin,  
Cydippe; but she was unfortunately so much above him in rank,  
that he had no hope of obtaining her hand in the usual way The  

<pb n="12"/>

wit of a lover accordingly helped him to an expedient. There was  
a law in <placeName key='Cea'>Cea</placeName>, that any oath pronounced in the temple of <persName key="Diana">Diana</persName> was  
irrevocably binding. Acontius got an apple, and writing some words  
upon it; pitched it into Cydippe's bosom.</p>
<p>The words were these; — </p>

<q xml:lang="anc-Greek">MA THN APTEMIN AKONTIΩ ΓAMOΥMAI.</q>
<q>By Dian, I will marry Acontius. </q>

<p>Or as a poet has written them : </p>

<lg><l><persName key="Juro">Juro</persName> tibi sanctae per mystica sacra Dianse, </l>
<l>Me tibi venturam comitem, sponsamque futuram. </l></lg>

<lg xml:lang="en" type="hunt-translation"><l>I swear by holy Dian, I will be </l>
<l>Thy bride betrothed, and bear thee company. </l></lg>

<p>Cydippe read, and married herself. — It is said that she was repeatedly  
on the eve of being married to another person; but her imagination  
in the shape of the Goddess as often threw her into a fever;  
and the lover, whose ardour and ingenuity had made an impression  
upon her, was made happy. Aristaenetus in his <placeName key='Epistles'>Epistles</placeName> calls the  
apple <hi xml:lang="anc-Greek">Κνδωνιον μήλον</hi> a Cretan apple, which is supposed to mean a quince : or as others think, an orange, or a citron. But the apple was, is,  
and must be, a true, unsophisticated apple. Nothing else would  
have suited. "The apples, methought," says Sir Philip Sydney, of  
his heroine in the Arcadia, " fell down from the trees, to do homage   
to the apples of her breast.-' The idea seems to have originated with  
<persName key="Theocritus">Theocritus</persName>, (Idyl. 27- v. 50. Edit. Valckenaer.) from whom it was  
copied by the Italian writers. It makes a lovely figure in one of the  
most famous passages of <persName key="Ariosto">Ariosto</persName>, where he describes the beauty of  
Alcina (<placeName key='Orlando'>Orlando</placeName> Furioso, Canto 7- st. 14.) : — </p>

<lg xml:lang="it"> <l>Bianca neve e il bel collo, e'l petto latte: </l>
<l>II collo e tondo, il petto colmo e largo : </l> 
<l>Due pome acejbe, e pur d'avorio fatte, </l>
<l>Vengono e van come onda al primo margo, </l>
<l>Quando piacevole aura il mar combatte. </l></lg>

<lg xml:lang="en" type="hunt-translation"> <l>Her bosom is like milk, her neck like snow; </l>
<l>A rounded neck; a bosom, where you see </l>
<l>Two crisp young ivory apples come and go. </l>
<l>Like waves, that on the coast beat tenderly, </l> 
<l>When a sweet air is ruffling to and fro. </l></lg>

<p>And after him, <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>, in his fine ode on the Golden Age : — </p>

<lg xml:lang="it"><l><persName key="Allor">Allor</persName> tra fiori e linfe  </l>
<l><placeName key='Tracan'>Tracan</placeName> dolci carol e  </l>
<l>Gli Amoretti senz'archi e senza faci :  </l>
<l><placeName key='Tracan'>Tracan</placeName> tra fiori e linfe  </l>
<l>Meschiando a le parole  </l>
<l><persName key="Vezzi">Vezzi</persName> e susurri, ed ai susurri i baci  </l>
<l>Strettamente tenaci.  </l>
<l>La verginella ignude  </l>
<l><placeName key='Scopria'>Scopria</placeName> sue fresche rose  </l>
<l>Ch'or tien nel velo ascose,  </l>
<l>E le pome del seno acerbe e crude: </l> 
<l>E sperso o in fiume o in lago  </l>
<l>Scherzar si vide con <placeName key='Tamata'>Tamata</placeName> il vago. </l></lg>

<pb n="13"/>

<lg xml:lang="en" type="hunt-translation"><l>Then among streams and flowers. </l>
<l>The little Winged Povrers </l>
<l>Went singing carols, without torch or bow; </l>
<l>The nymphs and shepherds sat </l>
<l><persName key="Mingling">Mingling</persName> with innocent chat </l>
<l><persName key="Sports">Sports</persName> and low whispers, and with whispers low </l>
<l><persName key="Kisses">Kisses</persName> that would not go. </l>
<l>The maiden, budding oe'r. </l>
<l>Kept not her bloom uneyed, </l>
<l>Which now a veil must hide, </l>
<l>Nor the crisp apples which her bosom bore: </l>
<l>And oftentimes in river or in lake. </l>
<l>The lover and his love their merry bath would take. </l>
<l><persName key="Honi">Honi</persName> soit qui mal y pense. </l></lg>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3">
<head type="header">VENICE.</head> 

<p>This is the country of <persName key="Titian">Titian</persName>, of <persName key="Palladio">Palladio</persName>, of <persName key="Marcello">Marcello</persName>, who from  
a nobleman became one of the finest musicians in <placeName key='Italy'>Italy</placeName>; of <placeName key='Bembo'>Bembo</placeName>,  
one of the most liberal and accomplished of cardinals; of <persName key="Paul Sarpi">Paul Sarpi</persName>,  
who kept his countrymen independent of the church of Rome.</p>

<p>The Venetians are like a lively family cut oflf from the rest of  
<placeName key='Europe'>Europe</placeName>, Let the reader imagine himself pushing off from a sea-coast,  
and coming at a distance of a league and a half upon a city standing in  
the sea. This is <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName>. It is built upon seventy-two little islands,  
the houses abutting directly upon the water, the finest of them with-  
out even a landing place but the stairs; so that instead of streets  
there are only canals of sea- water; and instead of coaches and carts,  
gondolas and other boats. Perhaps the best idea the reader can  
have of a Venetian street is to imagine a street like <placeName key='Portland-place'>Portland-place</placeName>,  
or rather a more winding one like the <placeName key='High-street'>High-street</placeName> at <placeName key='Oxford'>Oxford</placeName>, mixed  
with nobler as well as smaller houses, and the full sea running through  
it, with abundance of boats of traffic and swift-darting gondolas.  
The gondola is a sort of wherry, about five feet broad, and twenty-  
five long, covered with black cloth, and having a cabin standing up  
in the middle of it, like the body of a caravan. The cabin is covered with  
black also, and has moveable windows with curtains A Venetian gentle-  
keeps his gondola as an <persName key="Englishman">Englishman</persName> does his coach; only with much  
greater cheapness. The full complement of a gondola is two rowers,  
who stand to their oars, one at each end, and with their faces the  
reverse way of our boatmen. They're very expert, and dart their  
gondolas in and out among the intricacies of this watery bustle, like  
fish. They are proverbial for their cheerfulness and honesty. They  
used to be famous for singing passages out of <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName> and other Italian  
poets; but political trouble has dashed the spirits even of the  
Venetian gondolier, and he is now comparatively mute.*<note type="hunt" place="foot">It is curious and natural enough, that one of their most favourite passages  
was the beginning of the seventh book of the Jerusalem Delivered, where <persName key="Errainia">Errainia</persName>  
gets among the country-people. They sang to a kind of chant, sometimes  
responding to each other; and the aflfect at night-time, when the sound came  
.softened by distance over the water, was often delightful. Rousseau, who was  
once at <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName>, published the chant in notes. We do not remember whether it is  
from him that <placeName key='Mr'>Mr</placeName>. <placeName key='Shield'>Shield</placeName> has copied it in the appendix to his Introduction to Har-  
mony; but it is there to be found. <persName key="Ariosto">Ariosto</persName> used to be the great favourite with  
the Venetians; but <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>'s poem seems to have superseded even the <placeName key='Orlando'>Orlando</placeName> in  
popularity. An Italian gentleman, when asked his opinion of this mystery,  
thought it explained by the great mixture of Turkish affairs in the Jerusalem,  
the Venetians having had a good deal to do with the Turks, both as enemies and  
friends. </note> The guitar 
<pb n="14"/>
however is still heard in <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName>, especially of an evening; and the  
visitor continually hears those delightful dancing airs which have  
been collected and published in this country. The chief, or rather  
the only place of assemblage for the inhabitants of <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName> out of  
doors (for they have a fine opera and multitudes of opera-houses  
within) is a large square, containing the principal church and the  
government offices. Here all ranks are accustomed to meet of an  
evening; and here something of amusement is generally going  
forward all day, from the guitar-player to the punchinelio. There is  
very little more standing-room throughout the city; and so little  
vegetation, that they call a court by way of eminence the Court of  
the Tree, and there is a church entitled our Lady of the Garden.  
There is a monastery with one of these gardens, such as they are;  
the Palace Zenobio has another, and a Casino,*<note type="hunt" place="foot"> Baretti defines one of these <persName key="Casinos">Casinos</persName> exactly. He calls it "a small house kept for pleasure in a town, besides our own." They are in great request at <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName>; more so now, we suppose than ever, since the nobility have shrunk in their pa-  
laces like withered nuts.</note> called Zanne, another.  
We suppose they muster up some others in miniature; but there  
is an island near <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName>, where the gentry have country-houses, and  
contrive to be a little more horticultural.</p>

<p>Next to it's watery streets, <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName> is remarkable for the number  
of it's bridges and palaces. The latter are truly so called, and  
comprise many of the master-pieces of <persName key="Palladio">Palladio</persName>. Every noble family  
appears to have once occupied a palace, some of them many palaces.  
They stand upon the principal canals, into which run smaller ones,  
all of them having their bridges. These bridges however are in  
general very small; nor is the famous one, called the <placeName key='Rialto'>Rialto</placeName>, so  
remarkable as it's celebrity would imply, though it is built in a strik-  
ing manner, of one arch. It has houses on it, like old <placeName key='London'>London</placeName> bridge,  
though not after the same fashion. They cross it in a covered angle,  
forming a double arcade. The artist who built it was called <persName key="Antonio">Antonio</persName>  
of the <placeName key='Bridge'>Bridge</placeName>. In the same spirit of poetical tendency, the bridge  
leading to the city jail is called the <placeName key='Bridge'>Bridge</placeName> of Sighs; and one of the  
principal canals, probably from the residence of some great musician,  
is entitled the <placeName key='River of Song'>River of Song</placeName>.</p>

<p>The Venetians have always been famous for their enjoying temper,  
and what the Italians call <persName key="Brio">Brio</persName>, — a certain sparkling of the animal  
spirits. A quintessence of this quality would seem to have been almost  
the only thing which made a late celebrated dramatist, <persName key="Goldoni">Goldoni</persName>,  
be taken all over <placeName key='Europe'>Europe</placeName> for a great genius. Yet the Venetian character  
in general is relieved from the frivolous by an evident capacity

<pb n="15"/>
for the serious. The wine in their blood has a body with it. There  
is a tone and substance in their composition as different from the old  
French levity, as <persName key="Titian">Titian</persName>'s pictures are from La Guerre. You still  
meet with <persName key="Titian">Titian</persName>'s men and women at <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName>, — the same rich dark  
complexions and fine figures; the same faces, earnest without sharp-  
ness, quick without confusion, thoughtful without severity, volup-  
tuous without grossness. The men are robust as well as agile : the  
women have that sort of tone in their composition which made the  
very courtezan of <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName> a Calypso to strangers, and enthroned the  
more sentimental mistress at the top of her sex, at once to fascinate  
and to rule.</p>

<p>The leading men in the state, the counsellors at law, etc. take ad-  
vantage of this solid part of the national character to affect a prodi-  
gious air of gravity: and it was perhaps from a mixed spirit of re-  
publican pride, and a sort of gusto of contrast to the pleasurability  
of their temperament, that black colours became the national wear.  
Not only the divines and lawyers wore black, but the statesmen wore  
black, the ladies all wore black; and the gondolas, carrying guitars  
and lovers in their bosoms, were clothed in the same external symbol  
of solemnity. We believe it is the same to this day, if not so uni-  
versally. There seems in this a kind of pleasant and avowed hypo-  
crisy, which stands the lively and sincere Venetian instead of the  
more hypocritical zests of other countries.</p>

<p><placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName> originated with fugitives from the Italian peninsula during  
the fierce time of <persName key="Attila">Attila</persName>, and subsisted afterwards as an independent  
state for many centuries, unbesieged even but by the waves. It's  
famous oligarchical form of government, under which it became  
mistress of the sea, still divides the opinions of politicians. Some  
think it must have been an intolerable tyranny; while others, among  
whom is our republican countryman <persName key="Harrington">Harrington</persName>, have regarded it  
as the true model of a popular state. The truth seems to be, that  
the good climate and chearful temperament enjoyed by the Vene-  
tians rendered them very easy subjects; and this easiness had it's  
effect in turn upon their leaders, who with all their outward stateli-  
ness were in reality like themselves. There was none of the physical  
suffering, which naturally renders the people so impatient in harder  
climates; and on the other hand, the rulers were generally wise and  
kind, and not provoked into tyranny either by conscious injustice,  
or extra-national ambition. The Venetians were too contented with  
what was done and allowed, to quarrel for the last, sad privilege of  
political talking; and provided a Venetian did not talk politics, he  
might talk or do any thing he pleased. Thus they were like a happy  
family living under a father of austere aspect and real goodnature.  
But as their less happy neighbours out-grew them, this happy family  
was to be disturbed; and it was so. <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName> in common with the  
other northern states of <placeName key='Italy'>Italy</placeName> became the property of the greatest  
neighbour for the time being, — of the <placeName key='Court of <placeName key='Vienna'>Vienna</placeName>'>Court of <placeName key='Vienna'>Vienna</placeName></placeName> first, then  
of <placeName key='France'>France</placeName>, and now of <placeName key='Vienna'>Vienna</placeName> again. It's nobles are at length  
ruined; it's palaces almost deserted; and the gay Venetian, now
<pb n="16"/>
a pensive animal to what he was, meditates on the approaching period  
when his very city is to be forsaken by the sea; when <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName> itself,  
eyeless, voiceless, and dead, is to stand like a gigantic skeleton on a  
stagnant and deserted shore, whistling with the screams of sea-fowl,  
and the disdainful rushing of the wind.</p>

<p>This apprehension now appears to be a good deal entertained.  
It was entertained also nearly forty years back, perhaps long before;  
and was understood to be disproved at that time. According to the  
systems, however, and calculations of modern philosophy, the sea-  
coasts all over the globe are in a constant state either of an accression  
or diminution of waters; and the imagination, in its gloomier mo-  
ments, may still contemplate the desolation of <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName>, approaching  
or far off.</p>

<p>Still the Venetians compared with most other people are a hap-  
py race. The blood runs quicker in their veins. They have more  
music, more freshness and easiness of life, more cordiality of  
intercourse. The good-natured philosopher still finds in <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName> the  
greatest mixture of liveliness and sentiment : the restless man of  
genius, impatient of the contradiction of his young hopes, still finds  
there something to admire and to love. If the Venetians have been  
thought to be of too amorous a disposition, they are acknowledged  
to be temperate in every other respect, and to make excellent parents  
and kinsfolk : and it is to be observed that in many of the cities of  
<placeName key='Italy'>Italy</placeName>, the proneness to love has gradually produced a state of opinion on  
those matters, less severe than in some other countries; so that they  
do not violate their consciences so much as might be supposed, and  
the guUt is of necessity diminished with the sense of it. A late tra-  
veller says, that the most striking thing after all, in <placeName key='Venice'>Venice</placeName>, is the  
extreme kindness and attentiveness of all ranks of people to one  
another. A young man going by with a burden begs his " good  
father" (any given old gentleman) to let him have way; and the good  
father in as unaffected a tone is happy to make way for his "son."  
It may be answered, considering the Venetian character, that this is  
but natural; and that the old gentleman does not, know whom he  
may be talking to. But these, we conceive, are evidences which the  
disputatious moralist would do better in letting alone.</p>
</div2>
                <div2 type="correspondents"> <!-- Publisher and printer information -->
                <p>[ As this publication is unstamped, it will not circulate by means of the  
                general post without a heavy expense. Persons in the country who  
                wish to become subscribers, should therefore order it of booksellers who  
                send weekly or monthly parcels to their respective places of residence.  
                The delay would be of little consequence with a work not containing  
                any thing of merely temporary interest. ] </p> 
                </div2>
<div2 type="colophon">
                <p>Orders received by the Booksellers, by the Newsmen, and by the Publisher, <persName type="real" key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName>, 19, Catherine-street, Strand.</p>
                <p>Printed by <persName type="real" key="<persName key="C. H. Reynell">C. H. Reynell</persName>"><persName key="C. H. Reynell">C. H. Reynell</persName></persName>, No. 45, Broad-street, Golden-square.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
  
