<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!-- Template Version 1.1 [FOR REFERENCE - DO NOT DELETE] -->
<!-- This template is intended to be used as a starting point for encoding a new text.
        It is not intended as a fixed structure, but rather collects some of the most common
        structural elements for convenience and uniformity. Please add/remove elements as
        necessary for your use case. -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <!-- File Description -->
        <fileDesc>
            <!-- Title of the work -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Indicator</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                    <surname>
                    Hunt</surname>, <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <p />
            </publicationStmt>

            <!-- Author information -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>
                        <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                        <surname>
                    Hunt</surname>, <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                    </author>
                    ,
                    <title>The Indicator</title>
                    <date when="1820-03-29">March
                    29th, 1820</date> <!-- The publication date of this issue ({Month} {Day}, {Year}) -->
                    <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Joseph
                    Appleyard</publisher> <!-- Publisher details if available -->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <!-- Encoding Description -->
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
            <p>
                Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers
                are
                included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
                preservation.
            </p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <!-- Profile Description -->
        <profileDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="issue" n="25">
                <pb n="193" /> <!-- Page beginning -->
                <div2 type="forematter"> <!-- Title, epigraph, and catalogue -->
                    <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
                    <epigraph>
                        <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
                        <l><persName key="And">And</persName> takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
                        <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
                        <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser"
                                ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055"
                                cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
                    </epigraph>
                    <head type="catalogue">No. XXV.—WEDNESDAY, March 29th, 1820.</head>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" n="1"> <!-- Header and content -->
                    <head type="header" rend="center"><persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>'s and <persName key="Farifax">Farifax</persName>'s <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName></head>
                    <note type="editorial"> Hunt's essay would prove influentially convincing enough
                        as to become the introduction to a subsequent 1851 edition of Thomas
                        <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>'s translation, <title>Godfrey of Bulloigne: Or, The Recovery of
                        Jerusalem</title>. </note>
                    <p>By far the best-known translation of the Jerusalem Delivered of
                        <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>, is <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>'s. It has appeared, and still appears, in editions
                        of all sizes; and is gathered as a matter of course into collections of
                        the <placeName key='British Poets'>British Poets</placeName>. The sole reason of this is, not that <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>
                        translated the work, but that his original was <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>. It is the name
                        of <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>, solely, that has carried him on from generation to generation,
                        like a corpse attached to the immortal spirit of the Italian, and making
                        it dull with the burden. </p>
                    <p>The re-publication, in various quarters, of the finer translation by
                        <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>, will doubtless help to detach one idea from the other; but as
                        <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>'s version has also been often reprinted of late, and as <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>
                        himself presents some difficulties in the way of popularity, a few
                        observations on the two works may not be useless in furthering the
                        public interests of poetry. </p>
                    <p><persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName> is a singular example of the popularity which a man may obtain by
                        taking up a great author to translate, with whom he has nothing in common,
                        and merely subserving to the worst taste of the times. Some readers put
                        faith in the imposture from the mere name of the original, some from a
                        deference to the translator's knowledge of Italian, some from the
                        recommendation of any living author who has talent in any thing, some from a
                        real wish to be acquainted with a great poet, some from national self-love,
                        some from indolence of various kinds, many from the habit of acquiescing in
                        any thing after their own fashion, and many more because the rest have done
                        so before them. Yet many of these, with whatever sincerity they have praised
                        the original author, would have thought no higher of him than of some middle
                        writers of their own country, as indeed has frequently been the case; and
                        others, who have undertaken to agree with the lovers of his native language
                        in their enthusiasm about his pathos and dignity, or his vivacity, naivete,
                        &amp;c. would have owned, if they had the courage, what <pb n="194" /> a
                        dull fellow they could not help thinking him. The rest, who really loved and
                        understood poetry, Italian or English, could only sit still and Wonder at
                        all this, preferring, at the risk of being thought foolish or pedantic, the
                        old obsolete translators of Shakspeare's time, when <q>our language,</q>
                        saith <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>, <q>was in <choice>
                                <corr>its</corr>
                                <sic>it's</sic>
                            </choice> rudiments.</q>
                        It was lucky however for this gentleman, that he had the period he wrote in
                        almost all to himself. There was not a single real poet surviving, except
                        Cowper.—Gray, Armstrong, Akenside, <persName key="Collins">Collins</persName>, Churchill,—every body was gone
                        who was likely to detect him publicly; and the age, in every respect, was
                        then in the fullness of <choice>
                            <corr>its</corr>
                            <sic>it's</sic>
                        </choice> poetical emptiness. The
                        French school was in <choice>
                            <corr>its</corr>
                            <sic>it's</sic>
                        </choice> last weedy exuberance.
                        The apprentices and their mistresses, in their pretty transparent Acrostic
                        masks, walked forth by hundreds to meet each other in Poet's Corner in the
                        magazines; and as nobody knew any thing about poetry, except that it had to
                        repeat <soCalled>ingenious</soCalled> common-places, to rhyme upon heart,
                        impart, love, prove, &amp;c., and to pause, as Pope did, upon the fourth and
                        fifth syllables, every body could write poetry, and admit it in others:
                        Pope, whose real merits they did not understand after all, was the greatest
                        poet that ever lived; next to him were Goldsmith, and <persName key="Collins">Collins</persName>, and Gray, the
                        two latter however very little understood; then, or perhaps before them, was
                        Dr. <persName key="Johnson">Johnson</persName>, whom our master at school gave us as a poetical model: then
                        came, in their respective circles, though at due distance, <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. Jenkins, <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>.
                        Tomkins, or <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. Hipkins, who wrote lines on the beautiful Miss Y. of
                        Bristol, or the charming Miss Z. of Fish Street Hill; and nothing was
                        wanting to make such a person as <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName> a great and popular writer with
                        these gentlemen and ladies, but that he should write a great quantity of
                        verses; which he accordingly did. That Dr. <persName key="Johnson">Johnson</persName> should speak a good word
                        for <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>, much less write a dedication for him, is not surprising;
                        though what a poet must he be, who goes to another to write a dedication for
                        him! <persName key="Johnson">Johnson</persName> was in the habit of writing dedications for those who were
                        conscious of not being good turners of a prose paragraph, and who wished to
                        approach the great with a proper one; and <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>, it seems, was among
                        these modest persons, though he did not scruple to approach <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName> and
                        Ariosto with his poetry. The dedication, which is to the late Queen, and
                        which expresses a wish that <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName> had lived in a happier time and
                        experienced from the descendants of the House of Este, <q>a more liberal and
                        potent patronage,</q> is elegant and to the purpose. The good word is a mere
                        word, and very equivocal besides. <persName key="Johnson">Johnson</persName>, who is now pretty generally
                        understood not to have been so good a critic in poetry as he was strong in
                        general understanding, and justly eminent in some respects, might have been
                        very capable of applauding a translation upon <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>'s principles; but it
                        is more than to be suspected, that he would have desired a higher order of
                        workmanship out of the manufactory. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName> was a pitch too low for his
                        admiration, though it appeared he had private qualities sufficient to secure
                        his good wishes; and even those, there is good reason to conclude, could not
                        have prevented a feeling of contempt for a translator of great poets, who
                        would come to him for a dedication. When Boswell, in one of his maudlin fits
                        of adulation, affected to consider something with Goldsmith's name to it as
                        supplied by the Doctor, the latter would not restrain his scorn; and said,
                        that Goldsmith would no more come to him for a paragraph, than he would to
                        be fed with a pap-spoon. <persName key="And">And</persName> it is curious to observe, aWfter all, how and
                        in what place <persName key="Johnson">Johnson</persName> has said his good word for our translator. It is at
                        the end of the Life of Waller, and amounts to this coy prophecy;—that
                        <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>'s work, <cit>
                            <q>after <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>'s translation, will not-soon be
                                reprinted.</q>
                            <note type="source">
                                <bibl xml:id="johnson_LivesOfPoets">
                                    <author>
                                        <forename>Samuel</forename>
                                        <surname><persName key="Johnson">Johnson</persName></surname>
                                    </author>
                        ,
        <title>Lives of the English Poets</title>, <biblScope>Chapter on
                        Waller</biblScope>
                                </bibl>. </note>
                        </cit></p>
                    <p><persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName> indeed, with superfluous ingenuity, has contrived to let us know,
                        by other means than his translation, how totally unfit he was for the task.
                        He came to it with an ignorance of all real poetry, that of his own country
                        not excepted. After telling us that <q><placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>'s
                            version is in stanzas that cannot be read with pleasure by the
                        generality
                            of those who have a taste for English poetry,</q>—that it is <q>irksome
                        in such a degree as to surmount curiosity, and more than counterbalance
                            all the beauty of expression and sentiment to be found in
                            that work,</q>—and that, as a proof of all this, <q>it appears scarcely
                        to
                            have been read at all,</q>—he adds, <q>I do not flatter myself that I
                        have
                            excelled <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>, except in my measure and versification, and even of
                        these the principal recommendation is that they are modern, and better
                        adapted to the ear of all readers of English poetry, except of the very
                            few who have acquired a taste for the phrases and cadences of those
                        times, when our verse, if not our language was in it's rudiments:</q> that
                        is to say, at the close of our very greatest age both in poetry and prose.
                        So little did <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName> know what he was about, either in poetry, or the
                        versification of it, that while in the course of his translation he was
                        elaborately doing or undoing something now and then, in order to mingle a
                        little of Dryden with Pope, he forgot, or was not aware, that Dryden himself
                        professed to have learnt part of his versification from <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>. </p>
                    <p>In our first <hi rend="smallcaps">Indicator</hi> we gave a specimen of the
                        way in which a common-place writer would translate Shakspeare, and melt down
                        his fine things into nothings. The reader might take that specimen alone, as
                        giving a full, true, and particular account of the merits of <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName> as a
                        translator of <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>. <persName key="And">And</persName> we will beg him still to keep it in mind, or to
                        refer to it, as saving us the necessity of many extracts; for it is not a
                        pleasant task to dwell upon the demerits of any body. We will just give a
                        comparative specimen or two of the old and modern version of <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>, and then
                        take our leave of <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>, to indulge ourselves with a few more words upon
                        <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName> and translation. </p>
                    <p>Edward <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName> led a life which a brother poet might envy. He was of a
                        distinguished family, the same as that of <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName> the Parliament General;
                        and having an estate of his own, and the greater estates of leisure and
                        genius, he passed the whole of his days at a seat in the Forest of
                        Knaresborough, in the bosom of his family, and in the cultivation of poetry.
                        He appears to have had all, and more than a poet wants,—tranquillity, a
                        fortune beyond competence, books, rural scenes, and an age that could
                        understand him. He flourished just at the close of that golden period, that
                        height and strong summer-time of <pb n="196" /> our poetry, when language,
                        wisdom, and imagination were alike at their noblest, and thoughts were
                        poured forth as profusely as words have been since. He was inclined to the
                        music of verse; and the age was full of music, of every species;—he was of a
                        romantic and most probably superstitious turn of mind<note type="hunt">He
                        wrote a treatise on Daemonology, which was founded on <q>occurrences in
                                his own family,</q> and is still somewhere in MS. If King James knew
                        this, it must have been an additional incitement to his patronage of the
                        Jerusalem, the second edition of which was printed at his desire.</note>;
                        and popular superstitions were still more in favour than during the
                        preceding era;—he had perhaps something of the indolence of a man of
                        fortune; and in the course of his Italian luxuries, he met with a poet,
                        whose tendencies were like his own, and who was great enough to render the
                        task of translation honourable as well as delightful. </p>
                    <p>He accordingly produced a version of <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>, which we do not say Is equal to
                        the original, or at all exempt from errors which a future translator (always
                        provided he is a poet too) may avoid; but which we nevertheless do not
                        hesitate to pronounce the completest translation, and most like it's
                        original, of any we have ever seen.—We will open our extracts with that
                        famous blast of the trumpet, which has been so echoed in all countries, and
                        which <persName key="Voltaire">Voltaire</persName> quotes to <choice>
                            <corr>show</corr>
                            <sic>shew</sic>
                        </choice> what the Italian
                        language can do in the way of grandeur. <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>Chiama gli abitator de l'ombre eterne </l>
                                    <l>Il ranco suon de la tartarea tromba,</l>
                                    <l><placeName key='Treman'>Treman</placeName> le spaziose atre caverne, </l>
                                    <l>E l'aer cieco a quel romor rimbomba: </l>
                                    <l>Nè sì stridendo mai da le superne </l>
                                    <l><persName key="Regioni">Regioni</persName> del cielo il folgor piomba: </l>
                                    <l>Nè sì scossa gia mai trema la terra, </l>
                                    <l>Quando i vapori in sen gravida serra. </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <bibl xml:id="tasso_Liberata">
                                    <author>
                                        <forename>Torquato</forename>
                                        <surname><persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName></surname>
                                    </author>
                        ,
        <title>La Gerusalemme Liberata</title>, <biblScope><persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>V,
                        stanza 3</biblScope>
                                </bibl>. </note>
                        </cit>
                        This is certainly nothing like the <q>tinsel</q> which Boileau ventured to
                        talk about; but <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName> would have made it so if he could. This is his
                        translation. He begins with making the trumpet convene the devils. It is
                        Pluto at Home,—or sending a court circular. <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>The trumpet now with hoarse resounding breath </l>
                                    <l><persName key="Convenes">Convenes</persName> the spirits in the shades of death; </l>
                                    <l>The hollow caverns tremble at the sound; </l>
                                    <l>The air re-echoes <hi rend="italic">to the noise around</hi>; </l>
                                    <l><hi rend="italic">Not louder terrors shake the distant pole</hi>
                        , </l>
                                    <l>When through the skies tlie rattling thunders roll; </l>
                                    <l>Not greater tremors heave the labouring earth, </l>
                                    <l>When vapours, pent within, <hi rend="italic">contend for
                        birth</hi>.</l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <bibl xml:id="tasso_Liberata_<persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>">
                                    <author>
                                        <forename>Torquato</forename>
                                        <surname><persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName></surname>
                                    </author>
                        ,
        <title>Jerusalem Delivered; An Heroic Poem</title>, translated by <editor>
                                        <forename>John</forename>
                                        <surname><persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName></surname>
                                    </editor>
                        ,
        <biblScope><persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>V, verse 17</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        .
</note>
                        </cit> <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>, though he translates the
                        concluding couplet rather from Virgil than <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>, lets loose a spirit worthy
                        of both poets. Observe the fine taste with which he has managed to preserve
                        the double rhymes, that make the original so resounding. <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>The drearie trumpet blew a dreadful blast, </l>
                                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> rombled through the lands and kingdomes under, </l>
                                    <l>Through wastness wide it roar'd, and hollowes vast, </l>
                                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> fill'd the deepe with horror, feare, and wonder; </l>
                                    <pb n="197" />
                                    <l>Not halfe so dreadful noise the tempests cast, </l>
                                    <l>That fall from skies with stormes of haile and thunder; </l>
                                    <l rend="indent">Nor half so lowd the whistling winds doe sing, </l>
                                    <l rend="indent">Broke from the earthen prisons of their king. </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <bibl xml:id="tasso_Liberata_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>">
                                    <author>
                                        <forename>Torquato</forename>
                                        <surname><persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName></surname>
                                    </author>
                        ,
        <title>Godfrey of Bulloigne, or the <placeName key='Recoverie of Jerusalem'>Recoverie of Jerusalem</placeName></title>,
                        translated by <editor>
                                        <forename>Edward</forename>
                                        <surname><placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName></surname>
                                    </editor>
                        ,
        <biblScope><persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>V, stanza 3</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        .
</note>
                        </cit> We must not, however, take tip our
                        room with the original Italian. The next passage we shall quote is a
                        celebrated one also, of a different description,—that of the angel
                        descending on Mount <placeName key='Lebanon'>Lebanon</placeName>;—but it is all the same to <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>. <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>Refulgent rays his beauteous locks enfold; </l>
                                    <l><persName key="White">White</persName> are his nimble wings, and edg'd with gold: </l>
                                    <l>With these through winds and clouds he cuts his way, </l>
                                    <l>Flies o'er the land, and skims along the sea. </l>
                                    <l>Thus stood the angelic power prepared for flight, </l>
                                    <l>Then instant darted from th' empyreal height; </l>
                                    <l>Direct to <placeName key='Lebanon'>Lebanon</placeName> his course he bent, </l>
                                    <l>There closed his plumes, and made his first descent. </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="tasso_Liberata_<persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>">
                                    <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>, <persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>, verse 107.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
                        This closing couplet is a sad misrepresentation of the original, where the
                        angel is described, on his first touch of the mountain, as balancing himself
                        on his wings. When <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName> takes leaves of his author, it is for want of
                        strength to accompany him; when <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName> does it, it is to lead you into some
                        beautiful corner of his own fancy. It is thus he renders the passage: <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>Of silver wings he tooke a shining paire, </l>
                                    <l>Fringed with gold, unwearied, nimble, swift; </l>
                                    <l>With these he parts the windes, the clouds, tge aire, </l>
                                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> over seas and earth himselfe doth lift: </l>
                                    <l>Thus clad he cut the spheares and circles faire, </l>
                                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> the pure skies with sacred feathers clift. </l>
                                    <l rend="indent">On <placeName key='Libanon'>Libanon</placeName> at first his foot he set, </l>
                                    <l rend="indent"><persName key="And">And</persName> shooke his wings with roarie May-dewes wet. </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberato_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>">
                                    <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>, <persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>, stanza 14.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
                        The most striking part of the beautiful choral stanza describing the <choice>
                            <corr>chanting</corr>
                            <sic>chaunting</sic>
                        </choice> of the army is
                        totally omitted in <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>'s version. We suppose he thought the remainder
                        sufficient, and so indeed his reader will think. <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>So pass the tuneful band with cadence sweet, </l>
                                    <l>The hollow vales the lengthened notes repeat; </l>
                                    <l>The winding caverns and the mountains high </l>
                                    <l>A thousand echoes to the sounds reply. </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberata_<persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>">
                                    <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>, <placeName key='Canto XI'>Canto XI</placeName>, verse 77.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
<lb />
<cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>Hither the armies went, and chanted shrill, </l>
                                    <l>That all the deepe and hollow dales resound; </l>
                                    <l>From hollow mounts and caves on every hill </l>
                                    <l>A thousand echoes also sung around; </l>
                                    <l>It seem'd some quire (that sung with art and skill) </l>
                                    <l><persName key="Dwelt">Dwelt</persName> on those savage dennes and shadie ground; </l>
                                    <l rend="indent">For oft resounded from the banks they heare </l>
                                    <l rend="indent">The name of <persName key="Christ">Christ</persName> and of his mother deare. </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberata_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>">
                                    <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>, <placeName key='Canto XI'>Canto XI</placeName>, stanza 11.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
                        Another specimen of <persName key="Mr">Mr</persName>. <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>, and we have done with him. It is his close of
                        the bird's song in book the sixteenth. <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>He ceas'd; th'approving choir with joy renew </l>
                                    <l>Their rapturous music, and their loves pursue. </l>
                                    <pb n="198" />
                                    <l>Again in pairs the cooing turtles bill, </l>
                                    <l>The feathered nations lake their amorous fill. </l>
                                    <l>The oak, the chaster laurel seems to yield </l>
                                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> all the leafy tenants of the field. </l>
                                    <l>The earth and streams one soul appears to move, </l>
                                    <l>All seem impregnate with the seeds of love. </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberata_<persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>">
                                    <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>, <placeName key='Canto XVI'>Canto XVI</placeName>, verse unspecified.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
                        Here is not the faintest resemblance of the intense though airy
                        voluptuousness of the original, The conclusion in particular is no more like
                        it, than a nursery-man's ledger is like the scent of his roses. But now hear
                        <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>. <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>He ceast; and as approoving all he spoke, </l>
                                    <l>The quire of birds their heavenly tunes renew; </l>
                                    <l>The turtles sighed, and sighs with kisses broke; </l>
                                    <l>The fowles to shades unseene, by paires, withdrew; </l>
                                    <l>It seem'd the laurel chaste and stubborne oak, </l>
                                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> all the gentle trees on earth that grew, </l>
                                    <l rend="indent">It seem'd the land, the sea, and heav'n above, </l>
                                    <l rend="indent">All breath'd out fancy sweet, and sigh'd out
                        love. </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberata_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>">
                                    <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>, <placeName key='Canto XVI'>Canto XVI</placeName>, stanza 16.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
                        This is even superior, we think, to the original. It is the quinta pars
                        nectaris, and makes the senses swim aside on their ovvn faintness. It is
                        like the perfection of a <choice>
                            <corr>crystal</corr>
                            <sic>chrystal</sic>
                        </choice> summer's day, made
                        a little languid with noon, and seeming to have a sparkling and airy
                        consciousness about it that vents itself in odorous whispers.</p>
                    <p>The reader will observe in the foregoing specimens of <persName key="Hoole">Hoole</persName>, how a
                        bad translator takes refuge from the real feelings of his author in
                        vagueness and cant phrases. As he has no feeling of his own, he
                        resorts, when any thing is mentioned, not to the thing itself, but to the
                        terms in which it has been mentioned by the writers with whom he is
                        most familiar. He does not translate his author's thoughts, but his
                        words; or rather, he attempts only to do even that; for on that very
                        account, he does neither. To feel either properly, is to feel both. </p>
                    <p>We are greatly tempted to make many more extracts from <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>; but we must
                        restrain ourselves. In further illustration of what we have said about the
                        lines which he has inserted of his own, or altered to his own ideas, and the
                        sympathy which he still keeps up with his author's feelings, we will just
                        refer to his calling Armida, when she sets off, the Syrians' <cit>
                            <q>night-ambling dame,</q>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="tasso_Liberata_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>"><persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>V, stanza 27.</ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>—to
                        the two lines in which he calls Sophionia in the hands of the malefactors a <cit>
                            <q>dumb
                            <seg type="incise">and</seg>
                            silver dove;</q>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberata_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>">
                                    <persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>I, stanza 26.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>—the
                        neighing of the horses, and clattering of arms, which, he says, <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l>Pursue the echo over dale and downe; </l>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberata_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>">
                                    <persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>, stanza 78.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
                        to the description of Armida in which, with a little over-mixture of
                        conceit, yet beautiful, he tells us, <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>The marble goddesse, set at <placeName key='Gnidos'>Gnidos</placeName> naked. </l>
                                    <l>She seem'd, were she uncloath'd, or that awaked; — </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberata_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>">
                                    <persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>V, stanza 29.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
                        and to the issuing forth of the devils (4. v. 18.) which as the stanza is
                        almost entirely his own as well as a fine one, and crowded with his
                        favourite love of daemonology, we shall quote entire:— <pb n="199" />
<cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>Before his words the tyrant ended had, </l>
                                    <l>The lesser devils arose with gastlie rore, </l>
                                    <l><persName key="And">And</persName> thronged foorth about the world to gad; </l>
                                    <l>Each land they filled, river, streame, and shore; </l>
                                    <l>The goblins, fairies, feends, and furies mad, </l>
                                    <l>Ranged in flowrie dales and mountains hore; </l>
                                    <l rend="indent"><persName key="And">And</persName> under every trembling leaf they sit, </l>
                                    <l rend="indent">Between the solid earth and walkin flit. </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberata_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>">
                                    <persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>V, stanza 18.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit></p>
                    <p>The faults of <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName> are partly his own, and partly those of the period then
                        commencing. They consist in too great a license of inversion; occasional
                        crampness and obscurity; an over tendency to contrast; and in a singular
                        fondness for occupying a line here and there either with epithets almost <choice>
                            <corr>synonymous</corr>
                            <sic>synonimous</sic>
                        </choice>, or with a marked
                        detail of nouns, which close his statnza like palisadoes; as for instance, <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>The soil was gentle, smooth, soft, delicate— </l>
                                    <l>With pitie, sadness, griefe, compassion, feare— </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note>
                                <ref target="#tasso_Liberata_<placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>">
                                    A paraphrased combination of two distinct lines from <persName key="Canto I">Canto I</persName>,
                        stanza 62, and <placeName key='Canto XI'>Canto XI</placeName>II, stanza 40, respectively.
                                </ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
                        Yet we aire not sure, whether this kind of repetition does not fall in
                        sometimes with a certain gentle and continuous beauty. It is clear, at any
                        rate, that the Italians, from a feeling of that sort, gave rise to it
                        themselves, though <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName> has carried it to an excess. Petrarch and his
                        followers sometimes heap a line with descriptive nouns or adjectives; and
                        that delightful wild fellow Pulci seems to take a pleasure even in repeating
                        a multitude of notes of interrogation, and beginning a whole stanza or more
                        with the same word. The over-tendency to contrast may also be traced to the
                        Italians, especially as Marino was now becoming admired in England, and
                        every body had not strength to resist his crowding syrens like Milton. The
                        other faults are perhaps owing to <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>'s having chosen to abide by the
                        stanza of the original; for not being so great a master of his native
                        language as Spenser, who with his additional line seemed to defy difficulty
                        in this respect, and too often to no purpose, he hampered himself with the
                        great recurrence of rhymes, which suits Italian much better than English. He
                        was also, though by no means the literal translator which Hume has made him,
                        naturally anxious in general to get the sense of his original into the same
                        compass, which hampered him farther; and the result of all this, joined no
                        doubt to a natural inferiority in his own genius, however true a one, is,
                        that he is not equal to his original in the easier part of his majesty,—in
                        livs clearness which is like that of an Italian atmosphere,—and in a certain
                        virgin sweetness, <q>casta melodies soalve;</q>—in short, he is inferior,
                        generally speaking, in simplicity.</p>
                    <p>But, on the other hand, he has great beauties. If he roughened the music of
                        <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName> a little, he stilt kept it music, and beautiful music;—some of his
                        stanzas indeed give the sweetness of the original with the still softer
                        sweetness of an echo; and he blew into the rest some noble organ-like notes,
                        which perhaps the original is too deficient in. He can be also quite as
                        stately and solemn in feeling;—he is as fervid in his devotion, as earnest
                        and full of ghastly apprehension in his supernatural agency, as wrapt up in
                        leafiness in his sylvan haunts, as luxuriant and alive to tangible shapes in
                        his voluptuousnes. H? feels the <pb n="200" /> elements and varieties of his
                        nature, like a true poet; and his translation has consequently this special
                        mark of all true poetry, translated or original,—that when the circumstances
                        in the story or description alter, it gives us a proper and pervading sense
                        of the alteration. The surfaces are not all coloured alike, as in a bad and
                        monotonous picture. We have no silken armour, as in Pope's eternal enamel;
                        nor iron silks, as in Chapman (who is perhaps the only other various
                        translator nevertheless); nor an everlasting taste of chips instead of
                        succulence, as in the Ariosto of Harrington. </p>
                    <p>We repeat, however, that the reader must not expect a perfect version in
                        <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>, much less at the outset. <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName> himself, in our opinion, does not
                        well warm you into his work till after several books; but set out resolutely
                        with him or his translator, or with both, get past some cold looking places,
                        and scratch through a few of <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>'s roughnesses and obscurities, and you
                        come upon a noble territory, full of the romantic and the sweet, of stately
                        and of lovely shapes, of woods, waters, and sunny pleasures,—with drearier
                        seclusions apart, and fields of sonorous battle. We do not wonder that
                        <persName key="Collins">Collins</persName> was fond of this author and his translator, since <persName key="Johnson">Johnson</persName> has told
                        us, in that piece of prose music of his, that <cit>
                            <q>he loved fairies, genii, and monsters,<seg type="incise">—that</seg>
                        he delighted to rove through the meanders of enchantment, to gaze on the
                        magnificence of golden palaces, and to repose by the waterfalls of Elysium.</q>
                            <note type="source">
                                <ref target="#johnson_LivesOfPoets"><persName key="Johnson">Johnson</persName>, Lives of the English
                        Poets, in the chapter on <persName key="Collins">Collins</persName>.</ref>
                            </note>
                        </cit>
                        <persName key="Collins">Collins</persName> has given <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName> a high and proud eulogy in his ode on the Popular
                        Superstitions of the <placeName key='Highlands'>Highlands</placeName>.—Speaking of <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName> he says, <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>How have I sat, when piped the pensive wind, </l>
                                    <l>To hear his harp by British <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName> strung, </l>
                                    <l>Prevailing poet! whose undoubting mind </l>
                                    <l>Believed the magic wonders which he sung;— </l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote>
                            <note type="source">
                                <bibl>
                                    <author>
                                        <forename>William</forename>
                                        <surname><persName key="Collins">Collins</persName></surname>
                                    </author>
                        ,
        <title>An Ode on the Popular Superstitions of the <placeName key='Highlands'>Highlands</placeName> of
                        <placeName key='Scotland'>Scotland</placeName>, Considered as the Subject of Poetry</title>
                                </bibl>
                        .
</note>
                        </cit> <persName key="And">And</persName> then he goes on in a strain of
                        softness and luxury, that seem irritated from the countryman he is praising.
                        Yet <persName key="Collins">Collins</persName>, be it observed, was an accomplished scholar, and quite
                        conversant with the merits of the original. Indeed that was one great cause
                        of his eulogy. Waller, who appears to have known Italian, and Dryden who
                        undoubtedly did so, were both great admirers of <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName>. Waller professed to
                        have <q>derived the harmony of his numbers</q> from him; and so did Dryden,
                        if a reported speech of his to the Duke of Buckingham is to be taken for
                        granted. He gives him high praise at any rate, and joins him with Spenser as <q>great
                        masters in our language.</q> But his greatest title to regard on the score
                        of authority comes from Milton, who when he borrowed from <persName key="Tasso">Tasso</persName>, took care
                        to look at <placeName key='Fairfax'>Fairfax</placeName> also, and to add now and then something from him by the
                        way. </p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="correspondents"> <!-- Appended notes to correspondents -->
                    <p>The Editor will be happy to take up both of the subjects mentioned by J. C.
                        He
                        had already intended to write upon the latter; and the other will fall in
                        excellently
                        with the spirit of his little work.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="colophon"> <!-- Publisher and printer information -->
                    <p>Orders received by the Newsmen, by the Booksellers, and by the Publisher,
                        <persName type="real" key="<persName key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName>"><persName key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName></persName>.</p>
                    <p>Printed by <persName type="real" key="<persName key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName>"><persName key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName></persName>, No. 19, Catherine-street, Strand,——Price 2d.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
  