<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <!-- File Description -->
    <fileDesc>
      <!-- Title of the work -->
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Indicator</title>
        <title type="subtitle">No. XL.— WEDNESDAY, JULY 12th, 1820.</title>
        <author>
                        <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                        <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                        <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                    </author>
      </titleStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>

      <!-- Author information -->
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>
                        <forename>James</forename> <forename>Henry</forename> <forename>Leigh</forename>
                        <surname>Hunt</surname>,
                        <date from="1784" to="1859">1784-1859</date>
                    </author>
          <title>The Indicator</title>
          <date when="1820-07-12">JULY 12th, 1820</date> <!-- The publication date of this issue ({Month} {Day}, {Year}) -->
          <pubPlace><settlement>London</settlement>, <country>England</country></pubPlace>
          <publisher>Joseph Appleyard</publisher> <!-- Publisher details if available -->
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <!-- Encoding Description -->
    <encodingDesc>
      <!-- Add any encoding information or guidelines here if applicable -->
      <p>
        Basic encoding, capturing relevant formatting and layout information. Page numbers are
        included for reference to the source only and are not intended to indicate precise
        preservation.
      </p>
    </encodingDesc>

    <!-- Profile Description -->
    <profileDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div1 type="issue" n="40">
        <pb n="313"/> <!-- Page beginning -->
        <div2 type="forematter"> <!-- Title, epigraph, and catalogue -->
          <head type="title">THE INDICATOR.</head>
          <epigraph>
            <l>There he arriving round about doth flie,</l>
            <l>And takes survey with busie, curious eye:</l>
            <l>Now this, now that, he tasteth tenderly.</l>
            <l><persName key="Edmund Spenser" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4352055" cert="high" type="real">SPENSER</persName>.</l>
          </epigraph>
          <head type="catalogue" rend="center">No. XL.<date when="1820-07-12"> —WEDNESDAY, July 12th, 1820</date>.</head>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" n="1"> <!-- Header and content -->
          <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">Superfine Breeding.</head>
           <p>There is an anecdote in 
           <bibl>
           <author>Aulus Gellius</author>
           (<title key="Noctes Atticae" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q660519">Noctes Atticæ</title>
            <ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/fr/search?q=Noctes+Atticæ"/>, 
            <biblScope>Lib. 10, Cap. 6</biblScope>,)</bibl> 
            which exhibits, we think, one of the highest instances of what may be called polite blackguardism that we ever remember to have read. The fastidionsness, self-will, and infinite resentment against a multitude of one's fellow-creatures for presuming to come in contact with one's own importance, are truly edifying: and to complete the lesson, this extraordinary specimen of the effect of superfine breeding and blood is handed down to us in the person of a lady. Her words might be thought to have been a bad joke; and bad enough it would have been; but the sense that was <choice><orig>shewn</orig><reg>shown</reg></choice> of them proves them to have been very gravely regarded.</p> 
<p><persName key="Claudia" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1097301" cert="high" type="real">Claudia</persName>, the daughter of <persName key="Appius Claudius Caecus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q297783" cert="high" type="real" xml:id="appius_claudius">Appius Cæcus</persName>, in coming away from a public spectacle, was much pressed and pushed about by the crowd; upon which she thus vented her impatience: — <cit><quote>"What should I have suffered now, and how much more should I have been squeezed and knocked about, if my brother <persName key="Publius Claudius Pulcher" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q435404" cert="high" type="real" xml:id="claudius">Publius Claudius</persName> had not had his ships destroyed in battle, with all that heap of men? I should have been absolutely jammed to death! Would to heaven my brother were alive again, and could go with another fleet to <placeName type="region" corresp="Italy" key="Sicily" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q4951156" cert="high" xml:id="sicily">Sicily</placeName>, and be the death of this host of people, who plague and pester one in this horrid manner!"</quote><note type="hunt" xml:lang="latin">"Quid me nunc factum esset, quantoque arctius pressiusque conflictata essem, si <persName ref="#claudius" type="real">P. Claudius</persName> frater meus navali prælio classem navium cum ingenti civium numero non perdidisset? certe quidem majore nunc copiâ populi oppressa intercidissem. Sed utinam, inquit, reviviscat frater, aliamque classem in <placeName key="Sicily" type="region" corresp="Italy" ref="#sicily" xml:lang="latin">Siciltam ducat</placeName>, atquestam multudinem perditum eat, quæ me male nunc miseram convexavit."</note></cit>
For these words, <cit><quote>"so wicked and so uncivic,"</quote><note type="source" xml:lang="latin">(tam improba ac tam incivilia)</note></cit> says good old <persName ref="#Gellius" type="real">Gellius</persName>, the <orgName key="aedile" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q205757" cert="high">Ædiles</orgName>, <persName cert="medium" key="Caius Fundanus" type="real">Caius Fundanus</persName> and <persName key="Tiberius Gracchus" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q212109" cert="medium" type="real">Tiberius Sempronius</persName>, got the lady fined in the sum of twenty-five thousand pounds brass. There is a long account in <persName key="Titus Livius" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2039" cert="high" type="real">Livy</persName> of the speech which they made to the people, in reply to the noble families that interceded for her. It is very indignant. <persName key="Claudia" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1097301" cert="high" type="real">Claudia</persName> herself confessed her words, and does not appear to have joined in the intercession. They are not related at such length by <persName key="Titus Livius" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2039" cert="high" type="real">Livy</persName>, as by <persName key="Aulus Gellius" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q294800" cert="high" type="real" xml:id="Gellius">Aulus Gellius</persName>. He
<pb n="314"/>
merely makes her wish that her brother were alive to take out another fleet. But he <choice><orig>shews</orig><reg>shows</reg></choice> his own sense of the ebullition by calling it a dreadful imprecation; and her rage was even more gratuitous according to his account, for he describes her as coming from the <choice><orig>shews</orig><reg>shows</reg></choice> in a chariot.</p> 
<p>Insolence and want of feeling appear to have been hereditary in this Appian family: which gives us also a strong sense of their want of capacity; otherwise a disgust at such manners must have been generated in some of the children. They were famous for opposing every popular law, and for having kept the <orgName key="House of Commons of the United Kingdom" ref="http://dbpedia.org/resource/House_of_Commons_of_the_United_Kingdom" cert="medium">Commons</orgName> as long as possible out of any share in public honours and government. The villain <persName ref="#appius_claudius">Appius Claudius</persName>, whose well-known story has lately been made still more familiar to the public by the tragedy of <persName key="James Sheridan Knowles" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q353538" cert="high" type="real">Mr. Knowles</persName>, was among <choice><orig>it's</orig><reg>its</reg></choice> ancestors. <persName ref="#appius_claudius">Appius Cæcus</persName>, or the Blind, the father of <persName key="Claudia" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1097301" cert="high" type="real">Claudia</persName>, though he constructed the celebrated Appian Way and otherwise benefited the city, was a very unpopular man, wilful, haughty, and lawless. He retained possession of the <orgName key="Roman censor" ref="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Roman_censor" cert="high">Censorship</orgName> beyond the limited period. It is an instance perhaps of his unpopularity, as well as of the superstition of the times, that having made a change in one of the priestly offices, and become blind some years afterwards, the Romans attributed it to the vengeance of heaven; an opinion which <persName key="Titus Livius" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2039" cert="high" type="real">Livy</persName> repeats with great devotion, calling it a warning against innovations in religion. It had no effect however upon <persName ref="#claudius">Claudius</persName> the brother, whose rashness furnished the pious Romans with a similar example to point at. Before an engagement with the Carthaginians, the <orgName key="Sacred Chickens" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augury">Sacred Chickens</orgName> were consulted, and because they would not peck and furnish him with a good omen, he ordered them to be thrown into the sea. "If they won't eat," said he, "let 'em drink." The engagement was one of the worst planned, and the worst fought in the world; but the men were avowedly dispirited by the Consul's irreverend behaviour to the chickens; and his impiety shared the disgrace with his folly. <persName key="Titus Livius" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2039" cert="high" type="real">Livy</persName> represents him as an epitome of all that was bad in his family; proud, stubborn, unmerciful though full of faults himself, and wilful and precipitate to a degree of madness. This was the battle, of which his sister wished to see a repetition. It cost the Romans many ships sunk, ninety-three taken, and according to the historian, the miraculous loss of eight thousand men killed and twenty thousand taken prisoners, while the Carthaginians lost not a ship or a man.</p>
</div2>
       <div2 type="section" n="2"> <!-- Header and content -->
          <head type="header" rend="center">Shaking Hands.</head>
          <p>
          Among the first things which we remember noticing in the manners of people, were two errors in the custom of shaking hands. Some we observed, grasped every body's hand alike, — with an equal fervour of gtip. You would have thought that <persName>Jenkins</persName> was the best friend they had in the world; but on succeeding to the squeeze, though a slight acquaintance, you found it equally flattering to yourself; and on the appearance of somebody else (whose name, if turned out, the operator 
<pb n="315"/> 
had forgotten,) the crush was no less complimentary: ––the face was as earnest and beaming, the "glad to see you" as syllabical and sincere, and the shake as close, as long, and as rejoicing, as if the semi-unknown was a friend come home from the <choice><orig>Desarts</orig><reg>Deserts</reg></choice>.</p> 
<p>On the other hand, there would be a gentleman now and then as coy of his hand, as if he were a prude or had a whitlow. It was in vain, that your pretensions did not go beyond the "civil salute" of the ordinary shake; or that being introduced to him in a friendly manner and expected to shake hands with the rest of the company, you could hot in decency omit his. His fingers, half coming out, and half retreating, seemed to think that you were going to do them a mischief; and when you got hold of them, the whole shake was on your side: the other hand did but proudly or pensively acquiesce, — there was no knowing which: you had to sustain it, as you might a lady's in handing her to a seat; and it was an equal perplexity to know how to shake or to let it go. The one seemed a violence dene to the patient; the other an <choice><orig>aukward</orig><reg>awkward</reg></choice> responsibility brought upon yourself. You did not know, all the evening, whether you were not an object of dislike to the person; till on the party's breaking up, you saw him behave like an equally ill-used gentleman, to all who practised the same unthinking civility.</p> 
<p>Both these errors, we think, might as well be avoided: but of the <choice><sic>too</sic><corr>two</corr></choice>, we must say we prefer the former. If it does not look so much like particular sincerity, it looks more like general kindness; and if those two virtues are to be separated, (which they assuredly need not be, if considered without spleen) the world can better afford to dispense with an unpleasant truth than a gratuitous humanity. Besides, it is more difficult to make sure of the one, than to practice the other; and kindness itself is the best of all truths. As long as we are sure of that, we are sure of something, and of something pleasant. It is always the best end, if not in every instance the most logical means.</p> 
<p>This manual shyness is sometimes attributed to modesty, but never, we suspect, with justice, unless it be that sort of modesty, whose fear of ommitting itself is grounded in pride. Want of address is a better reason, but this particular instance of it would be grounded in the same feeling. It always implies a habit either of pride or distrust. We have met with two really kind men, who evinced this soreness of hand. Neither of them perhaps thought himself inferior to any body about him, and both had good reason to think highly of themselves; but both had been sanguine men contradicted in their early hopes. There was a plot to meet the hand of one of them with a fish-slice, in order to <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> him the disadvantage to which he put his friends by that flat mode of salutation; but the conspirator had not the courage to do it. Whether he heard of the intention, we know not; but shortly afterwards he took very kindly to a shake. The other was tke only naan of a warm set of politicians, who remained true to his first love of mankind. He was impatient at the change of his companions and at the folly and inattention of the rest; but though his manner became cold, his consistency still remained warm; and this gave him a right to be as strange as he pleased.</p>
</div2>
<pb n="316"/>
<div2 type="section" n="3"> <!-- Header and content -->
          <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">On Receiving a Sprig of Laurel from  <placeName type="region" corresp="France" key="Vaucluse" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q12792" cert="high">Vaucluse</placeName>.</head>
          <p>
          And this piece of laurel is from <placeName type="region" corresp="France" key="Vaucluse" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q12792" cert="high">Vaucluse</placeName>! Perhaps <persName key="Francesco Petrarch" cert="high" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1401" type="real">Petrarch</persName>, perhaps <persName key="Laura de Noves" cert="medium" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q270227" type="real">Laura</persName>, sat under it! This is a true present. What an exquisite dry old, vital, young-looking, everlasting twig it is! It has been plucked nine months, and looks as hale and as crisp as if it would last ninety years. It shall last at any rate as long as <choice><orig>it's</orig><reg>its</reg></choice> owner, and longer, if care and love can preserve it. How beautifully it is turned ! It was a happy pull from the tree. <choice><orig>It's</orig><reg>Its</reg></choice> shape is the very line of hcauty; it has berries upon it, as if resolved to <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> us in what fine condition the trees are; while the leaves issue from it, and swerve upwards with their elegant points, as though they had come from adorning the poet's head. Be thou among the best of one's keepsakes, thou gentle stem, — in <hi rend="italic" xml:lang="latin">deliciis nostris</hi>; — and may the very maid-servant who wonders to see thy withered beauty in <choice><orig>it's</orig><reg>its</reg></choice> frame, miss her lover the next five weeks, for not having the instinct to know that thou must have something to do with love.</p> 
<p>Perhaps <persName key="Francesco Petrarch" cert="high" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1401" type="real">Petrarch</persName> has felt the old ancestral boughs of this branch, stretching over his head, and whispering to him of the name of <persName key="Laura de Noves" cert="medium" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q270227" type="real">Laura</persName>, of his love, and of their future glory; for all these ideas used to be entwined in one. <bibl><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Il_Canzoniere"/>(<ref corresp="#sestina2verse1">Sestina 2</ref>, Canzone 17, Sonetti 162, 163, 164, 207, 224, <choice><orig>&amp;c.</orig><reg>etc.</reg></choice>)</bibl> Perhaps it is of the very stock of that bough, which he describes as supplying his mistress with a leaning-stock when she sat in her favourite bower. (See the translation at the end.)</p> 
<cit>
<quote>
<lg xml:lang="it" rend="center" xml:id="sestina2verse1" corresp="#translation">
<l>Giovane donna sotto un verde lauro</l>
<l>Vidi più bianca e più fredda che neve</l>
<l>Non percossa dal sol molti e molt' anni:</l>
<l>E'l suo parlar, e'l bel viso, e le chiome.</l>
<l>Mi piacquer si, ch' i' l'ho a gli occhi</l>
<l>Ed avrò sempre, ov'io sia in poggio o'n riva.</l>
<l rend="right"><bibl>Vol. I , Sestina 2.</bibl></l>
</lg>
</quote>
<note type="source"><bibl><author>Francesco Petrarch</author><title>Il Canzoniere</title><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Il_Canzoniere"/>Vol. I , Sestina 2.</bibl></note> 
</cit>

<lg xml:lang="en" rend="center" type="translation-hunt" corresp="#sestina2verse1" xml:id="translation">
<l>A youthful lady under a green laurel</l> 
<l>I saw, more fair and colder than white snows</l> 
<l>Unshone upon for many and many a year:</l> 
<l>And her sweet looks, and hair, and way of speaking,</l> 
<l>So pleased me, that I have her now before me,</l> 
<l>And shall have, ever, whether on hill or lea.</l> 
</lg>
<p>The laurel seems more appropriated to <persName key="Francesco Petrarch" cert="high" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1401" type="real">Petrarch</persName> than to any other poet. He delighted to sit under <choice><orig>it's</orig><reg>its</reg></choice> leaves; he loved it both for itself, and for the resemblance of <choice><orig>it's</orig><reg>its</reg></choice> name to that of his mistress; he wrote of it continually; and he was called from out of <choice><orig>it's</orig><reg>its</reg></choice> shade, to be crowned with it in the Capitol. It is a remarkable instance of the fondness with which he cherished the united ideas of <persName key="Laura de Noves" cert="medium" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q270227" type="real">Laura</persName> and the laurel, that he confesses it to have been one of the greatest delights he experienced in receiving the crown upon his head.</p> 
<p>It was out of <placeName type="region" corresp="France" key="Vaucluse" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q12792" cert="high" xml:id="Vaucluse">Vaucluse</placeName> that he was called. <placeName type="region" corresp="France" key="Vaucluse" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q12792" cert="high">Vaucluse</placeName>, <placeName type="region" corresp="Italy" key="Valchiusa" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q59770834">Valchiusa</placeName>, the Shut Valley, (from which the French, in the modern enthusiasm for intellect, gave the name to the department in which it lies), is a remarkable spot in the old poetical region of <placeName type="region" corresp="France" key="Provence" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q101081">Provence</placeName>, consisting of a little deep glen of green meadows surrounded with rocks, and containing the fountain of the river <placeName type="physical" corresp="France" key="Sorgue(river)" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q688959">Sorgue</placeName>. <persName key="Francesco Petrarch" cert="high" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1401" type="real">Petrarch</persName>, when a boy of eight or 
<pb n="317"/>
nine years of age, had been struck with <choice><orig>it's</orig><reg>its</reg></choice> beauty, and exclaimed that it was the place of all others he should like io live in, better than the most splendid cities. He resided there afterwards for several years, and composed in it the greater part of his poems. Indeed, he says in his own account of himself, that he either wrote or conceived in that valley almost every work he produced. He lived in a little cottage with a small homestead, on the banks of the river. Here he thought to forget his passion for <persName key="Laura de Noves" cert="medium" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q270227" type="real">Laura</persName>, and here he found it stronger than ever. We do not well see how it could have been otherwise; for <persName key="Laura de Noves" cert="medium" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q270227" type="real">Laura</persName> lived no great way off, at Chabrieres: and he appears to have seen her often in the very place. He paced along the river; he sat under the trees; he climbed the mountains; but Love, he says, was ever by his side,</p> 
<cit>
<quote>
<l xml:lang="it" rend="center" xml:id="verse" corresp="#verse-trans">
Regionando con meco, ed io con lui.
</l>
</quote>
</cit> 
<l xml:lang="en" rend="center" corresp="#verse" xml:id="verse-trans">
He bolding talk with me, and I with him.
</l> 
<p>We are supposing that all our readers are acquainted with <persName key="Francesco Petrarch" cert="high" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1401" type="real">Petrarch</persName>. Many of them doubtless know him intimately. Should any of them want an introduction to him, how should we speak of him in the gross? We should say, that he was one of the finest gentlemen and greatest scholars that ever lived; that he was a writer who flourished in Italy in the 14th century at the time when Chaucer was young, during the reigns of our Edwards; that he was the greatest light of his age; that although so fine a writer himself, and the author of a multitude of works, or rather because he was both, he took the greatest pains to revive the knowledge of the ancient learning, recommending it every where, and copying out large manuscripts with his own hand; that two great cities, Paris and Rome, contended which should have the honour of crowning him; that he was crowned publicly, in the Metropolis of the World, with laurel and with myrtle; that he was the friend of Boccaccio, the Father of Italian Prose; and lastly, that his greatest renown nevertheless, as well as the predominant feelings of his existence, arose from the long love he bore for a lady of Avignon, the far-famed <persName key="Laura de Noves" cert="high" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q270227" type="real">Laura</persName>, whom he fell in love with on the 6th of April, 1327, on a Good Friday; whom be rendered illustrious in a multitude of sonnets, which have left a sweet sound and sentiment in the ear of all after lovers; and who died, still passionately beloved, in the year 1348, on the same day and hour on which he first beheld her. Who she was, or why their connexion was not closer, remains a mystery. But that she was a real person, and that in spite of all her modesty she did not <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> an insensible countenance to his passion, is clear from his long-haunted imagination, from his own repeated accounts, from all that he wrote, uttered, and thought. One love, and one poet, sufficed to give the whole civilized world a sense of delicacy in desire, of the abundant riches to be found in one single idea, and of the going out of a man's self to dwell in the soul and happiness of another, which has served to refine the passion for all modern times; and perhaps will do so, as long as love renews the world.</p> 
<p>By way of completing this ebullition on <persName key="Francesco Petrarch" cert="high" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1401" type="real">Petrarch</persName>, which has been unexpectedly excited in us, (for we intended to devote a longer 
<pb n="318"/>
and perhaps a duller article to him by and by), we will conclude it with a translation his most celebrated canzone, which was addressed to the river <placeName type="physical" corresp="France" key="Sorgue(river)" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q688959">Sorgue</placeName> and <choice><orig>it's</orig><reg>its</reg></choice> bowers. It has appeared before, though not in a place so suitable as the present; and as we have been asked to re-print it, before we ever thought of doing so, we repeat it with the less scruple. It is the 14th Canzone, Vol. 1., beginning,</p> 
<l xml:lang="it" rend="center">CHIARE, FRESCHE, E DOLCE ACQUE.</l>
<lg xml:lang="en" type="hunt-translation" xml:id="Canzone14" rend="center">
  <lg xml:id="verse1"> 
  <l>Clear, fresh, and dulcet streams,</l> 
  <l>Which the fair shape, who seems</l> 
  <l>To me sole woman, haunted at noon-tide;</l>
  <l>Bough, gently interknit,</l>
  <l>(I sigh to think of it)</l>
  <l>Which formed a rustic chair for her sweet side;</l>
  <l>And turf, and flowers bright-eyed,</l>
  <l>O'er which her folded gown</l>
  <l>Flowed like an angel's down;</l> 
  <l>And you, O holy air and hush'd.</l>
  <l>Where first my heart at her sweet glances gush'd;</l>
  <l>Give ear, give ear, with one consenting,</l>
  <l>To my last words, my last and my lamenting.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg xml:id="verse2">
  <l>If 'tis my fate below,</l> 
  <l>And heaven will have it so.</l> 
  <l>That love must close these dying eyes in tears.</l> 
  <l>May my poor dust be laid</l> 
  <l>In middle of your shade,</l> 
  <l>While my soul, naked, mounts to <choice><orig>it's</orig><reg>its</reg></choice> own spheres.</l>
  <l>The thought would calm my fears,</l> 
  <l>When taking, out of breath,</l> 
  <l>The doubtful step of death;</l> 
  <l>For never could my spirit find</l> 
  <l>A stiller port after the stormy wind;</l> 
  <l>Nor in more calm, abstracted bourne,</l> 
  <l>Slip from my travailled flesh, and from my bones out-worn.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg xml:id="verse3"> 
  <l>Perhaps, some future hour,</l>
  <l>To her accustomed bower</l> 
  <l>Might come the untamed, and yet the gentle she;</l>
  <l>Aud where she saw me first,</l>
  <l>Might turn with eyes athirst</l> 
  <l>Aud kinder joy to look again for me;</l>
  <l>Then, Oh the charity!</l>
  <l>Seeing <choice><orig>betwixt</orig><reg>between</reg></choice> the stones</l>
  <l>The earth that held my bones,</l>
  <l>A sigh for very love at last</l>
  <l>Might ask of heaven to pardon me the past:</l>
  <l>And heaven itself could not say nay,</l>
  <l>As with her gentle veil she wiped the tears away.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg xml:id="verse4"> 
  <l>How well I call to mind,</l> 
  <l>When from those boughs the wind</l> 
  <l>Shook down upon her bosom flower on flower;</l>
  <l>And there she sat, meek-eyed,</l> 
  <l>In midst of all that pride,</l> 
  <l>Sprinkled and blushing through an amorous shower,</l> 
  <l>Some to her hair paid dower,</l> 
  <l>And seemed to dress the curls,</l> 
  <l>Queenlike, with gold and pearls;</l> 
  <l>Some, snowing, on her drapery stopp'd,</l> 
  <l>Some on the earth, some on the water dropp'd;</l> 
  <l>While others, fluttering from above,</l> 
  <l>Seemed wheeling round in pomp, and saying "Here reigns Love."</l> 
  </lg>
  <pb n="319"/>
  <lg xml:id="verse5">
  <l>How often then I said.</l> 
  <l>Inward, and fill'd with dread,</l>
  <l>––"Doubtless this creature came from Paradise!"</l>
  <l>For at her look the while,</l> 
  <l>Her voice, and her sweet smile,</l> 
  <l>And heavenly air, truth parted from mine eyes;</l> 
  <l>So that, with long-drawn sighs,</l> 
  <l>I said, as far from men,</l> 
  <l>"How came I here, and when!"</l> 
  <l>I had forgotten; and alas,</l> 
  <l>Fancied myself in heav'n, not where I was;</l>
  <l>And from that time till this, I bear</l> 
  <l>Such love for the green Bower, I cannot rest elsewhere.</l>
  </lg>
 </lg>

      </div2> 
           <div2 type="correspondents">
                    <head type="title" rend="center uppercase">A True Story.</head>
                    <head type="header" rend="center uppercase">To the Indicator.</head>
                    <p>
                    Sir, — When I was a young boy, I had delicate health, and was somewhat of a pensive and contemplative turn of mind: it was my delight in the long summer evenings to slip away from my noisy and more robust companions, that I might walk in the shade of a venerable wood, my favourite haunt, and listen to the cawing of the old rooks, who seemed as fond of this retreat as I was.</p> 
<p>One evening I sat later than usual, though the distant sound of the cathedral clock had more than once warned me to my home. There was a stillness in all nature that I was unwilling to disturb by the least motion. From this reverie I was suddenly startled by the sight of a tall slender female who was standing by me, looking sorrowfully and steadily in my face. She was dressed in white, from head to foot, in a fashion I had never seen before; her garments were unusually long and flowing, and rustled as she glided through the low shrubs near me as if they were made of the richest silk. My heart beat as if I was dying, and I knew not that I could have stirred from the spot; but she seemed so very mild and beautiful, I did not attempt it. Her pale brown hair was braided round her head, but there were some locks that strayed upon her neck; and altogether she looked like a lovely picture, but not like a living woman. I closed my eyes forcibly with my hands, and when I looked again she had vanished.</p> 
<p>I cannot exactly say why I did not on my return speak of this beautiful appearance, nor why, with a strange mixture of hope and fear, I went again and again to the same spot that I might see her. She always came, and often in the storm and plashing rain, that never seemed to touch or to annoy her, and looked sweetly at me, and silently passed on; and though she was so near to me, that once the wind lifted those light straying locks, and I felt them against my cheek, yet I never could move or speak to her. I fell ill; and when I recovered, my mother closely questioned me of the tall lady, of whom, in the height of my fever, I had so often spoken.</p> 
<p>I cannot tell you what a weight was taken from my boyish spirits, when I learnt that this was no apparition, but a most lovely woman; 
<pb n="320"/>
not young, though ahe had kept her young looks, for the grief which had broken hor heart seemed to have spared her beauty.</p> 
<p>When the rebel troops were retreating after their total defeat, in that very wood I was so fond of, a young officer, unable any longer to endure the anguish of his wounds, sunk from his horse, and laid himself down to die. He was found there by the daughter of <persName key="Sir Henry R" type="fictional" xml:id="SirHenryR">Sir Henry R––––</persName>, and conveyed by a trusty domestic to her father's mansion. <persName key="Sir Henry R" type="fictional" ref="#SirHenryR">Sir Henry</persName> was a loyalist; but the officer's desperate condition excited his compassion, and his many wounds spoke a language a brave man could not misunderstand. <persName key="Sir Henry R" type="fictional" ref="#SirHenryR">Sir Henry</persName>'s daughter with many tears pleaded for him, and pronounced that he should be carefully and secretly attended. And well she kept that promise, for she waited upon him (her mother being long dead) for many weeks, and anxiously watched for the first opening of eyes, that, languid as he was, looked brightly and gratefully upon his young nurse.</p> 
<p>You may fancy better than I can tell you, as he slowly recovered, all the moments that were spent in reading, and low-voiced singing, and gentle playing on the lute, and how many fresh flowers were brought to one whose wounded limbs would not bear him to gather them for himself, and how calmly the days glided on in the blessedness of returning health, and in that sweet silence so carefully enjoined him. I will pass by this to speak of one day, which, brighter and pleasanter than others, did not seem more bright or more lovely than the looks of the young maiden, as she gaily spoke of "a little festival which (though it must bear an unworthier name) she meant really to give in honour of her guest's recovery;" "and it is time, lady," said he, "for that guest so tended and so honoured, to tell you his whole story, and speak to you of one who will help him to thank you: may I ask you, fair lady, to write a little billet for me, which even in these times of danger I may find some means to forward?" To his mother, no doubt, she thought, as with light steps and a lighter heart she seated herself by his couch, and smilingly bade him dictate; but, when he said. "My dear wife," and lifted up his eyes to be asked for more, he saw before him a pale statue, that gave him one look of utter despair, and fell, for he had no power to help her, heavily at his feet. Those eyes never truly reflected the pure soul again, or answered by answering looks the fond enquiries of her poor old father. She lived to be as I saw her, – sweet and gentle, and delicate always; but reason returned no more. She visited till the day of her death the spot where she first saw that young soldier, and dressed herself in the very clothes that he said so well became her.</p><signed rend="right">Δ.</signed>
                    </div2>
        <div2 type="colophon"> <!-- Publisher and printer information -->
        <p>Printed and published by <hi rend="smallcaps"><persName type="real" key="Joseph Appleyard">Joseph Appleyard</persName></hi>, No. 19, Catherine-street, Strand. 
            Price 2d. — And sold also by <hi rend="smallcaps"><orgName cert="low">A. Gliddon</orgName></hi>, Importer of Snuffs, No. 31, Tavistock-street, Covent-garden. Orders received at the above places, and by all Booksellers and Newsmen.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
